<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Practical reflections on the late earthquakes in Jamaica, England, Sicily, Malta, &amp;c., anno 1692 with a particular, historical account of those, and divers other earthquakes / by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 239 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31944</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277845</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12277845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1515:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Practical reflections on the late earthquakes in Jamaica, England, Sicily, Malta, &amp;c., anno 1692 with a particular, historical account of those, and divers other earthquakes / by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xvi, 206 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ... ad Abraham Chandler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCIII [1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Wrath.</term>
               <term>Earthquakes.</term>
               <term>Fear of God.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58544:1"/>
            <p>PRACTICAL REFLECTIONS On the Late <hi>Earthquakes</hi> IN <hi>Jamaica, England, Sicily, Malta,</hi> &amp;c. Anno 1692.</p>
            <p>With a Particular, Hiſtorical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe, and divers other EARTHQUAKES.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury</hi> at the Riſing Sun in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and <hi>Abraham Chandler</hi> at the Chirurgion's Arms in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet.</hi> MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58544:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:58544:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE late <hi>Earthquakes</hi> abroad in <hi>America,</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> with <hi>that</hi> we had here last <hi>September,</hi> made ſo much Diſcourſe amongst all ſorts of People, that I endeavoured the ſerious Improvement of 'em, in a <hi>Sermon</hi> on that Occaſion; which at the Deſire of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, is now enlarged, with many Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Paſſages of <hi>other Earthquakes,</hi> and moral Reflections relating to our own Countrey.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Authors</hi> I have cited, I have conſulted the <hi>Originals</hi> as to the most of
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:58544:3"/>'em; and am well ſatisfied of the Truth of thoſe few Others, which I had not the Leiſure, or Opportunity to look into. In ſome <hi>Chronological Differences</hi> between <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> I have mentioned that Year, which I thought the moſt <hi>Probable:</hi> but if the Matter of Fact be truly related, though I ſhould miſtake the Year, the Reader is not much concerned. <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically</hi> to diſcuſs the Nature of <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,</hi> many Others (whom I need not name) have attempted: Such a Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning the late Extraordinary one in <hi>Sicily,</hi> I am inform'd we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſhortly from the Learned <hi>Malpig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot wonder if the Concerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>the Heathen World,</hi> upon any ſuch violent Motions of the Earth, did degenerate into <hi>Superſtition.</hi> Owning a Multiplicity of Gods, they knew not to which of 'em to aſcribe ſuch Events; and therefore we read of the <hi>Ancient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that upon thoſe Occaſions, they never addreſs'd their Prayers and Vows to <hi>any one particular Deity,</hi> as in other
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:58544:3"/>Caſes they were wont to do, leſt (ſaith
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Quoniam &amp; quâ vi, &amp; per quem Deorum, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumve Terra tremuit, incertum eſſet.</hi> Aul. Gell. Noct. Art. <hi>l. 2. c. 28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Varro</hi>) they ſhould miſtake; becauſe they knew not by whoſe Influence the Earth was ſhaken. To that <hi>Modeſty</hi> or <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> we may oppoſe the <hi>Vanity</hi> of the <hi>Greeks;</hi> who boaſted they could <hi>foretel Earthquakes,</hi> as is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have been done by
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Diog. Laert. in Vit. Pherec.</hi> See more Inſtances: <hi>La Mothe le Vayer,</hi> Lett. <hi>LXXV. des Trembl. de Terre.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pherecydes,</hi> the Maſter of <hi>Pythagoras.</hi> But when Earthquakes happened, they were all wont to quit their
<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Anno 3861. Crebris Terrae motibus undique nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatis, tam multae ſunt indictae Feriae</hi> Romae, <hi>ad placan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos Coeleſtes, ut nec Senatus haberi, nec adminiſtrari Reſpublica poſſet, Conſulibus Sacrificando, Expiando<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> occupatis.</hi> Lefcoloper <hi>in</hi> Ciceron. <hi>p. 229. Imperante Gordiano tertio, fuit Terrae motus eouſque gravis, ut Civitates etiam Terrae hiatu cum Populis deperitent: ob quae Sacrificia per totam Urbem totum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> orbem Terrarum ingentia celebrata ſunt.</hi> Hiſtor. Auguſt. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptores. Jul. Capitol. <hi>Gordianus tertius,</hi> Tom. <hi>2. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </note> Civil and Common Affairs, and betake themſelves to their <hi>Devotions,</hi> and by <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to appeaſe the Anger of the <hi>Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:58544:4"/>
            <p>Concerning the late Earthquakes in <hi>Sicily,</hi> it hath been obſerv'd, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">Preſent State of <hi>Europe,</hi> March <hi>1693. p. 86.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina</hi> received leſs Damage than ſome other Cities. The People in that Country be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> the <hi>Monks</hi> made advantage of their Simplicity, and ſpread abroad a Report at the time of the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, that the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> had revealed to a young Girl of nine Years old, (her particular Favourite) that by means of her Interceſſion, ſhe had obtain'd, that the City of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> which is under her Protection, ſhould not be ſwallowed up: This for a little while ſomewhat reviv'd their Spirits. But the Interceſſion of <hi>S. Agatha</hi> could not procure the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for the City of <hi>Catanea,</hi> whereof ſhe is <hi>Patroneſs.</hi> For when the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake began, the People flew to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral, where one of the Canons carried about <hi>the Relicks of the Saint:</hi> But neither the <hi>Relicks,</hi> nor the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the <hi>Saint,</hi> could ſtop the Thunderbolt which fell upon that City; but it was
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:58544:4"/>overturn'd as in a Moment, and not one Houſe left ſtanding. And beſides wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and maimed that were digg'd out of the Ruines, eighteen Thouſand are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have periſhed there. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples</hi> hath had a Share in that Earthquake, as well as the Iſland of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our great Difficulty in reflecting on ſuch Providences, will be to avoid the <hi>two Extreams,</hi> of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Superſtition</hi> on the other; not to make <hi>too little,</hi> or <hi>too much</hi> of ſuch Events; not to overlook the Divine Agency, and Warning thereby, as if they had no meaning; nor on the other hand, to be bold, and poſitive, and particular in determining what they ſignify, and what we may expect to follow. I have given divers Inſtances of other publick Calamities which have been preceded by <hi>Earthquakes.</hi> If National Repentance, and Reformation do not prevent it, we have reaſon to expect ſuch, from <hi>moral Prognoſtications,</hi> had we no ſuch Call, as by <hi>the late Earthquakes,</hi> to conſider our Ways.</p>
            <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:58544:5"/>
            <p>Few, we may fear, do practically Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg God's Government, and own his Agency in theſe things. The moſt are <hi>Confident,</hi> and <hi>Careleſs,</hi> as if they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried nothing in them either of <hi>Preſage,</hi> or <hi>Admonition;</hi> or at leaſt nothing but <hi>good News.</hi> VVe have been told in
<note n="*" place="bottom">Philoſophical Diſcourſe of <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> by <hi>C. H. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </note> Print, That <hi>if any thing can be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the late Earthquake here,</hi> September the 8th, <hi>it is this, That as we had a long and calm Serenity of Weather after it, ſo a laſting Peace and Tranquillity will be ſettled in the World by the Conduct and Victorious Arms of</hi> King VVILLIAM, <hi>whom God long preſerve.</hi> How little Ground we have to expect this without <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> I leave to the Conſideration of all who ſeriouſly believe God's Government of the VVorld, and know what he hath done to other Nations, and People.</p>
            <p>I may promiſe my ſelf the Concurrence of all Good Men in our Improvement of <hi>the late Earthquakes,</hi> which I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:58544:5"/>to perſwade to, <hi>viz.</hi> Thankfully to own our publick National Mercies, while other Countries are made Deſolate. <hi>That</hi> Trembling of the Earth in <hi>England,</hi> 'tis true, was not <hi>a Prodigy in one ſenſe,</hi> becauſe we were not <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by it: But then it had not been a <hi>Warning,</hi> but an <hi>Execution,</hi> as to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; not the <hi>Signal,</hi> but the <hi>Judgment.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Account of a Deliverance from a threatning Earthquake, <hi>Anno Chriſti 365.</hi> we find the City of
<note n="*" place="bottom">Sozomen, l. 6. c. 2. Amm. Marcell. Le Sieur.</note> 
               <hi>Alexandria</hi> obſerved an Annual Feaſt, in Commemoration of it.</p>
            <p>VVhen ſome are made <hi>Examples,</hi> and <hi>Signs</hi> to us, God expects we ſhould own his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> that we are ſpared; and take heed that we provoke not his <hi>Anger,</hi> by the like and further Tranſgreſſions. VVhen our Saviour exhorts us <hi>to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> Lot<hi>'s Wife,</hi> we may ſuppoſe it was not the <hi>Miracle,</hi> ſo much as the <hi>Moral</hi> he intended. God's Judgments on <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> he ſaid, ſhall be
<note n="†" place="bottom">Ezek. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>an Inſtruction,</hi>
               <pb n="x" facs="tcp:58544:6"/>and <hi>an Aſtoniſhment</hi> unto the Nations round about. So was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> warned by what had been done to the <hi>Proud Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;
<note n="*" place="bottom">Ezek. 31.3.</note> Speak unto</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and to his Multitude, Who art thou like in thy Greatneſs? Behold the</hi> Aſſyrian <hi>was a Cedar in</hi> Lebanon <hi>with fair Branches,</hi> &amp;c. In like manner he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues with <hi>Ninive,</hi> from his Severity on <hi>No,</hi> or <hi>Alexandria;
<note n="†" place="bottom">Nahum. 3.5, 8.</note> Behold I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee; Art thou better than po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous</hi> No, <hi>that was ſituate among the Rivers?</hi> The Puniſhment of <hi>One</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or Perſon, ſhould be a VVarning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>All.</hi> The Greek
<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Matth. 1.19.</note> word for <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> doth ſignify <hi>Example.</hi> VVith what Terror doth God threaten not to ſpare <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they continued in their Security and Rebellion,
<note n="(*)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Amos 2.6, 9.</hi> See <hi>Jerem. 44.2, 7, 9. Ezek. 23.5,—31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>though he had deſtroyed the</hi> Amorite <hi>before them?</hi> May we not fear, lest he ſay of us, as <hi>Jer. 49.12, 13. For thus ſaith
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:58544:6"/>the Lord, Behold, they whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not to drink of the Cup, have aſſuredly drunken, and art thou he that ſhalt altogether go unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Thou ſhalt not go unpuniſhed, but thou ſhalt ſurely drink of it. For I have ſworn by my ſelf, ſaith the Lord, that</hi> Bozrah <hi>ſhall become a Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a Reproach, a Waſte, and a Curſe, and all the Cities thereof ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Waſtes?</hi> God hath favoured us hitherto, and we conſider it not; he hath loved <hi>Us,</hi> and hated <hi>Others,</hi> as he <hi>loved Jacob,</hi> and <hi>hated Eſau;</hi> and yet we are ready to ſay, <hi>Wherein hath he loved us
<note n="*" place="bottom">Malachi 1.2, 3.</note>? Behold, ſaith the Lord, was not</hi> Eſau Jacob<hi>'s Brother? Yet I loved</hi> Jacob, <hi>and hated</hi> Eſau; <hi>I laid his Mountains, and his Heritage waſte,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But however God may in <hi>Soveraignty</hi> deal with us, as to publick Deliverance, and Preſervation, and a Good and Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Iſſue of the preſent VVar, (whereas
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:58544:7"/>we hear of <hi>Another Earthquake</hi> in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily,</hi> the last Month;) yet I have ſhewn in the <hi>laſt Chapter,</hi> that no particular Perſon, without Repentance, ſhall <hi>long</hi> eſcape his Juſtice. <hi>1 Kings 10.17. They that eſcape the Sword of</hi> Hazael, <hi>ſhall</hi> Jehu <hi>ſlay; and they that eſcape the Sword of</hi> Jehu, <hi>ſhall</hi> Eliſha <hi>ſlay:</hi> That is, they ſhall periſh in <hi>another World;</hi> for the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> denounc'd <hi>Eternal Judgments</hi> on thoſe who eſcap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d a <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Ruine,</hi> if they continued in their Sins.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>May <hi>26. 1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:58544:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>INTRODUCTION. <hi>AN Hiſtorical, particular Account of the late</hi> Earthquakes, <hi>which gave Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to this Diſcourſe. The Deſign thereof propoſed from that Paſſage of the Pſalmist,</hi> My Fleſh trembleth for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy Judgments. pag. 1.</p>
            <p>CHAP. I. <hi>The Method of the following Diſcourſe. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Divine Severity on Others are not to be overlook'd; whether in former Times, or of later Date; on Strangers, Neighbours, Friends or Enemies. They are proper to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect us with an awful Fear of God:</hi> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes <hi>eſpecially of all other Judgments. The Terror of ſuch a Judgment in part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: that it is the Effect of Sin.</hi> p. 35.</p>
            <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:58544:8"/>
            <p>CHAP. II. <hi>Such Inſtances of Divine</hi> Severity <hi>ſhould teach us to reverence and adore the Divine Power, and Providence; ſhould awaken us to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, excite most earnest Prayer, occaſion Thankfulneſs for our Preſervation hitherto, and call upon us to trust in God as our only Refuge, and to ſecure his Favour.</hi> p. 62.</p>
            <p>CHAP. III. <hi>We ought not to cenſure Others, becauſe of ſuch Calamities, as</hi> greater Sinners <hi>than thoſe who eſcape: much leſs ſhould we paſs a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on their</hi> Eternal State, <hi>becauſe they are cut off</hi> ſuddenly <hi>by a</hi> temporal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. p. 84.</p>
            <p>CHAP. IV. <hi>What</hi> Fear <hi>of Evils to come is</hi> lawful, <hi>how far a</hi> Duty, <hi>and when</hi> ſinful. <hi>Of the</hi> Penal Fear <hi>of future Calamity: Inſtances of it as a Divine</hi> Puniſhment. <hi>What</hi> little Ground <hi>we have to expect a much longer</hi> Reprieve; <hi>we have</hi> none <hi>for</hi> Security, <hi>and</hi> Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>The</hi> Doubtfulneſs <hi>of our Caſe ſhould awaken our utmost Concern, and Care to prevent Deſtruction</hi> p. 92.</p>
            <p>CHAP. V. <hi>Of</hi> God's Unwillingneſs <hi>to deſtroy a People.</hi> Hoſea 11.8, 9. <hi>explained, paraphraſed, and applied to our Nation and City:</hi> How ſhall
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:58544:8"/>I give thee up, <hi>Ephraim?</hi> &amp;c. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham<hi>'s pleading with God for</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomorrah, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>Moral Cauſes why we may expect, and fear National and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Calamities.</hi> p. 103.</p>
            <p>CHAP. VI. Earthquakes <hi>uſually reckoned the Forerunners of other Calamities. We have had many Signs and Warnings; and a long Seaſon of Divine Forbearance; tho we are guilty of the like Sins, as have brought deſtructive Judgments on other People.</hi> The Land full of Sin. <hi>Publick Societies only puniſh'd in this World.</hi> p. 117.</p>
            <p>CHAP. VII. <hi>Moſt ſlight ſuch Warnings. What was done in</hi> Jamaica, <hi>had ſpecial Relation to us in this Iſland. We in</hi> England <hi>have had divers Earthquakes formerly.</hi> Their <hi>Wickedneſs was great, ſo is</hi> ours. <hi>Several Earthquakes have extended as far as ours,</hi> Sept. 8th, <hi>tho felt beyond the Seas near the ſame Time. Other Inſtances of Earthquakes in</hi> Europe. p. 128.</p>
            <p>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Many Examples of Terrible</hi> Earthquakes <hi>in other Parts of the World, formerly, and of late.</hi> p. 156.</p>
            <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:58544:9"/>
            <p>CHAP. IX. <hi>God will yet preſerve his Church, and enlarge the Kingdom of Christ; tho Particular Churches and Countries may be deſtroyed. The Accompliſhment of Scripture-Prophecies and Promiſes, uſher'd in by great Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and by</hi> Earthquakes. <hi>Some Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof.</hi> p. 166.</p>
            <p>CHAP. X. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Fear <hi>of Divine Judgments, and the Regulation of it. What</hi> Fear of Evil <hi>God hath promiſed, and we may expect to be delivered from, and what not. Counſels proper to obtain an Interest in thoſe Promiſes, and to experience the fulfilling of them.</hi> p. 188.</p>
            <p>CHAP. XI. Security <hi>a Preſage of Temporal and Eternal Ruine, to particular Perſons, whatever God may do as to the Nation in general.</hi> p. 199.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58544:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Practical Reflections</hi> ON THE Late Earthquakes In <hi>Jamaica, England, Sicily, Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> &amp;c. Anno 1692.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An Hiſtorical, particular Account of the late</hi> Earthquakes, <hi>which gave Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this Diſcourſe. The Deſign there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of propoſed from that Paſſage of the Pſalmiſt,</hi> My Fleſh trembleth for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy Judgments.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THAT the late Earthquakes may be conſidered, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the beſt Purpoſes, it will be proper to premiſe a ſhort Narrative, or Hiſtorical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58544:10"/>of them, according to the order of Time wherein they happened. And therefore I begin with that at <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt Year, 1692. on the 7th of <hi>June,</hi> there happened a dreadful <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> which made great Ruines and Devaſtations throughout the whole Country; but eſpecially in the Capital Town of <hi>Port-Royal,</hi> which was almoſt ſwallowed up and overflowed by the ſinking of the Earth, and Irruption of the Sea. Two Letters from the Miniſter of the Place (publiſhed by Authority) give a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account of it; that it threw down moſt of the Houſes, Churches, Sugar and Indigo-Works, Mills and Bridges, throughout the whole Iſland, that it tore the Rocks and Mountains, (others tell us that it levelled ſome Mountains, and reduced them to Plains) that it deſtroyed ſome whole Plantations, and threw them into the Sea; but <hi>Port-Royal</hi> had much the greateſt ſhare in this terrible Judgment.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58544:10"/>
               <p>It is added by a farther Account in the Gazette of Thurſday, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 18. that on the Harbour-ſide the Houſes all ſunk down in a Minute's time, from the Depth of three to five Fathom Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the Streets next the Wharf: the Earth opened it ſelf wide and deep, and inſtantly guſhed out an Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Water, ſo that Multitudes were drowned. Among other Accidents of the Earthquake, the <hi>Swan</hi> Frigat lying at the Wharf for Careening, was driven in among the Houſes, and there loſt.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter in his Letter ſaith far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That ſuch was the deſperate Wickedneſs of the People there, that he was afraid to continue among them. That on the ſame Day of the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, as ſoon as Night came on, ſome lewd Rogues, whom they call <hi>Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers,</hi> fell to breaking open Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and Houſes deſerted, to rob and rifle their Neighbours, whilſt the Earth trembled under them, and ſome of the Houſes fell upon them in the Act. And thoſe audacious Whores
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58544:11"/>who remained ſtill upon the Place, were as impudent and drunken as ever. And that ſince the Earthquake, when he was on ſhore to pray with the bruiſed and dying People, and to chriſten Children, he met with too many drunk and ſwearing.</p>
               <p>The Day when this Calamity befel the Town and Iſland, was very clear, affording not any Suſpicion of the leaſt Evil; but in the Space of three Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, about half an Hour after eleven in the Morning, <hi>Port-Royal,</hi> the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Town of all the Engliſh Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the beſt <hi>Emporium</hi> and Mart of this part of the World, exceeding in Riches, and abounding in all good things, was ſhaken and ſhatter'd to pieces, and covered for the greateſt part by the Sea; the Wharf, and two whole Streets beyond it, intirely ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Sea.</p>
               <p>He, with the Preſident of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, running to ſave themſelves, made towards <hi>Morgan</hi>'s Fort, becauſe a wide open Place; he thought to be there ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58544:11"/>from the falling Houſes: but as he was going, he ſaw the Earth open, and ſwallow up a Multitude of People, and the Sea mounting in upon them over the Fortifications. He tells us further, that their large and famous Burying-place, called the <hi>Palliſado</hi>'s, was deſtroyed by the Earthquake; and that the Sea waſhed away the Carcaſes of thoſe that were buried out of their Graves; their Tombs being daſh'd to pieces by the Motion and Concuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: That the whole Harbour, one of the faireſt he ever ſaw, was covered with the dead Bodies of People of all Conditions, floating up and down without Burial. That in the opening of the Earth, the Houſes and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants ſinking down together, ſome of theſe were driven up again by the Sea, which aroſe in thoſe Breaches, and ſo did wonderfully eſcape. Some were ſwallowed up to the Neck, and then the Earth ſhut upon them, and ſqueezed them to Death: And in that manner ſeveral were left buried with their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58544:12"/>Heads above Ground, only ſome Heads the Dogs have eaten; others are cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Duſt and Earth by the People, which yet remain in the Place, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the Stench. So that by the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Earth, and the Fall of the Houſes, and the Inundation of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it is thought fifteen hundred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are loſt, and many of good Note.</p>
               <p>After he was eſcaped in a Ship, he ſaith, he could not ſleep all Night for the Returns of the Earthquake almoſt every Hour, which made all the Guns in the Ship to jar and rattle; and he ſuppoſeth the whole Town of <hi>Port-Royal</hi> will ſhortly be ſwallowed up of the Sea, the Houſes falling, and the Sea encroaching daily. That there were ſad Accounts of Miſchiefs done by the Earthquake in other Parts of the Iſland: As from St. <hi>Ann</hi>'s, they heard of above a thouſand Acres of Woodland changed into Sea, carrying with it whole Plantations.</p>
               <p>His own Preſervation was very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable and unexpected: after he had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58544:12"/>prayed with the People, and given them ferious Exhortations to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, (in which Exerciſes he ſpent near an Hour and half) he was deſired by ſome Merchants to retire to ſome Ship in the Harbour, whom he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied, paſſing over the Tops of ſome Houſes, which lay levelled with the Surface of the Water, got firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Canoe, and then into a Long-boat, which put him on board a Ship.</p>
               <div n="England" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of the Earthquake in</hi> England.</head>
                  <p>ON the 8th of <hi>September</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1692. an Earthquake was felt at <hi>London,</hi> and in ſeveral Parts of <hi>Eſſex, Kent, Suſſex, Hampſhire,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Sheerneſs, Sandwich, Deal, Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, Portſmouth,</hi> &amp;c. the People lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Houſes in many Places, leſt they ſhould fall on their Heads; but it laſted not above
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>See Mr.</hi> Ray<hi>'s</hi> Phyſico-Theol. <hi>Diſcourſe of the Dr luge.</hi> Diſc. 2. p. 209.</note> two Minutes: It
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58544:13"/>was about two a Clock; ſome reckon'd at <hi>London</hi> it was about four Minutes paſt two. It was felt in moſt parts of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands;</hi> as alſo in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> It affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Places moſt on the Sea-coaſts, and near great Rivers. It went not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond 52 Degrees and 40 Minutes of Northern Latitude: How far it reach'd to the South and Eaſt is not yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known for want of good Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: we have already trac'd it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Paris,</hi> to the 48th Degree of North Latitude: and beyond the <hi>Rhine,</hi> on the Eaſt, to <hi>Francfort;</hi> ſo that we know at preſent of 260 Miles ſquare ſhaken by it. The Time of its happening here in <hi>England,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, ſeems to vary ſome Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes; but that may eaſily be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for by the Difference of
<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Thus Dr.</hi> T. Robinſon <hi>in a Letter to Mr.</hi> Ray, <hi>dated</hi> Septemb. 22. 1692.</note> Meridians. So that the inflamed Damp, ſaith Mr. <hi>Ray,</hi> which cauſed this Earthquake,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58544:13"/>was lodged deep in the Earth, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns that contained it, paſſing under the bottom of the Sea.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Sicily" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of the Earthquakes in</hi> Sicily, <hi>and</hi> Malta.</head>
                  <p>THE following Account of the Earthquakes in <hi>Sicily,</hi> was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Authority here, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Meſſina. January</hi> 20, 1692/3;, they write, that ſeveral Earthquakes had happened in that Iſland, which were moſt violent in the Southern Parts of it, and have laid in heaps many Cities and Villages. <hi>Catanea</hi> was ſhaken on the 9th inſtant, and on the 11th quite deſtroyed, not one Houſe left ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and near <hi>twenty thouſand</hi> Perſons periſhed in that City alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auguſta</hi> was almoſt deſtroyed at the ſame time: and 400 Barrels of Powder that were in the Caſtle, took Fire at the ſame time, by Lightning, or ſome other Accident, and blew up about a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58544:14"/>thouſand People, who were got in there for their Security.</p>
                  <p>The Ancient <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> hath fared no better: and the Cities of <hi>Modica, Jaci</hi> and <hi>Noto,</hi> and all the Villages from Mount <hi>Aetna</hi> to Cape <hi>Paſſaro</hi> have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd extremely. 'Tis computed that above an <hi>hundred thouſand</hi> Perſons have been deſtroyed by theſe Earthquakes. <hi>Palermo</hi> felt the Shock on the 11th: and the Vice-King retired with all his Family on board the Gallies in that Port. Moſt of the Inhabitants of this City lay now in the Fields without the Gates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Letter from <hi>Naples, Feb.</hi> 3. men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that by the Shock on the 11th of the laſt Month, 37 Cities and Towns and large Villages were quite deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>one hundred and thirty thouſand</hi> Perſons.</p>
                  <p>By other Letters (in the Gazette of Thurſday <hi>March</hi> 16.) we have this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count from <hi>Meſſina, Feb.</hi> 3. That they hear every day of the lamentable Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the late Earthquakes, and give
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58544:14"/>the following Liſt of Places, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſtroyed, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calatagirone,</hi> about a fourth part of the City ruined, and 1500 Perſons killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luochuela,</hi> quite deſtroyed, with moſt of the Inhabitants, the number not known.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mineo,</hi> a Royal City, moſt of it fallen, and 3000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Militello,</hi> quite deſtroyed, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Inhabitants, the number not known.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Palaonia,</hi> very much ſhattered, but few Perſons killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scordia,</hi> the Palace fallen down, and 20 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Francofome,</hi> much ſhattered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sentini,</hi> quite ruined, and 3000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Carlontini,</hi> quite deſtroyed, with many of the Inhabitants, the number not known.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auguſta,</hi> quite deſtroyed, and 5000 killed.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58544:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Siragoſa,</hi> above half ruined, and 6000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Noto,</hi> quite ruined, and 7000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Specaſurno,</hi> quite ruined, and 3000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scichilo,</hi> quite ruined, and 8000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Santa Croce,</hi> 100 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Modica,</hi> quite deſtroyed, and 1000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Raguſa,</hi> greateſt part of it ruined, and 7000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cefomaro,</hi> 200 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Biſcuti,</hi> 100 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chiuramonte,</hi> wholly deſtroyed, and 300 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monteruſſo,</hi> 200 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Giamantano,</hi> 300 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bucchin,</hi> 160 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Patuzzolo,</hi> quite ruined, and 1000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scodia,</hi> 100 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paſceni,</hi> quite ruined, and 600 kill'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Furla,</hi> quite ruined, and 800 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sciorti,</hi> quite ruined, and 2000 kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58544:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vizzini,</hi> quite ruined, and 3000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Licodia,</hi> 400 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Catanea,</hi> wholly deſtroyed, and 18000 killed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jaci,</hi> much ruined, and 1800 kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In all,</hi> 73680 <hi>Perſons killed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In another Letter from <hi>Naples,</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>March</hi> 3. publiſhed in the Gazette of the 3d of <hi>April,</hi> there is an Account from <hi>Palermo,</hi> that the Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily</hi> had ſent Commiſſioners to take an exact Account of the Damage occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by the late <hi>Earthquakes</hi> in that Iſland; and they had found that the Ruine of the Towns and Villages, as well as Loſs of People, was greater and more deplorable, than was at firſt reported; and that there had periſh'd above <hi>one hundred thouſand</hi> Perſons.</p>
                  <p>A more particular Account of this terrible Earthquake in <hi>Sicily,</hi> was printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſince printed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58544:16"/>here from the Italian Copy; part whereof I ſhall here inſert. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor profeſſeth he cannot give himſelf nor others, all the Satisfaction he could wiſh, there being ſo many little Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and even ſome conſiderable Towns ſo utterly deſtroyed, that there are no Inhabitants left, to give us an account of the manner how theſe Places were ſwallowed up. So that of theſe we can have no other Narrative, but what People at a Diſtance, and in a Hurry themſelves, for fear of ſinking into the ſame Ruin, have been able to give us.</p>
                  <p>The Earthquake diffus'd it ſelf into all the three <hi>Diſtricts,</hi> or Diviſions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the Iſland of <hi>Sicily</hi> is uſually divided; <hi>Valli di Noto, Mazaro,</hi> and <hi>Mono.</hi> The greateſt Shake of all was from <hi>Mount Aetna</hi> to <hi>Cape Paſſaro,</hi> the <hi>Pachmus</hi> of the Ancients. In all this vaſt Tract of Land, nothing ſtood the ſhock, but all fell under the Weight of a General Ruin.</p>
                  <p>It was on the 7th of <hi>January,</hi> 1692/3, about 10 at Night, that <hi>Mount Aetna</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58544:16"/>began to utter thoſe hideous Roarings, which ſeldom but uſher in ſome Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy of the Nature of what followed. Thoſe loud Bellowings continued till the 9th, and about 12 a Clock began to ceaſe. Within an hour after, the Inhabitants of <hi>Catanea,</hi> which is the next Town to the Mountain, began to perceive a ſhaking under 'em, about three Minutes together. This did lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Hurt, other than to afright the People, and give them fears of ſome further Hurt. During this Shake, and for an hour before, there was not the leaſt Noiſe heard from <hi>Mount Aet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> but within leſs than a minute af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Shake was over, not only did the Noiſe redouble, infinitely more terrible than before, but the whole Top of the Mountain appeared all in Flames.</p>
                  <p>All this was but the Fore-runner of the horrideſt Shake of all, which fell out on the <hi>11th,</hi> which affected the whole Iſland, tho not equally. And by the exacteſt Computation can be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58544:17"/>made, the whole Period of it laſted not above <hi>ſix Minutes,</hi> from <hi>Meſſina</hi> Northwards to <hi>Cape Coio,</hi> the fartheſt Point of <hi>Sicily</hi> to the South.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Catanea</hi> is thought to be the firſt that fell under the Weight of this heavy Calamity. This City is as ancient as moſt in <hi>Sicily,</hi> ſeated in a pleaſant and rich Soil, inhabited by ſeveral of the Gentry thereabouts, endowed with an an Univerſity, and containing about 24000 Souls, was ſunk out of ſight in a moment. There happened to be ſome Fiſher-boats at that time in the Bay that lies South of the Town, and within a League's diſtance, who give an Account, that they ſaw the City ſink down, with the Noiſe as it were of ſome thouſand Pieces of great Ordnance diſcharged all at once. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was thus vaniſhed out of their ſight, the Fiſhermen ſay, That ſome minutes after, to the Eaſtward, near where the City ſtood, there roſe up a little Mountain, which lifting it ſelf ſeveral times a conſiderable Height, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58544:17"/>the ordinary Level of the Ground thereabouts, ſunk at laſt likewiſe out of their ſight. They declare alſo, that during all this horrid Tragedy, they expected every moment to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in the Bay, by reaſon of the ſtrange violent Agitations of the Sea. And ſcarce was this heaving up of the imaginary Mountain on the South-ſide of <hi>Catanea</hi> over, but they felt the Sea calm.</p>
                  <p>It is thought there hath not eſcap'd of the Inhabitants of <hi>Catanea</hi> above <hi>two thouſand</hi> in all, ſome of thoſe eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping after the firſt Shake on the 9th, others on the Morning of the 11th, who took the Warning. But they were the better ſort of People only that had the opportunity to make ſo happy an Eſcape, the reſt falling under the Univerſal Ruin. In the Place where <hi>Catanea</hi> ſtood, appears now at a diſtance a great Lake, with ſome great heaps of Rubbiſh, appearing here and there above Water.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58544:18"/>
                  <p>The ſame Shake that utterly deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Catanea,</hi> did lay in heaps more than half of <hi>Saragoſa,</hi> the Antient <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> once the greateſt City of <hi>Sicily;</hi> and if we will believe <hi>Strabo</hi> and others, the largeſt once in the World, and may contend with any in <hi>Europe</hi> for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. The leaſt Computation that can be made of the Loſs of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of it, is above <hi>ſeven thouſand:</hi> And ſome hundreds were digged out of the Ruins alive, but lame and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; ſo that few of them it's thought will recover. Moſt of the Magiſtrates and People of beſt Faſhion, ran into the great Church for ſhelter, where they met with Death by the fall of the Stone Roof, and the Steeple both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                  <p>The City of <hi>Noto</hi> (which once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the Preheminence with <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuſa</hi> it ſelf) had yet a worſe Fate: ſcarce any part of it is now ſtanding; tho ſituate on an high Rock, almoſt inacceſſible on all ſides, but by one nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Paſſage. The mighty Hardneſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58544:18"/>of the Rock ſeem'd to have ſecur'd it from the Hazard of Earthquakes; but it felt the Shake of the 9th; and on the 11th of <hi>January</hi> it was in a moment laid in heaps: the number of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants is computed about <hi>ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi> and very few are eſcaped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auguſta,</hi> a City well ſituated, and adorned with large and ſafe Harbours; a Place of good Trade for Corn. The Inhabitants reckoned near <hi>ſix thouſand,</hi> of whom we have account of none left; many kill'd on the 9th, more on the 10th, and the reſt buried by the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning of the Town on the 11th.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lentini,</hi> the ancient <hi>Leontium,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for a beautiful Lake on which it ſtood; a Place of about <hi>three thouſand Families,</hi> and a Place of tolerable Trade by Fiſhing, and Salt Mines, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to Aſhes on the 11th; and it is not known if any of the Inhabitants be ſaved. The Water of the Lake is now become brackiſh, and of a ſalt and bituminous Taſte; and vaſt numbers of Fiſh are every day found dead on the Shore.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58544:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calatgirone,</hi> a pretty Town, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining about 7000 People, and well built, moſt of hewn Stone; on the 11th a fifth part of the Town was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturned, and two Monaſteries; and 'tis thought, no fewer than <hi>two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> Souls were deſtroyed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mineo</hi> felt both the Shake of the 9th and 11th; on the former, the Heavens were ſerene, ſcarce a Cloud appearing above the Horizon; but on the 11th, there was a Storm of Thunder and Lightning for ſix Hours. At both times ſeveral Houſes, &amp; a large Church were overturned, and it's thought near <hi>four thouſand</hi> of the Inhabitants are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monreal,</hi> or <hi>Morreal,</hi> was ſhaken and ſhattered; and <hi>Palermo,</hi> the Seat of the Vice-Roy, but not above 100 Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple kill'd. <hi>Paſceni,</hi> conſiſting of about 200 Families, the richeſt of any little Town in <hi>Sicily,</hi> hath not one ſingle Houſe left ſtanding, nor one ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſav'd. <hi>Patuzolo,</hi> a bigger Town, underwent the ſame Fate; the number
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58544:19"/>of Inhabitants about 1000 at leaſt: It is not known that <hi>any</hi> are ſaved.</p>
                  <p>So for <hi>Furla,</hi> whoſe Inhabitants we reckon'd to be near <hi>a thouſand</hi> Souls. The like for <hi>Sciorti,</hi> which by the Shake of the 11th is a vaſt Heap of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins; only a Church belonging to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictine Nunnery, is intire: we know of <hi>none</hi> of the Inhabitants ſav'd, and they are reckon'd to amount to <hi>two thouſand</hi> Souls.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Fate befel <hi>Militello,</hi> no inconſiderable Town, probably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining about <hi>ſix thouſand</hi> People, whereof <hi>no one</hi> is left to give tidings how its Calamity came about.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luochela</hi> fared ſomewhat better: many, about half of the People, left the Town on the Shake of the 9th of <hi>January,</hi> when a great part of the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes fell. The Caſtle was ſwallowed up in a moment in ſight of the People; and a conſiderable Lake is in the place where the Caſtle ſtood. The reſt of the Town and Inhabitants were utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed on the <hi>11th.</hi> Of <hi>two
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58544:20"/>thouſand</hi> People, <hi>one half</hi> periſhed.</p>
                  <p>There was little Damage done in <hi>Palonia,</hi> another well-built Town, but that beſides feeling the Shake on the 9th, and the Church ſhattered, the <hi>Dome</hi> was thrown down on the 11th, which broke the high Altar to pieces, and cruſh'd to Death ſome 300 People, with the Prieſt that was ſaying Maſs. The like almoſt for <hi>Buchino,</hi> a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Village.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scodia,</hi> a Burgh about the bigneſs of the other, was greatly ſhaken on the 11th, and about 150 People kill'd by the fall of the Church in the time of Maſs. In a deep Lake within 2 miles of it (2 miles about) by the Shake of the 11th, there opened a large <hi>Caſma</hi> near the midſt of the Lake, which ſwallowed up the Water, (which by that of the 9th was leſſened) and left the whole Channel dry Land, which continues ſo.</p>
                  <p>Another Village, called <hi>Chivramonte,</hi> had its Houſes ſhattered by the Shake of the 9th, but overturned altogether
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58544:20"/>on the 11th, and the Inhabitants buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Ruins, computed between 3 and 400.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Monteruſſo</hi> was conſiderably ſhaken on the 9th; and on the 11th, 200 Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who fled into the Caſtle, were with it buried in the Ground; and the Place where it ſtood, is now <hi>a Pool of Water,</hi> of a briniſh Taſte.</p>
                  <p>The beautiful Town of <hi>Vizzini,</hi> containing about 3500 Souls, though it lay on a riſing Hill, made up of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but hardeſt Stones, of the nature of Marble, was yet ſhaken on the 9th, and ſwallowed up with the Inhabitants on the 11th, who thought the Danger had then been over.</p>
                  <p>The large Village of <hi>Modica,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining about 1400 People, was ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſwallowed up on the 9th, that <hi>no one Perſon eſcap'd.</hi> Since this <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> Years, this Village hath twice changed its Seat by <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> the People till now ſaving themſelves. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Rivers</hi> and <hi>Rivulets</hi> near this and other Places in <hi>Sicily,</hi> are covered by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58544:21"/>Hills, in the form of a Vault, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bridg, thrown over them by the <hi>Earthquake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Earthquake cauſed the fall of ſome Houſes at <hi>Biſenti,</hi> and the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to death of about 100 Perſons. <hi>Francofonte</hi> ſuffered more by Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Thunder for three days, than by the ſhake of the Earthquake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Carlontini,</hi> a Town of good Trade, and well inhabited, containing about 4000 People; a <hi>ſixth part</hi> of 'em periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Earthquake on the 11th; the reſt eſcaped by the warning on the 9th.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Raguſa,</hi> a beautiful Town; its Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, Buildings, Churches, Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and Territories about it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine to make it a ſort of <hi>Terreſtrial Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe;</hi> felt many Shakings on the 8th, with Lightning and Thunder: but on the 11th, the biggeſt Street in the Town, the Town-houſe, two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and many Houſes were overtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or ſwallowed up. The leaſt Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of People that periſh'd, is <hi>eight thouſand,</hi> of whom the Citizens of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58544:21"/>beſt Quality make up a great part of that Number.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Specafurno,</hi> a Town of conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bigneſs, on the Side of a Hill, all planted with Vineyards, and well inhabited, fell under the ſame Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity; partly by Lightning and Thunder on the 10th; and the whole Town in a Moment's time on the 11th. About a Mile from the Town was a pleaſant freſh Water Lake on the South ſide, which is now almoſt all dry Land; the Fiſh dead on the Shore, and the Water of a briniſh Taſte, and now of a black Colour. The People that periſh'd there are computed to be at leaſt <hi>three thouſand five hundred:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>three hundred</hi> only ſaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Day before.</p>
                  <p>The Town <hi>Scichilo,</hi> that hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 50 Years been <hi>eight</hi> times in hazard of an Earthquake, felt this on the 8th of <hi>January,</hi> and within 24 Hours there ſucceeded above 20 Shakes, the laſt ſtill exceeding the firſt in Violence; but on the 11th the whole Town, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58544:22"/>leſs than two Moments vaniſh'd out of Sight: in the room of it is now a ſtinking Pool of Water: And of <hi>ſix</hi> or <hi>ſeven thouſand</hi> Inhabitants of this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Town, it is thought there is <hi>no one</hi> ſaved. Beſides a ſtrong Caſtle on the Eaſt ſide of the Town, which is now all in Heaps, and above 30 Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple buried alive in them.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Cefamero,</hi> a Village of above two hundred Houſes, near two hundred People periſh'd in the Church, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they fled for Shelter, to implore the Aid of St. <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Sienne;</hi> and ſome twenty in the Village. In <hi>Santa Croce,</hi> another Village, about one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Inhabitants periſh'd, the reſt having fled to the Fields without the Town. In the little Town of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amontano,</hi> in the Quarter neareſt the River, about three hundred and fifty Perſons periſh'd, and about forty more. The Tower of <hi>Lacodia</hi> underwent near the ſame Fate; all the Houſes of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were overwhelmed by the Shake of the 11th, and in them about three hundred of the Inhabitants.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58544:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jaci,</hi> a very big Town, was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhatter'd, eſpecially in the Fall of two Churches on the 9th, in the time of Divine Service. Many of the Houſes of the Town were overturn'd on the 11th, together with two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, particularly that of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> where was kept St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Net, in which he took that vaſt quantity of Fiſh mention'd in the Goſpel. By the Fall of the Houſes and Churches there periſhed in all above two thouſand People, more than half died by the Fall of the two Churches.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>La-motta,</hi> a Village of about two hundred Inhabitants, famous for the Retirement of the Citizens of <hi>Paler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> there in the Summer-time, was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally overturn'd on the 9th, a ſalt Pool ſucceeding in its Place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Meſſina,</hi> a City of great Trade, lofty Buildings, and great Riches, felt the Shake on the 9th, and more than half the Inhabitants fled to the Fields; the reſt betook themſelves to their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſeveral Churches: the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58544:23"/>Archbiſhop ordered forty eight Hours of Prayer, and ſeveral Proceſſions, to appeaſe the Wrath of Heaven. On the 11th, twenty ſix Palaces were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, and many Timber-Houſes: every body expected immediate Death, and in vaſt Multitudes ran to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral, where the Archbiſhop of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina</hi> preach'd, and ſaid Maſs, and there after gave Abſolution, as did all the Prieſts through the reſt of the City by the Archbiſhop's Command. After this every one made the beſt of the ways they could, to eſcape the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Danger, and betook themſelves to the Fields, where they were not out of Hazard, through the Violence of the Thunder, Lightning, and Rain, that continued three Days together: The Chappel of the Archbiſhop's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace is overturn'd, moſt of the Churches ſhatter'd, but few People kill'd.</p>
                  <p>The Tide was higher on the 10th by three Foot than ever was known, and ſuch a violent Agitation of the Water, that ſeveral Ships and ſmaller
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58544:23"/>Veſſels were drown'd all along the Coaſt of the Iſland, and ſome even in the Harbours.</p>
                  <p>In ſhort, a more aſtoniſhing, a more univerſal, or a more ſwift Deſtruction was never known. And <hi>Sicily</hi> that was one of the moſt beautiful, rich, and fruitful Iſlands in the World, is now an Heap of Rubbiſh, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Deſolation. The Loſs of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Merchandize, Houſes, and Lands, may modeſtly be computed to ſix Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Ducats: And it will take an Age to repair the Damages it hath made. The number of Inhabitants periſh'd, may be ſafely reckon'd to an <hi>hundred and twenty thouſand</hi> Souls; and the bruiſed, and like to die, <hi>twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand</hi> more.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Malta" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of the Earthquake at</hi> Malta.</head>
                  <p>ALL the Account we have yet of the further Effects of this Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and the Extent of it to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58544:24"/>Iſland of <hi>Malta,</hi> is in a Letter from thence, dated <hi>January</hi> 16. publiſh'd by Authority. On the 9th Inſtant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten at Night happened here an Earthquake, and another on the 11th at three in the Afternoon: The laſt was ſo violent, and laſted ſo long, that every body thought this City would have been quite deſtroyed. The Roof of the Church of our Lady <hi>de Pelay</hi> was thrown down, with part of that of St. <hi>Laurence:</hi> The Church and College of the Jeſuits alſo ſuffered ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much: but the Cathedral and the Church of <hi>la Guſmane</hi> received the greateſt Damage, and are ſo ruined, that they can hardly be repaired. Moſt of the Houſes are extremely ſhatter'd, and deſerted by the Inhabitants, who lie now in <hi>Grotto's,</hi> and under Tents in the Fields. The great Maſter of the Order was then abroad a hunting, and he and all his Company were in great Danger by the falling of a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain near them. We cannot yet tell the Particulars of the Loſs this Iſland
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58544:24"/>hath ſuſtained, but only in general, that 'tis very great, and the Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Inhabitants inexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which hath received a new Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the ſad Accounts we have from <hi>Sicily,</hi> of the ſame Calamity that hath befallen their Iſland, in a more terrible manner.—Whereof I have given the moſt particular Account yet extant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>And now upon the Peruſal of this ſad Hiſtory, who that will conſider it as a Chriſtian, but may uſe the Pſalmiſt's Expreſſion,</hi> Pſal. 119.120. My Fleſh trembleth for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy Judgments?</head>
                  <p>GOD expects we ſhould be affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and awed by ſuch Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</p>
                  <p>Some Duties of Religion are always
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58544:25"/>ſeaſonable, and of conſtant Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that muſt mix with all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and be regarded in every ſtep of our daily Walk: There are others which the Providence of God doth particularly call us to, at one time more than at another: <hi>There is a time to weep, and a time to laugh; a time to mourn, and a time to rejoice:</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing is beautiful in its Seaſon. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly when God ariſeth to ſhake terribly the Earth, and puniſh the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof for their Iniquities; when he girds on his Sword to ride his Circuit by national Judgments; when other Countries and People are made Examples and Warnings, and the growing Atheiſm and Profaneneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, may make us juſtly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the like Severity; he expects that our Temper and Carriage ſhould ſomewhat correſpond and agree to his Works of Providence; that when the Lion roars, we ſhould tremble; when he ſtretches out his Hand, and ſhakes his glittering Sword, we ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58544:25"/>it, and fear. He expects that we ſhould take the Warning he gives us, by the Calamities of <hi>others;</hi> that we ſhould lie in the Duſt, throw off our Ornaments, put on Sack-cloth, and prepare to meet him in the way of his Judgments.</p>
                  <p>We are many Ways obliged to this; in Conformity to the beſt Examples of holy Men in the like Caſe; and by our Love to God, and Duty to him, who is diſpleaſed, and provoked. Our Senſe of his Diſhonour, and due Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his Diſpleaſure, require this: Our Relation to thoſe Places and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have been already made Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Divine Severity; our Love to our ſelves, and to our Brethren in this part of the World, who are yet preſerved, do all require this; and call upon us to be found in ſuch a Frame, as the Pſalmiſt here expreſſeth upon the like Occaſion, <hi>My Fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth for fear of thee, and I am afraid of thy Judgments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58544:26"/>
                  <p>In the former Verſe he endeavours to excite his Love to God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved Adherence to his Precepts, by the Conſideration of the Judgments executed on the Wicked; <hi>Thou putteſt away the Wicked of the Earth like Droſs, therefore I love thy Teſtimonies.</hi> And in this he makes another Improvement of ſuch Inſtances of Divine Juſtice, to awaken an holy Fear, and Awe of God, <hi>My Fleſh trembleth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>An extraordinary Fear is often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in Scripture, as having this Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Trembling: Fear came upon me, and Trembling, which made all my Bones to ſhake, and the Hair of my Fleſh ſtood up,</hi> Job 4.14, 15. The like you have expreſs'd by the Prophet, upon God's Denunciation of Judgment; <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.16. <hi>When I heard this, my Belly trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, my Lips quivered, Rottenneſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into my Bones, and I trembled in my Fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When God lifts up his Voice in threatning of Judgment, and roars like a Lion, ready to tear in pieces,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58544:26"/>
                     <hi>Who will not fear?</hi> Amos 3.8. Or when he diſplays his Power, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts his Juſtice, and appears with terrible Majeſty, in the Execution of Judgment upon others; who that hears of it will not tremble before him, and be afraid of his Judgments?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Method of the following Diſcourſe. Inſtances of Divine Severity on others are not to be overlook'd; whether in former times, or of later Date; on Strangers, Neighbours, Friends or Enemies. They are proper to affect us with an awful Fear of God:</hi> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes <hi>eſpecially of all other Judgments. The Terror of ſuch a Judgment in part deſcribed: that it is the Effect of Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Ground of my following Diſcourſe will therefore be this, <hi>That the Inſtances of Divine Severity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58544:27"/>Others, ſhould affect the ſerious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them, with an awful Fear of God and his Judgments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> It is here implied, that we are not ſlightly to overlook the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of God's Severity upon others, but ſeriouſly to obſerve and conſider them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly;</hi> That ſuch Inſtances are proper to affect us with an awful Fear of God: eſpecially the Deſolations that are made by terrible <hi>Earthquakes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly;</hi> That this Awe of God, and Fear of his Judgments, upon ſuch Examples of Divine Severity, is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Duty</hi> unto all, that do obſerve and conſider them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly;</hi> How this may be applied, and improved by us, with reference to this City and Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> It is here implied, <hi>That we are not ſlightly to overlook the Examples of God's Severity upon Others.</hi> How often has God threatned, and puniſhed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58544:27"/>the ſecure and careleſs Frame of ſuch, as <hi>regard not the Works of the Lord, nor the Operation of his Hands?</hi> Iſa. 5.11. Pſal. 28.5. <hi>He ſhall,</hi> for this Reaſon, <hi>deſtroy them, and not build them up.</hi> We are bid to remember, conſider, and improve the ancient Judgments of God upon the old World, and upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> And 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5. to remember the Example of <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, and the ſeveral Calamities that befel the Jews in the Wilderneſs, and after their Settlement in <hi>Canaan:</hi> The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of God's Juſtice upon them for their ſeveral Provocations, are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Types and Warnings unto us, <hi>on whom the Ends of the World are come,</hi> who live in theſe latter Days, under the Goſpel-Diſpenſation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6, 11. that we ſhould not luſt as they luſted, and murmur as they, tempt Chriſt as they. It is ſaid of them whoſe Carcaſes fell in the Wilderneſs for their many repeated Provocations, that they are <hi>our Examples.</hi> God's Severity againſt them is recorded for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58544:28"/>our Uſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.11. God made them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an expreſs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and Repreſentation of what ſhould be done in others. Some ſhall ſmart, that others may fear. God hath further Ends in the Execution of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than we imagine: He intends them not only for Acts, but Patterns: Every Judgment is a new Leſſon; and God doth not intend to puniſh only, but to teach, and warn, and inſtruct: He warns when he wounds, and ſtrikes ſome, that others may be ſpared by taking Warning. <hi>When a Scorner is puniſh'd,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, the Simple is made wiſe,</hi> Prov. 2.11. And we are more apt to be impreſs'd by what we ſee executed, than by what is only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd in a Threatning.</p>
               <p>The Judgments of God on neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Countries and People are mentioned to this purpoſe for our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement; <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. <hi>I have cut off Nations,</hi> ſays God, (I have hanged them up as on a Gibbet, to inſtruct and warn you by their Ruine.)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58544:28"/>
                  <hi>Their Towers are deſolate, their Streets are waſte; ſo that no Man paſſeth by; their Cities are deſtroyed, that there is no Inhabitant. Hereupon I ſaid, Surely thou wilt fear me, ſurely thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Inſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This therefore does ſuppoſe the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, and laying ſuch things to Heart.</p>
               <p>We ought not eaſily to paſs over, and forget the Works of God, eſpecially when by the Terribleneſs and Severity of them, he has made them <hi>fit to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,</hi> Pſal. 111.4. They are Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies to a Divine Providence, and as ſuch ſhould be recorded. It is taken notice of to this purpoſe by
<note n="*" place="bottom">Verulam <hi>de Augment. Scient.</hi> l. 2. c. 11.</note> a learned and great Man, as a Defect among Chriſtians, that there is not yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant an <hi>Hiſtoria Nemeſews,</hi> a Judicious, Impartial, and well-atteſted Hiſtory of the Divine Vengeance, containing the moſt remarkable Monuments of God's Juſtice in the World.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58544:29"/>
               <p>When he afflicts and plagues any of our Neighbours or Brethren, or but Strangers, in an eminent manner, we are called to conſider his Doings, that we may <hi>learn Righteouſneſs, when the Judgments of God are abroad in the Earth,</hi> Iſa. 26.9. It is but fit that the Puniſhment of ſome ſhould make other Sinners tremble. As when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were ſtruck dead, it is ſaid, <hi>Great Fear fell upon all that heard theſe things,</hi> Acts 5.11. It is mentioned as a Fault, that when the Hand of God is lifted up, Men will not ſee and conſider it: And for this Stupidity God often expreſſeth his Diſpleaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.4, 5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>Job</hi> 34.26. <hi>Micah</hi> 6.9. We are commanded to take notice of his powerful Juſtice in ſuch Examples; <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.3. <hi>Come and ſee the Works of God, he is terrible in his Doings towards the Children of Men.</hi> He is ſaid to viſit us, and come nigh to us in <hi>Judgment</hi> as well as in <hi>Mercy:</hi> And ſhall he viſit us, and we not take
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58544:29"/>notice of it, or obſerve him? We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe make a due Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, in order to ſuitable Duty.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially ſhould it be thus, when any of <hi>our Brethren,</hi> of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with us, meet with any more than ordinary Rebuke of Providence, as is the caſe of <hi>Jamaica:</hi> Not but that we ought to eye and own God, tho the Inſtances of his Severity be more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, as in the late extraordinary Earthquakes in <hi>Sicily.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of God's righteous Judgments on the Wicked,</hi> will make <hi>the Righteous that ſee it, to fear</hi> and <hi>tremble,</hi> Pſal. 52.6. <hi>The Righteous doth wiſely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Houſe of the VVicked, how God overthroweth the Wicked for their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> Prov. 21.12. All the great Diſplays of God's Juſtice in the World, are fit to be regiſtred and remembred by us, as Teſtimonies to us of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Holineſs, and Righteous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Come hither,</hi> ſays God, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Works of the Lord, what Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58544:30"/>he has made in the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 46.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly;</hi> As we muſt obſerve, and conſider theſe Inſtances of God's Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon others, ſo <hi>they are very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to affect us with an holy Awe and Fear of God.</hi> He owns himſelf the Author of all the Deſolations wrought in the Earth. Earthly Princes will have Matters of Favour deriv'd from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but all Acts of Severity they put off to ſubordinate Agents. But God will not ſtand on ſuch Points, he rather profeſſeth to lay claim to all the memorable Acts of Vengeance upon ſinful Nations and People. It is He that ſhakes terribly the Earth, and rends the Rocks, and makes the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains tremble; who overturns Cities and Countries, as in an Inſtant; who ſwallows up <hi>many hundreds</hi> and <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> of <hi>Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Families</hi> at once: And ſhall not we who hear of it, ſtand in a we of him? We ſhould ſay on ſuch an Occaſion, <hi>Who hath an Arm like
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58544:30"/>God?</hi> We ſhould conſider, <hi>Who can ſtand before him, when he is angry?</hi> Who can contend with him? Who would not tremble in his Preſence? He who can caſt Soul and Body into Hell in a moment, can as ſoon cauſe his Earth to open, and ſwallow up the ſtrongeſt, the largeſt, the moſt populous City upon Earth, and turn it into a Heap of Aſhes, or a Pool of Water: Ought not this God to be feared?</p>
               <p>When <hi>his right Hand does teach him terrible things,</hi> ſhall not the Queſtion then be put, as <hi>Job</hi> 12.9. <hi>Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that the Hand of the Lord has wrought this?</hi> When he <hi>ſhakes the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> and <hi>melts the Mountains,</hi> and <hi>cleaves the Valleys,</hi> as <hi>Wax before the Fire,</hi> and as <hi>VVaters poured down a ſteep Place,</hi> Mich. 1.4. he ſeemeth to ſay, <hi>I will work, and who ſhall let? I will deſtroy, and who ſhall ſave?</hi> I will lay my Hand, ſays God, upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> and I will bring my People thence <hi>by my great Judgments.</hi> And it follows, <hi>The Egyptians ſhall know that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58544:31"/>I am the Lord,</hi> Exod. 7.4, 5. The Greatneſs and Terribleneſs of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, in ſuch caſes, beſpeaks God to be the Author of it. Man cannot but take notice of His Hand, and inquire, <hi>Wherefore has the Lord done this,</hi> and <hi>what means the Heat of this great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi> Deut. 29.24. With God is <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Majeſty;</hi> he is <hi>Almighty,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find him out.—<hi>Men do therefore fear him,</hi> Job 37.22, 23, 24.</p>
               <p>When he makes the Mountains tremble, and the Earth ſhake, our Hearts ſhould <hi>tremble</hi> too. <hi>Fear ye not me, ſays the Lord? and will ye not trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at my Preſence?</hi> Jer. 5.22. Will ye not fear me, who can open the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taracts of Heaven <hi>above,</hi> or break up the Fountains of the great Deep <hi>below,</hi> and pour forth whole Floods of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance when I pleaſe; who can rain Hell out of Heaven, or kindle thoſe Exhalations and Steams that are in the Bowels and Caverns of the <hi>Earth,</hi> (as I cauſe Thunder by giving Fire to thoſe in the <hi>Clouds</hi>) and make them force
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58544:31"/>their way, to the Overthrow and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Villages, and Towns, and Cities, and Countries, whenever I will; who can thus ſuddenly turn a fruitful populous Land, into an ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Spectacle of Deſolation and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine?</p>
               <p>If God but write bitter things upon the Wall againſt <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> his Loins are looſed, and his Knees knock one againſt another. The great Emperour <hi>Caligula</hi> runs under the Bed at the noiſe of God's Tabernacle, his thundring Voice. And certainly God's ſhaking the Earth, in ſo terrible a manner as of late, may much more make us trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. To this purpoſe it is elegantly deſcribed by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Fear, and the Pit, and the Snare are upon thee, O Inhabitant of the Earth. And it ſhall come to paſs, that he who fleeth from the noiſe of the Fear, ſhall fall into the Pit; and he that cometh up out of the midſt of the Pit, ſhall be taken in the Snare: for the Windows from on high are open, and the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58544:32"/>of the Earth do ſhake. The Earth is utterly broken down, the Earth is clean diſſolv'd, the Earth is mov'd exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the Earth ſhall reel to and fro like a Drunkard, and ſhall be removed like a Cottage; and the Tranſgreſſion thereof ſhall be heavy upon it; and it ſhall fall, and not riſe again.</hi> Upon ſuch Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtations of Divine Power and Juſtice, we may well cry out, <hi>Great and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous are thy Works, O Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty! VVho would not fear thee, and glorify thy Name, when thy Judgments are thus manifeſt?</hi> Rev. 15.3, 4.</p>
               <p>Such a Judgment as <hi>this</hi> of <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,</hi> is eſpecially proper to affect us with an awful Fear of God, of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> his <hi>Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion,</hi> his <hi>Soveraignty</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi> He cauſed the Mountain to quake at the Delivery of the Law, when he would prove to the Jews that he was their Lord and Soveraign. When the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion</hi> obſerved the <hi>Earthquake,</hi> at the Death of Chriſt, <hi>He,</hi> and others <hi>feared greatly,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Truly this was the Son of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:58544:32"/>
               <p>To this purpoſe we may conſider the <hi>Earthquake</hi> that did hinder the Attempt of rebuilding the
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Amm. Marcell.</hi> Hiſt. l. 23. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> Orat. 2. c. Jud. <hi>Socrates,</hi> l. 3. c. 17. <hi>Sozomen,</hi> l. 5. c. 21.</note> Jewiſh Temple, which the Emperour <hi>Julian</hi> ſet afoot to ſpight the Chriſtians, and to contradict the Prophecy of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and to oppoſe <hi>Moſes</hi> unto Chriſt. He gave all Encouragement to the Jews, he provided them with all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials at his own charge. They with great Joy and Readineſs ſet about it. But when they began to ſearch the Ground, in order to the laying of the Foundation, the Earth round about trembles with a horrible <hi>Earthquake,</hi> and the Flames on a ſudden break out, which not only conſumed the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, but a multitude of Spectators too, and the Materials prepared for the Building. This made an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Aſtoniſhment, and ſtruck <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf with ſome Fear; ſo that he gave over the Attempt, and many of the Jews were perſwaded to receive
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58544:33"/>the Faith of Chriſt. About the ſame time, the Pagan Temple at <hi>Delphos</hi> was deſtroyed by Earthquakes, Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning. Such Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Power challenge our Fear. <hi>He looketh on the Earth, and it trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth; he toucheth the Hills, and they ſmoak,</hi> Nahum 1.5. <hi>The Mountains quake before him, and the Hills melt; he removeth the Mountains, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth them in his Anger; he ſhaketh the Earth out of its place, and the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars thereof tremble,</hi> Job 9.5.</p>
               <p>And the rather ſhould we fear in ſuch Caſes, becauſe they are often ſet forth as God's Judicial Act. Theſe fiery Meteors are turned by God's Counſel, for <hi>Correction</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> Job 37. <hi>The Earth ſhook and trembled, the Foundations of the Hills were moved and ſhaken,
<note n="*" place="bottom">See more of this in the following Chapters.</note> BECA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE HE WAS WROTH. There went up a Smoak out of his Noſtrils, and Fire out of his Mouth devoured; Coals were kindled by it;</hi> Pſal. 18.7, 8. <hi>I will ſhake the Heavens, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58544:33"/>the Earth ſhall remove out of its place, in the VVrath of the Lord of Hoſts, and in the Day of his fierce Anger;</hi> Iſa. 13.13. This is brought in, after God had ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>I will puniſh the VVorld for their Evil, and the VVicked for their Inquity. I will cauſe the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy of the Proud to ceaſe, and will lay low the Haughtineſs of the Terrible.</hi> Again, <hi>Tremble thou Earth at the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, at the Preſence of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114.7. <hi>VVho can ſtand before his Indignation, or abide the Fierceneſs of his Anger? His Fury burns like Fire, and the Rocks are thrown down by him,</hi> Nahum 1.6. Thou ſhalt be <hi>viſited by the Lord of Hoſts, with Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and with Earthquakes,</hi> Iſa. 29.6. that is, penally, and judicially viſited.</p>
               <p>There are other Conſiderations, that ſhould make this Judgment of <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes</hi> the more affecting: As, <hi>the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Warning</hi> they are commonly attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with; and <hi>the ſurprizing Effects</hi> that follow, able to aſtoniſh the moſt valiant <hi>Men of War,</hi> and make the moſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58544:34"/>couragious Spirits ſink and fall: For ſo <hi>they</hi> are repreſented, as <hi>trembling</hi> on this Account, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.15.</p>
               <p>When the Judgment comes unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly, as a Thief in the Night: When God viſits a People by <hi>terrible things in Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſuch as they looked not for: When,</hi> to uſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's words, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Hell has enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it ſelf, and opened her Mouth without meaſure; and their Glory, and their Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and their Pomp, and he that rejoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth deſcends into it.</hi> When there is no Time to flee, or Method to eſcape, or Poſſibility to reſiſt; when no Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, or Refuge remains; no Shelter is to be found in the higheſt Towers, or the loweſt Cellars; when the Earth opens on a ſudden, and becomes the Grave of whole Families, Streets, and Cities; and effects this in leſs time than you are able to tell the ſtory of it; either ſending out a Flood of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to drown, or vomiting out Flames of Fire to conſume them; or cloſing again upon them, that they die by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58544:34"/>Suffocation, or Famine, if not by the Ruins of their own Dwelling. When Parents and Children, Husbands and Wives, Maſters and Servants, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and Miniſters, and People, without difference or diſtinction, in the midſt of Health, and Peace, and Buſineſs, are buried in <hi>a Common Ruin,</hi> and paſs <hi>All together</hi> into the Eternal World; and there is only the difference of a few Hours or Minutes between a famous City and none at all; They that have been in the Neighbourhood of ſuch Tragedies, and beheld the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Effects of ſuch a Judgment on O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and yet have been preſerved, cannot but conſider it with trembling. Our own ſerious Thoughts may help to affect us in like manner. Thus the late Earthquake at <hi>Jamaica</hi> happened in a clear Day, without Warning or Suſpicion; and in the ſpace of <hi>three minutes,</hi> the Town of <hi>Port-Royal</hi> was ſhaken and ſhattered to pieces, and ſunk into the Sea, and the greateſt part of it under Water.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58544:35"/>
               <p>Now if it be dreadful to have our Country the Seat of <hi>VVar,</hi> as they, whoſe Caſe that is, will tell us, and we muſt preſently grant; <hi>this</hi> is yet more diſmal, that in the midſt of Peace brings a worſe Ruine than the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of War. If <hi>a raging Peſtilence</hi> be dreadful, that ſweeps away thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in a Day, and ten thouſands in a Night, as ſome of you can remember; If <hi>a conſuming Fire</hi> be an amazing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which you of this City have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced; an <hi>Earthquake</hi> is not leſs, but <hi>more ſo;</hi> when Houſes and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, Towns and Cities, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are all deſtroyed at one Stroke, in a few Minutes. <hi>Dat ſignum Ruina;</hi> Death is the only Preſage of ſuch a Judgment; without giving Leiſure to prepare for <hi>another World,</hi> or Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to look for any Shelter in <hi>this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who doth not ſtart at the thought of ſuch a Trembling of the Earth? The more a Man knows, the more is his Aſtoniſhment. <hi>He hangeth the Earth upon nothing,</hi> Job 26.7. For a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58544:35"/>Man to feel the Earth, which hangeth upon nothing, (but as ſome vaſt Ball in the midſt of a thin yielding Air) totter under him, how can his Soul chuſe but be poſſeſs'd with a ſecret Fright and Confuſion? Methinks I tremble but to think of ſuch a Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. — <q>I deſign not, ſaith Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Hall</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Sermon on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 60.2.</note>, to aſtoniſh you with the Relation of the fearful Effects which Earthquakes have produc'd in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as it were eaſy to do out of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and Philoſophical Diſcourſes, where you may ſee Rocks torn in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Mountains not caſt down only but removed; Hills raiſed not out of Vallies only, but out of Seas; Fires breaking out of Waters, Stones and Cinders belched up, Rivers changed, Seas diſlodg'd, Earth opening, Towns ſwallowed up, and many other ſuch hideous Events. Of which kind our own Memory can furniſh us with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any at home, altho theſe colder Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58544:36"/>are more rarely infeſted with ſuch frightful Accidents.</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>In what Condition can a Man be ſafe, ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Epiſt. 23. Nat. Quaeſt. lib. 5. c. 1.</note>, ſpeaking of <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,</hi> when the World it ſelf is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and the only thing that paſſes for fixed and unmovable in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, trembles, and deceives us? Whither ſhall we fly for Security, if whereſoever we are, the Danger be ſtill under our Feet? Upon the crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Houſe, every Man takes himſelf to his Heels, and leaves all to ſave himſelf. But what Retreat is there, where that which ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us, fails us; when the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not only of Cities, but even of the World it ſelf, opens and wavers? What Help, or what Comfort, where Fear it ſelf can never carry us off? An Enemy may be kept at a diſtance with a Wall; a Caſtle may put a ſtop to an Army; a Port may protect us
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58544:36"/>from the Fury of a Tempeſt; Fire it ſelf doth not follow him that runs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from it; a Vault may defend us againſt Thunder; and we may quit the Place in a Peſtilence: There is ſome Remedy in all theſe Evils. Or however, no Man ever knew a whole Nation deſtroyed by Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. A Plague may unpeople a Town, but it will not carry it away. There is no Evil of ſuch an Extent, ſo Inevitable, ſo Greedy, and ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly Calamitous, as an <hi>Earthquake:</hi> For it does not only devour Houſes, Families, and ſingle Towns, but ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines whole Countries and Nations; either overturning, or ſwallowing them up, without ſo much as leaving any Footſtep or Mark of what they were. Some People have a greater Horror for this Death than any other: <hi>To be taken away Alive, out of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Living;</hi> as if all Mortals by what Means ſoever were not to come to the ſame End, Death.— And 'tis not a Pin matter, whether I
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58544:37"/>am cruſh'd to pieces by one Stone, or by a whole Mountain; whether I periſh by the fall of an Houſe, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Burden of the whole Earth; whether I be ſwallowed up alone, or with a thouſand more for company.</p>
                  <p>We ſhould therefore arm our ſelves againſt that Blow, that can neither be avoided or foreſeen. And it is not the forſwearing thoſe Places that we find infeſted with Earthquakes, that will do our buſineſs; for there is no Place that can be warranted againſt them. What if the Earth be not yet moved? It is ſtill movable; for the whole Body of it lies under the ſame Law, and expos'd to Danger; only ſome part at one time, and ſome at another. As it is in Great Cities, where all the Houſes are ſubject to Ruin, tho they do not all fall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So in the Body of the Earth; now this Part fails, and then that. <hi>Tyre</hi> was formerly ſubject to Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes: In <hi>Aſia</hi> twelve Cities were ſwallowed up in a Night: <hi>Achaid</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58544:37"/>and <hi>Macedonia</hi> have had their turns, and now <hi>Campagnia.</hi> The Fate goes round, and ſtrikes at laſt where it hath a great while paſſed by. It falls out oftner, 'tis true, in ſome Places than in others: But no Place is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally free and exempt. And it is not only Men, but Cities, Coaſts, nay the Shores, and the very Sea it ſelf, that ſuffer under the Dominion of Fate. And yet we are ſo vain as to promiſe our ſelves ſome ſort of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Goods of Fortune; never conſidering that the very Ground we ſtand upon, is unſtable. And it is not the Frailty of this or that Place, but the Quality of every Spot of it; for not one Inch of it is ſo compacted, as not to admit many Cauſes of its Reſolution. And tho the Bulk of the Earth remain entire, the Parts of it may yet be broken.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus the Pagan Philoſophers prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves, and others, for theſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, as for Diſorders that were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable; and did not trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58544:38"/>with the Thought of Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which chaſtiſeth Men by theſe dreadful Puniſhments. But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, whoſe Opinions were not ſo corrupted, reverenc'd the Anger of Heaven in theſe Calamities; and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Safety in Superſtition, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to appeaſe the Evil Spirits by Sacrifice, and ſo provoked the Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God the more. Chriſtians who are inſtructed in a better School, own theſe Diſaſters as the Puniſhment of Sin.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>And of all the Animadverſions that Divine Juſtice gives Men, there is none more Horrid, or leſs Evitable than this of
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Senault,</hi> of the Corruption of Nature by Sin, <hi>Treat.</hi> 6th, <hi>Diſc.</hi> 7th.</note> 
                     <hi>Earthquakes.</hi> For what Aſſurance can we hope for here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if the Earth quake under our Feet? Where can we think to eſcape Danger, if the moſt ſolid thing of all the World do ſhake? if that which ſuſtains all other Things about us,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58544:38"/>threaten us with ſinking under our Feet? What Sanctuary ſhall we find to defend us from an Evil, that doth encompaſs us round? And whither can we withdraw, if the Gulphs, which open themſelves, ſhut up our Paſſages on all ſides? With what Horror are Men ſtruck, when they hear the Earth groan? when her Trembling ſucceeds her Complaints, when Houſes are looſned from their Foundations, when the Roofs fall upon their Heads, and the Pavement ſinks under their Feet? What Hope is there to be had in ſo General a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, when Fear cannot be fenc'd by Flight? In other Caſes there is ſome Outlet whereby to eſcape an Evil: An Enemy is beaten from the Bulwark he had poſſeſs'd himſelf of; Earthworks are oppoſed to the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Canon; Winds which raiſe Tempeſts, deliver us from 'em, and after having a long time toſs'd us to and fro, they caſt us on the Shore: Houſes ſerve us for Sanctuaries againſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58544:39"/>the Injuries of the Air and Weather. —If a Man will reſign his Goods to the Fire, he may ſecure his Perſon. Thunder hurts not thoſe who hide themſelves in Caverns. When the Peſtilence infects whole Cities, we may ſhun the Contagion by going into the Country; and if it diſpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Towns, it doth not throw down the Houſes. But an Earthquake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſeth what it overthrows; and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges War, not with ſome few Houſes only, but whole Provinces; and ſometimes leaves nothing behind it, to inform Poſterity of its Outrages: more inſolent than Fire, which ſpares Rocks; more greedy than the Sea, which vomits up Shipwracks; more cruel than the Conqueror, who ſpares Walls: it ſwallows and devours what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it overturns.—The Sea is ſubject to its Empire; and Mariners confeſs, that thoſe Storms are moſt dangerous, which are occaſioned by Earthquakes.—</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58544:39"/>
                  <p>This Misfortune is common to all Kingdoms, ſince Man became Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal: all Parts of the Earth are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come moveable; and Stedfaſtneſs muſt no longer be look'd for in the World, ſince Innocency is baniſh'd thence by Injuſtice. This Diſorder is the Puniſhment of our Sin; and Reaſon as well as Faith, doth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently aſſure us, that the Univerſe would never have been agitated with theſe furious Accidents, during the State of Original Righteouſneſs. Wherefore ſhould God's Anger have armed the Elements againſt his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and obedient Subjects? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould he have overthrown all his Works, to deſtroy Innocent Men? Why ſhould it have overwhelm'd the Inhabitants of the Earth with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines thereof, if they had not been ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? Why ſhould it have <hi>buried</hi> thoſe in the Bowels of the Earth, who were not to <hi>die?</hi> Let us then conclude that Earthquakes are the Effects of <hi>Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58544:40"/>
               <p>Such <hi>ſudden Inſtances</hi> of Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are threatned in Scripture as ſome of the <hi>moſt terrible;</hi> and therefore the higheſt Severity is expreſs'd by ſuch <hi>unexpected</hi> and <hi>ſudden Strokes:</hi> They are ſet forth ſometimes by <hi>the Breach of a Wall,</hi> that catcheth a Man 'ere he be aware, and cruſheth him in pieces, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.12, 13. Sometimes reſembled to <hi>a Whirlwind,</hi> that comes ſuddenly, and carries all before it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God threatens, that obſtinate and incurable Sinners ſhall be <hi>deſtroyed at once,</hi> or ſhall be <hi>ſuddenly deſtroyed, and that without Remedy,</hi> Prov. 29.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Such Inſtances of Divine Severity ſhould teach us to reverence and adore the Divine Power, and Providence; ſhould awaken us to Repentance, excite most earnest Prayer, occaſion Thankfulneſs for our Preſervation hitherto, and call upon us to truſt in God as our only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and to ſecure his Favour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58544:40"/>
               <p>LET us further conſider, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch Appearances of God, it becomes us to be thus affected, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Duty.</hi> If we have any becoming Apprehenſions of the Divine Power, and the Terrors of his Wrath; If we have any Concern at his Diſpleaſure, and the Manifeſtations of it; If we have any thing of that Tenderneſs of Spirit, that <hi>Heart of Fleſh,</hi> which is the great Bleſſing of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, we ought to evidence it on ſuch Occaſions, by <hi>ſutable Affections,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Improvement of theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences for our own Advantage. For inſtance,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To reverence the <hi>Divine Power,</hi> and <hi>Providence;</hi> to confirm our Minds in the Belief of it; <hi>That verily there is a God that judgeth in the Earth; That we may ſee, and know, and underſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that the Hand of the Lord has done this, and the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath created it: That God hath not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Earth, but makes himſelf known
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58544:41"/>by the Judgments that he executes.</hi> And when they are thus <hi>manifeſt,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>All Nations ſhall worſhip before thee, O Lord,</hi> Rev. 15.4. &amp; 19.2. So when God executes Judgment on the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by ſudden Calamity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.7, 8, 9. it is added at the 11th Verſe, that <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon</hi> a Man ſhall ſay, <hi>Verily there is a Reward for the Righteous, verily there is a God that judgeth in the Earth.</hi> If he did not ſometimes appear in ſuch Acts of Juſtice, Men would be ready to ſay, <hi>Where is the God of Judgment? Mal.</hi> 2.17. or with them, <hi>Job</hi> 9.24. <hi>The Earth is given into the Hand of the Wicked; if not, where, or who is he? Where is he,</hi> who ſhould puniſh them? <hi>Who is he,</hi> that calls them to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? And the wiſe Man hath told us, that <hi>becauſe Sentence againſt an evil Doer is not ſpeedily executed, therefore the Heart of the Sons of Men is fully ſet in them to do Evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11.</p>
               <p>But when he looketh on the Earth, and makes it tremble; when he touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Hills, and they ſmoke, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:58544:41"/>104.32. When <hi>he ſhows himſelf to be wiſe in Heart, and mighty in Strength, he removeth Mountains, and they know it not; he overturneth them in his Anger.</hi> Who would not then reverence his Power, and Providence? Read <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. for an Inſtance of it.</p>
               <p>Even the Heathens have condemn'd thoſe for mad Men, and diſtracted, who would fear nothing, no not an <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> as it is
<note n="*" place="bottom">Petri Victor. Comment. in Ariſt. de Moribus, lib. 3. p. 160.</note> obſerved by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> concerning the <hi>Celtae,</hi> a barbarous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Which makes it the more ſtrange that <hi>Seneca</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">Seneca Quaeſt. nat. lib. 6. cap. 3.</note> ſhould be ſo much at a loſs, about the Divine Agency in ſuch things, and aſcribe them only to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cauſes. Whereas <hi>Cicero</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="bottom">Cicero de Nat. Deorum, l. 2. §. 13. <hi>mentions</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes, <hi>and other of the</hi> Stoicks <hi>to be of the ſame Opinion. See</hi> Leſcoloper, <hi>in</hi> Cic. de Nat. Deorum, p. 227.</note> reckons Earthquakes, with Thunder, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be one of the four Ways by which the Notion of <hi>a God</hi> is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58544:42"/>in the World, and the Minds of Men awed with the Apprehenſion of the Divine Being.</p>
               <p>By ſuch Acts of Judgment and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance God is ſaid <hi>to ſhow himſelf,</hi> Pſal. 94.1, 2. to confute the Atheiſm of the World, and make Men acknowledg his Being and Providence. By ſuch things Men <hi>are made to know,</hi> that <hi>God ruleth in</hi> Jacob, <hi>unto the Ends of the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 58.13. Thus was <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> brought to acknowledg God, who at firſt deſpiſed him, ſaying, <hi>VVho is the Lord, that I ſhould obey him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us <hi>take heed of the like Sins,</hi> that others have been guilty of, with whom God has dealt in ſuch Severity. Let us remember, He is a holy God, and jealous of his Honour, and will not ſuffer high Provocations always to go unpuniſhed. Others have ſmarted, who were guilty of ſuch and ſuch Tranſgreſſions, as are found amongſt us: Why ſhould we expect to eſcape, if we continue under <hi>the like Guilt?</hi> By Judgments upon one Nation, God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58544:42"/>warns Another, that except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, they may expect to periſh. Thus Tyrus <hi>ſhall be devoured with Fire,</hi> Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelon (ſays God) <hi>ſhall ſee it and fear;</hi> Gaza <hi>and</hi> Ekron <hi>ſhall be very ſorrowful, Zech.</hi> 9.3, 4, 5. When <hi>Jonah</hi> was thrown over-board, and the Storm quell'd, <hi>the Men feared the Lord exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,</hi> and offered <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> in the ſenſe of their own Sins. Much more, when God executes Remarkable Judgments on ſuch as are notoriouſly wicked. All Men will fear, and declare theſe Works of God, if they wiſely conſider of his Doings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.9. If we will not be warned by the Examples of Others, we may expect to be made <hi>Examples</hi> our ſelves. <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the Cities of the Plain, are ſet forth as <hi>an Example</hi> unto us, <hi>Jud.</hi> 7. <hi>The Man that will do preſumptuouſly, even that Man ſhall die,</hi> Deut. 17.12, 13. <hi>And all the People ſhall hear, and fear, and do no more preſumptuouſly.</hi> God ſingled out the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe Blood <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their Sacrifices, and thoſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58544:43"/>on whom the Tower of <hi>Siloam</hi> fell, to tell the Jews, except they did <hi>repent,</hi> they ſhould alſo periſh: And within a few Years, upon their neglect of theſe inſtructive Examples, Thouſands and ten Thouſands of them had <hi>their Blood,</hi> as it were, <hi>mingled with their Sacrifices;</hi> being ſlain by Multitudes in the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> the Place of their Offerings; and no leſs Number periſhing in the Fall and Ruine of their <hi>Walls,</hi> and <hi>Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> battered down by the <hi>Romans.</hi> When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> round about ſaw <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company devoured of the Earth, they ran away at the Cry of them, and ſaid, <hi>Leſt the Earth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By what we have ſeen of God's Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity on Others, we ſhould run away trembling from the Gulph of God's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Judgments, by running from thoſe Sins, which may bring the like on us, which Others have felt. 'Twas the great Aggravation of <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>'s Pride, that he humbled not himſelf, tho he knew the Judgment God had
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58544:43"/>executed on his <hi>Father</hi> for that very Sin. He that will run into a Bog, wherein Others have plunged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in his view, is guilty of double Folly, of adventuring raſhly, and of not taking warning. <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells us, that upon the Statue of <hi>Zenacherib,</hi> after the Angel of the Lord had ſlain <hi>an hundred and eighty five thouſand</hi> of his Army, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.36. it was engraven, <q>Diſcite Juſtitiam moniti, &amp; non tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Divos:</q> 
                  <hi>Let him that looks on me, learn to fear God.</hi> He hath a thouſand other Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in reſerve, if the ſame we ſee inflicted on Others, do not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take Us. Not only ſtormy Winds and Tempeſts are in his Treaſury, that he can rain Snares, and Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and an horrible Tempeſt on the Wicked; but he has Arrows of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Quiver of <hi>various ſorts,</hi> or is able to repeat the ſame, when he pleaſeth. God will never want Ways
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58544:44"/>and Methods to puniſh a wicked Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. All Creatures in the Earth, and Air, and Sea, are his Servants. He hath Hoſts and Armies of them, above and under Ground, to be the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let it excite our more <hi>earneſt Prayers</hi> for <hi>Preſervation,</hi> and <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> from ſuch Judgments, as others have ſuffered by. We ſee, if God be not for us, but againſt us, how ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, how dreadfully he can puniſh, and deſtroy any People. How earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould we pray, <hi>Lord, ſpare thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and deliver us from ſudden Death.</hi> The louder, and the more repeated our Warnings are, and the juſter our Fears of approaching Calamity, the more importunately ſhould we pray, as that <hi>Captain,</hi> 2 Kings 1.13, 14. When <hi>two</hi> before him, with their <hi>Fifties,</hi> had been deſtroyed, fell upon his Knees before the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>O Man of God, let my Life, and the Lives of theſe fifty of thy Servants be precious in thy ſight: Behold, there came Fire from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58544:44"/>and burnt up the two Captains with the former Fifties; O let my Life be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in thy ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us pray for the <hi>Diverſion</hi> of ſuch Judgments, but endeavour to form our Spirits to a Preparedneſs for the whole good Pleaſure of God; and bring them to a conditional <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will, as to our own Share in any National Deliverance we pray for. We muſt own that we deſerve, that the overflowing Scourge ſhould not paſs away from us, and that we know not whether it ſhall or no; but we ought to pray alway, <hi>Father, glorify thine own Name, and help us to glorify it; and let us be pleaſed that thou ſhouldſt do ſo, in thine own Way; which we are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges of.</hi> We lie at thy Foot, and own that thou art Juſt, and Wiſe, and Holy, and infinitely ſo: <hi>Lord, ſave us, if it be conſiſtent with thy Glory to ſave ſuch a People: And help us to adore thee in the way of thy unſearchable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if by that Method thou wilt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy thy ſelf.</hi> We are not fit to judg of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58544:45"/>God's Works of Providence; nor can we comprehend how far his Glory, in the Accompliſhment of his Great and Eternal Purpoſes, may be ſubſerv'd, and promoted by ſuch Temporal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, as we would deprecate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us <hi>thankfully</hi> own our <hi>preſent Safety,</hi> our <hi>Preſervation</hi> hitherto, that when others have been deſtroyed, we are yet ſpared. God manifeſted glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Power in making the Earth to ſhake; but it was free Mercy that it did <hi>but ſhake</hi> and tremble <hi>in our Iſland.</hi> His ſovereign Mercy has hitherto made a Difference between Us and other People: we are ſpared, when other Countries are deſtroyed. Let us ſtand, and behold the <hi>Severity</hi> of God on them; but adore his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> unto us, that we are not ſurprized in our Sins. He is Righteous in all his Ways, and Holy in all his Works. He is a God of Truth, and without Iniquity; Juſt and Right is he. So we muſt own him in his moſt terrible Judgments on Others. But to Us he is a God of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58544:45"/>and Long-ſuffering, and ſo we muſt acknowledg and adore him. How did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> triumph in the God of their Salvation, when they eſcaped, and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were drowned? Why might not thoſe of <hi>Jamaica</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> have been warned by <hi>our Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> as we are admoniſhed by <hi>theirs?</hi> How is it, that God has not inlarged, or repeated the Commiſſion of the <hi>Earthquake</hi> amongſt us, that did but gently give us notice of what he might have done? Let us bleſs God, that he did not ſhake the Earth, ſo as to open and ſwallow us up quick; and that he has not repeated it, becauſe of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Security ſince: Let us be <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> that when our Houſes rolled, they did not tumble.</p>
               <p>To ſome Countries, and ſome Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he is known by the <hi>Judgments</hi> that he <hi>executes;</hi> but to us and ours by the Judgments that he <hi>diverts.</hi> To us he is known by his adorable Long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, by his manifold Deliverances, notwithſtanding our repeated, aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58544:46"/>Crimes, ſo as to make us even the Wonder of the World: for ſo we are, in that, having ſuch Enemies, and ſuch National Guilt, we have yet ſo many National Bleſſings, to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate from time to time; and the Liberty of doing ſo in publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. God makes himſelf known to our <hi>Neighbours</hi> round about, by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of <hi>War,</hi> by the Barbarity of Souldiers, and the Fury of the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor; and to others in remote Countries, by <hi>deſolating Earthquakes:</hi> But to Us, by merciful <hi>Preſervations,</hi> and many of the Bleſſings of <hi>Peace.</hi> To <hi>Amalek,</hi> and <hi>Edom,</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> he is known by deſtructive Judgments; but in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in <hi>Sion</hi> his Dwelling-place, he makes himſelf known in another manner. Tho the Profeſſion of the Truth, and the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Worſhip of the True God in any Place, is no ſufficient Security a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a Judgment: for how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly was <hi>Antioch</hi> (where the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians) afflicted
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58544:46"/>with Earthquakes; and ſome of the famous ſeven Cities, whence the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches are denominated, deſtroyed by Earthquakes?</p>
               <p>As to <hi>Antioch,</hi> we read, that in the Emperor
<note n="*" place="bottom">Howel<hi>'s General Hiſt.</hi> Vol. 2. p. 883. Dion. Caſſ. Trajan. cap. 18. Dio Xiphilin. Le Sieur Hiſt. del' Egliſe, An. de N. S. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>Trajan</hi>'s time, <hi>A. D.</hi> 115. or according to others, <hi>An.</hi> 111. who ſucceeded <hi>Nerva</hi> in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire, after his Conqueſts in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and his obtaining the Title of <hi>Optimus,</hi> he returned to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and there made ſome ſtay, but was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with a moſt terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, which afflicted other Cities, but eſpecially this, in an unheard-of manner. By the Fall of Houſes, and Rubbiſh, and other means, a vaſt number of People periſh'd; ſo that the Town being full of Strangers, who came thither for Law-ſuits, upon Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, or other Buſineſs, the Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then there all the Winter; there
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58544:47"/>was no Nation that receiv'd not Loſs from ſo great a Calamity. <hi>Trajan</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf eſcaped out of a Window, being it's ſaid, drawn out by one of a more than humane Proportion. And though the Earthquakes ceaſed, he continued in the open Air for many Days. The Hill <hi>Coraſius</hi> was ſo ſhaken, that its higher Parts fell down, and it look'd as if it would tumble on the City. Other Mountains were levelled: Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters broke out where none before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; and Fountains which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poured out Water, were ſtopped up.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time, in <hi>Trajan</hi>'s time, <hi>Oroſius</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="bottom">P. Oroſii Hiſt. l. 7. cap. 12.</note> mentions 103 Cities of <hi>Aſia</hi> overturn'd by Earthquakes. And afterwards, in <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s time,
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cluverius ad An. Dom. 528.</note> 
                  <hi>Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius</hi> mentions another Earthquake at <hi>Antioch,</hi> that deſtroyed above <hi>forty thouſand.</hi> And by
<note n="†" place="bottom">Ib. ad An. Dom. 602.</note> another Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake there, 61 Years after the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58544:47"/>in the time of the Emperor <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius, ſixty thouſand</hi> periſhed.</p>
               <p>The Preſervation of our City and Nation, while others are deſtroyed by this Judgment formerly, and of late, ſhould make us thankful. The like may be amplified as to particular <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> and <hi>Perſons:</hi> the bright Side of the Cloud is to <hi>thee,</hi> while the dark one is to <hi>others:</hi> As a God of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Severity</hi> he appears to <hi>others,</hi> as a God of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to <hi>thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How many Salvations has God wrought for us of late, for <hi>this Nation,</hi> and for <hi>this City;</hi> prolonging our Tranquillity and Peace, and keeping off publick Calamities from us! How often has he diſappointed and defeated our Enemies Deſigns and Attempts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us! It is well if our Ingratitude do not at laſt provoke him to ſay, as to his ancient People; <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.11, 12, 13. <hi>Did I not deliver you from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yet you have forſaken me, therefore will I deliver you no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:58544:48"/>
               <p n="5">5. Let it awaken us, <hi>to clear up our Intereſt in God, as our only Refuge and Shelter.</hi> If he be our God in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, we need not fear, though the Earth be removed, and the Mountains be caſt into the Sea; <hi>though the VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereof roar and be troubled, though the Mountains ſhake with the ſwelling thereof,</hi> Pſal. 46.1. Our Hearts may be <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> and <hi>fixed, truſting in the Lord,</hi> ſo as <hi>not to fear any evil Tidings, Pſal.</hi> 112.7, 8. We may poſſeſs our Souls in Peace; for God will keep them in <hi>perfect Peace, whoſe Minds are ſtayed on the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 26.3. They may ſay when it thunders, It is the Voice of my Father; and when the Earth trembles, It is the Tread of his Foot: or with <hi>David, The Lord is my Refuge, the Lord is my Habitation, what need I be afraid?</hi> Pſal. 91.9. <hi>A Refuge</hi> is a Place of Retreat and Safety in a time of <hi>VVar: An Habitation</hi> is a Place of Abode in a time of <hi>Peace:</hi> At all <hi>Times</hi> and in all <hi>Conditions</hi> ſuch are provided for: The Lord is <hi>my hiding-Place and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58544:48"/>my Shield,</hi> therefore will <hi>I hope in his VVord,</hi> Pſal. 119.114. He will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther keep me out of Danger, or defend me when I am expoſed to it: either what I fear ſhall not overtake me, God will be <hi>my hiding-Place;</hi> or if it do come, it ſhall not hurt me, God will be <hi>my Shield.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has promiſed to be with me in the <hi>Fire,</hi> and in the <hi>VVater:</hi> He has bid me not to be diſmayed; <hi>for I am with thee, I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen and help thee, and uphold thee with the right Hand of my Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 41.10. and 42.2. He will cover me with his <hi>Feathers,</hi> and under his <hi>VVings</hi> I ſhall be ſafe: I may <hi>abide un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Shadow, and dwell ſafely from the Fear of Evil.</hi> Now it is one great End of ſuch extraordinary Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of God, to bring Men to adore and ſeek after God: <hi>Joel</hi> 2.30. <hi>I will ſhew VVonders in the Heavens, and in the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>before the great and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Day of the Lord; and whoſoever ſhall call on his Name, ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58544:49"/>
               <p>Our Buſineſs therefore is to make <hi>Peace</hi> with God; to acquaint our ſelves with God, and <hi>be at Peace with him;</hi> and then Good ſhall come unto us, and <hi>the Almighty himſelf ſhall be our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> ſo as we need not fear, <hi>Job</hi> 22.21. Let what will come to paſs, ſuch ſhall be <hi>ſafe</hi> who are under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Love and Care of God. And it is his <hi>Preſence</hi> alone is able to ſecure us. Good Men have always thought ſo, even when they had the greateſt Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for outward Security: <hi>O Lord, we rest on thee alone,</hi> ſays <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2 Chron. 14.8. When he had <hi>an Army</hi> that bare Targets and Spears out of <hi>Judah,</hi> to the number of <hi>three hundred thouſand,</hi> and near as many out of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> that bare Shields and drew Bows, <hi>viz. two hundred and fourſcore thouſand;</hi> yet he overlooks all this, and reſts on <hi>God alone.</hi> So did <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> 2 Chron. 17.14, 15, 16. with an Army of <hi>eleven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; threeſcore thouſand fighting Men,</hi> beſides his Gariſons; and yet <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.12. he ſays, <hi>VVe have no Might againſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58544:49"/>thoſe that come against us, but our Eyes are unto thee.</hi> Eleven hundred and threeſcore thouſand fighting Men in the Field, and yet had no Might but what he expected from the Preſence of God. All our Stability and Safety de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon God as our Keeper. If it be asked, Is it in your Armies, and Officers, and Commanders? they muſt ſay, <hi>No,</hi> it is not in us. Is it in your Fleets, and Navies, and Admirals? It muſt be ſaid, It is not in them. Is it in your Allies and Confederates? It muſt be ſaid ſtill, It is not in them. In your Caſtles, and Gariſons, and Fortifications, in the Situation of your Country, or the Numbers of your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is not in them. In no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Power, Policy, Cunning, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencies abroad, or Councils at home; nothing but <hi>in God,</hi> who is the Keeper of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and therefore to be at <hi>Peace</hi> with him is our <hi>only Safety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If he be our Rock and Refuge, we may depend on him, and find Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; all other Foundations and Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58544:50"/>are weak and tottering; <hi>but the Foundation of God ſtands ſure: The Lord knoweth who are his,</hi> and he can and will take Care of them, though the Earth tremble under your Feet, or you ſink into the Bowels of it. He can own and diſtinguiſh you even in ſuch a Calamity, by a temporal Salvation, as <hi>An.</hi> 1584. when a certain Hill near <hi>Berne</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> was violently removed by an Earthquake, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a whole Village that had <hi>ninety</hi> Families in it, one half Houſe only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, wherein the Maſter of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily was praying, with his Wife and Children:
<note n="*" place="bottom">Polani Syntagma, <hi>p.</hi> 841.</note> 
                  <hi>Polanus</hi> relates it, who lived in thoſe Parts. By an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wherein <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand</hi> Men periſh'd, <hi>An.</hi> 1509. many of the <hi>Turkiſh Moſques</hi> fell, but the <hi>Chriſtian Temples</hi> ſtood firm.
<note n="‖" place="bottom">An. 1663. in Inſula <hi>Canada</hi> horrendi Terrae motus ſentiuntur. Haec Tempeſtas ingentem Terrarum tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum infeſtavit: &amp; Barbaros, <hi>Chriſtianis interim incolumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> gravi damno affecit. <hi>Cluverius,</hi> p. 868.</note> And
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58544:50"/>other Inſtances may be given of the like.</p>
               <p>God is an unchangeable Refuge, and by Intereſt in him we are ſure of <hi>a Building not made with Hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi> Though our earthly Dwellings ſhould be ſwallowed up, our Souls are ſafe, our Portion is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure: for when this earthly Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is diſſolved into Duſt, by that or any other Calamity, yet ſhall we not miſs of eternal Bleſſedneſs in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Manſions: And there are no Storms or Tempeſts, no Commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Tremblings there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:58544:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We ought not to Cenſure others, becauſe of ſuch Calamities, as</hi> greater Sinners <hi>than thoſe who eſcape: much leſs ſhould we paſs a Judgment on their</hi> Eternal State, <hi>becauſe they are cut off</hi> ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>by</hi> a temporal Judgment.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO apply this: 1. Let us not then <hi>excuſe</hi> or <hi>encourage</hi> our ſelves, by <hi>cenſuring</hi> others, as <hi>greater Sinners than we,</hi> on whom more terrible Judgments have been inflicted: For <hi>except we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, we muſt</hi> alſo <hi>periſh.</hi> This is the expreſs Declaration of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> upon the Account given him of thoſe on whom the Tower of <hi>Siloam</hi> fell, and of the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe Blood <hi>Pilate</hi> had mingled with their Sacrifices, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.5. As to theſe <hi>Galileans</hi> their Crime is not certain: ſome think they brought this Judgment upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their <hi>Sedition,</hi> as conſpiring
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58544:51"/>againſt the Roman Government; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixing ſome Acts of Religion as the Bond of their Conſpiracy; which <hi>Pilate</hi> hearing of, ſurprized them in the Act, and put them to Death: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers think they were the Followers of <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 5. who ſeduced many from their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Roman Emperor; and that they were <hi>Jews</hi> coming up to the Paſſover to ſacrifice, and there he fell upon upon. Others ſuppoſe them to be <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and that they were ſlain, worſhipping in their Temple on <hi>Mount Gerizim;</hi> but called <hi>Galileans,</hi> from <hi>Judas</hi> the Head of the Faction: and the Hatred of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt the <hi>Samaritans</hi> might occaſion that ſevere and bitter Cenſure. Whatever the Occaſion was of their Sufferings, our Lord condemns the Cenſure of them as <hi>greater Sinners</hi> on that Account; for tho ſometimes Men guilty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Sins, are followed with ſuch remarkable Judgments, that it would be ſtupid Impiety not to obſerve the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58544:52"/>Hand of God therein, as in the Caſe of <hi>Herod, Acts</hi> 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet God may chuſe out ſome to be <hi>Examples</hi> and <hi>Warnings</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> who are <hi>not greater Sinners</hi> than they. 'Tis true, ſome Mens Sins are ſo viſible, as to be <hi>open before hand, going before to Judgment,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24. (They are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, manifeſt to the Judgment of all Men, before they come to be laid open at the laſt Day: they go to Judgment before the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners themſelves are brought thither.) When ſuch <hi>notorious Crimes</hi> are follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>extraordinary Puniſhments,</hi> the Connection &amp; Relation between them muſt not be denied: But otherwiſe we ſhould judg charitably of the <hi>Sufferers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt not make a raſh and haſty Judgment of the <hi>Providences</hi> of God, or interpret the Voice of his Rod by uncertain Gueſſes of our own. We may eaſily be too curious in prying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Secrets of Providence; for <hi>his Judgments are a great Deep;</hi> and of many of them we may ſay with <hi>Aſaph,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58544:52"/>VVhen I thought to know this, it was too wonderful for me.</hi> He hath not thought fit to give us a full Account of all his Deſigns and Ends, why ſuch who are not greater Sinners than others, are ſometimes puniſhed more. In ſuch Enquiries we ſhall ſoon get out of our Depth, ſo as to ſwim in Diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſink into Diſtruſt, if we ſuffer our Curioſity to ſtretch it ſelf too far.</p>
               <p>Therefore after <hi>Solomon</hi> had told us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.15. that there is a juſt Man who periſhes in his Righteouſneſs, and a wicked Man on the contrary who prolongeth his Life in his Wickedneſs; he adds in the next Verſe, <hi>Be not righteous over-much, nor make thy ſelf over-wiſe:</hi> that is, do not think thy ſelf <hi>more righteous</hi> than the Perſon to whom ſuch a Judgment befals; nor make thy ſelf <hi>over-wiſe, i.e.</hi> do not pretend to be able infallibly to expound this Riddle, and to know the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Divine Providence in ſuch a Diſpenſation; for <hi>one Event may befal the Righteous and the VVicked,</hi> Eccl. 9.11.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58544:53"/>The great Apoſtle may have his Hand arreſted with a <hi>Viper;</hi> and yet none but <hi>Barbarians</hi> would conclude, upon that Account, that he is follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Divine Vengeance, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.4.</p>
               <p>We read of <hi>twenty ſeven thouſand</hi> killed by the Fall of a Wall at <hi>Aphek,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.30. As ſometimes Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals have been made to God in the high Places of the Field, and yet the Succeſs of the War hath not always been on the juſter Side. The <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> were engaged in an ill Cauſe, and yet were victorious over the other Tribes, <hi>Judg.</hi> 20. The Ark of God hath been taken by the <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> Children are ſometimes cut off for the Sins of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.30. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16, &amp; 17.</p>
               <p>God acts as a Soveraign, in theſe things. The ſucking Infants of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> muſt periſh by the Sword, and their Brains be daſh'd out: And the little Children of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were burnt with their Parents, by Fire from Heaven: Concerning which God ſaith, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20. <hi>I took away
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58544:53"/>Young and Old, as I ſaw good.</hi> He doth what he pleaſeth; and <hi>who can ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, What doſt thou?</hi> He doth not think fit to give us <hi>now</hi> a full Account of all his Matters, or to ſay all that he can in juſtification of his preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; <hi>Job</hi> 33.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.9. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.34. But the Great <hi>Day of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Righteous Judgment of God,</hi> will unriddle all theſe things, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all thoſe Clouds, and remove all thoſe Difficulties that now puzzle us.</p>
               <p>Much leſs ſhould we conclude con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>their Eternal State,</hi> who are cut off by ſome temporal Judgment. We have no Warrant, or Authority to ſit as <hi>Coroners</hi> on the Souls of deceaſed Perſons. It would be very uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conclude, that all the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſhut out of <hi>Heaven,</hi> who died in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and by the righteous Judgment of God were not permitted to enter into <hi>Canaan:</hi> Or that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive <hi>Bethſhemites,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza,</hi> and others that have been ſtruck dead for unwarrantable Actions, did periſh to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58544:54"/>Eternity. There is a Vail of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon many ſuch Works of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: but <hi>what we know not now, we ſhall know hereafter,</hi> John 13.7. Good <hi>Joſiah</hi> may die in a Battel as well as wicked <hi>Ahab;</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> may have a proſperous Reign of <hi>forty Years,</hi> as well as <hi>David.</hi> Eternal Love and Hatred are not known by theſe things. We muſt not conclude a Man to be certainly <hi>wicked,</hi> becauſe he is cut off by a <hi>ſudden Death,</hi> or doth not go to his Grave in Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Think not,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>that they were greater Sinners than others,</hi> who were thus ſuddenly and exemplarily cut off; That is, you cannot <hi>for that Reaſon,</hi> and barely <hi>on that Account,</hi> ſo ſuppoſe, and judg of them. He doth not deny that they were <hi>greater Sinners,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerts that their <hi>greater Sufferings</hi> will not prove that <hi>they were ſo:</hi> For it is agreeable enough to the Wiſdom of Divine Government, (or of any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) that, when many Perſons are <hi>equally guilty,</hi> ſome may be ſelected
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58544:54"/>to be <hi>Examples,</hi> and Warnings to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when others no leſs criminal are ſpared. Other Nations, as bad as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> have not been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by Fire from Heaven. We muſt Adore <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> in the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a wicked People, but his <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty</hi> muſt be owned in the Choice of Subjects. We ſhould be very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to our ſelves, and uncharitable to our Neighbours and Brethren, if we conclude them to be greater Sinners than we, becauſe they have ſuffered more. I repeat this, as knowing that we are very apt to condemn ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are thus Examples in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; &amp; to hug our ſelves, as <hi>more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> than they, becauſe we are ſpared.</p>
               <p>But as to our ſelves, and our own Caſe, we ought to know that God will not always bear to have his merciful Warnings contemned, to have num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs extraordinary Mercies abuſed, to have leſſer Judgments upon us, and his more remarkable Severity upon others, diſregarded. We ought ſtill
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58544:55"/>to remember and conſider it, that, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we repent, we are like to periſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What</hi> Fear <hi>of Evils to come is</hi> lawful, <hi>how far a</hi> Duty, <hi>and when</hi> ſinful. <hi>Of the</hi> Penal Fear <hi>of future Calamity: Inſtances of it as a Divine</hi> Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>What</hi> little Ground <hi>we have to expect a much longer</hi> Reprieve; <hi>we have</hi> none <hi>for</hi> Security, <hi>and</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>The</hi> Doubtfulneſs <hi>of our Caſe ſhould awaken our utmoſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, and Care to prevent Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="2">2. LET us therefore apprehend the Caſe to be exceeding hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous, as to our City and Nation; when we have had ſo many <hi>Warnings,</hi> and are not awakened to <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Reformation.</hi> Beſides the <hi>natural Fear</hi> of approaching Evil, which is not to be condemned as a Fault, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58544:55"/>inevitable, there is a <hi>ſinful Fear</hi> of Evils to come, and of the Tidings of them; proceeding either from Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of God, Forgetfulneſs of his Care, or Diſtruſt of his Providence, or as unſutable to the Nature, Kind, and Degree, and Duration of the Evils we apprehend: Such a Fear, as hinders us in the performance of our preſent Duty, that infeebles our Spirits, and weakens our Hands as to the uſe of lawful Means; or puts us upon the uſe of prohibited unlawful ones: Such a Fear, as takes off the Sweetneſs of our preſent Mercies, by the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and Fear of future Evil; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we reflect upon God's Government, and overlook his Promiſes of Support and Deliverance, and become unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to encounter the Evils, that we may be called to ſuffer.</p>
               <p>However, there is a <hi>Fear</hi> of proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, threatned, and approaching Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, that is both <hi>Allowable,</hi> and <hi>Commendable;</hi> a Fear of <hi>Caution,</hi> and <hi>Circumſpection,</hi> to excite us to prepare
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58544:56"/>for the Worſt; to put on our Armour, and make Proviſion for an evil Day. <hi>David</hi> wanted ſuch a Fear, when he ſaid within himſelf, that his Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was ſo ſtrong, that it could not be moved, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.6. It is ſuch a Fear, as is oppoſite to ſinful <hi>Preſumption,</hi> and <hi>Hardneſs of Heart.</hi> And therefore <hi>Bleſſed is the Man that feareth always,</hi> in this ſenſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.14. But he that is <hi>fearleſs,</hi> and hardneth his Heart, <hi>ſhall fall into Miſchief.</hi> We may and ought ſo far to fear, and apprehend the <hi>Poſſibility,</hi> and ſometimes the <hi>Likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> of bearing our Share in the like Sufferings, as our Brethren feel, ſo as may prevent our Security, and ſettling on our Lees, and a fooliſh Confidence, that <hi>the Cup of Trembling,</hi> which our Brethren have drunk ſo deep of, ſhall never be put into our Hands.</p>
               <p>It may farther be conſidered, that there is alſo a <hi>Penal Fear</hi> of future E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, which God inflicts as a <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> on ſuch with whom he is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: Deut. 28.64, 65. <hi>The Lord ſhall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58544:56"/>ſcatter thee among all People, from the one End of the Earth even to the other; and there thou ſhalt ſerve other Gods, which neither thou, nor thy Fathers have known, even Wood and Stone. And among theſe Nations ſhalt thou find no Eaſe, neither ſhall the Sole of thy Foot have Reſt: but the Lord ſhall give thee there a Trembling Heart, and Failing of Eyes, and Sorrow of Mind.</hi> The wicked Nations which inhabited the Promiſed Land, were driven out by ſuch Fears: for theſe ſeem to be the <hi>Hornets,</hi> that God ſent amongſt the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and <hi>Amorites,</hi> to drive them out of the Land, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.11, 12. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 23.27, 28. There are many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to this purpoſe in the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 15.21, 22, 24. &amp; 18.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.25. &amp; 20.2. &amp; 49.29. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.2. compared with 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 16. begin. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.9, 10.</p>
               <p>But this is quite another thing from what I am perſwading to: for we have probable Grounds to <hi>fear,</hi> what God may do as to this Nation and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58544:57"/>We have looked for <hi>Peace,</hi> that great comprehenſive Bleſſing, and <hi>as yet no Good comes:</hi> We are engaged in a <hi>War,</hi> that none can tell how, or when it ſhall be determined. We look for a <hi>Time of Healing,</hi> but our <hi>Phyſicians</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto have been <hi>of little Value:</hi> Our Wounds are not healed, and we know not when they will: Though we have much to be <hi>thankful</hi> for, we have cauſe enough to be <hi>humbled,</hi> and to fear: <hi>Rejoice</hi> we may on ſome Accounts, but yet <hi>rejoice with Trembling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though God be <hi>long</hi> before he comes to take Vengeance; though he may reprieve us for a little while longer; though he have done ſo wonderfully hitherto, beyond what we could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect; yet we cannot <hi>thence</hi> conclude, that he will <hi>always ſpare,</hi> that he will not ſtrike. The Confidence of ſome in our Forces, and Confederates, and Fleets, and Armies; ſo many tried Souldiers, and ſuch accompliſh'd Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and experienc'd Generals, and mighty Preparations by Sea and Land;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58544:57"/>and the Confidence of Others, upon bold Interpretations of <hi>Scripture Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies,</hi> with particular Application of them to our <hi>Iſland,</hi> are not of Weight enough, to hinder our Fears from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt. God may ſuddenly cover the Heavens with Darkneſs, and confute all our vain Preſumptions in a Month or two, when we expect it not.</p>
               <p>What God has done againſt <hi>Others,</hi> he may as <hi>righteouſly</hi> do againſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> if we deſpiſe his Judgments, and go on in the like Sins. <hi>Behold, ye Deſpiſers, wonder, and periſh,</hi> Acts 13.41. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> what I have done in <hi>other Places,</hi> and can do againſt you: <hi>For I work a Work in your Days, a Work which you ſhall in no wiſe believe, though a Man declare it unto you.</hi> Men little thought that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as it was, as little as we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>London,</hi> to be a Scene of Calamity. But we may live to ſee ſuch Effects of it, as may make our Eyes, and Hearts fail, before God has compleated his Work, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.18, 19.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58544:58"/>
               <p>If the Prophet cried, <hi>My Bowels, my Bowels, I am pained at the Heart, my Heart maketh a Noiſe within me; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold my Peace, becauſe thou haſt heard, O my Soul, the Sound of the Trumpet, the Alarum of War,</hi> Jer. 4.19. Much more may we ſay ſo of the Fear of an <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> which is unſpeakably more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible; when every Man ſinks with his own Houſe, as his Sepulchral Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument; when the Roofs fall upon our Heads, and the Floors cleave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Feet; and, whether by Day or Night, Tables, and Beds are ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly cruſhed into the Diſorders of a Grave, and the Inhabitants periſh at once with their Habitations.</p>
               <p>I know <hi>the Moſt</hi> do not love to hear of ſuch things, but Peace and Plenty, Victory and Succeſs, Liberty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity; and they are ready to ſay, you <hi>diſcourage,</hi> and <hi>diſhearten</hi> Men. But if a City or a Town be on Fire, or like to be ſo, muſt we not <hi>diſcourage</hi> Men by telling of it? It is true, God may ſave us by <hi>Prerogative;</hi> but if he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58544:58"/>by <hi>Common Law,</hi> according to the common Rules by which he has acted towards other Nations, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, or may expect to be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>God now ſeems to call us to <hi>Weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Mourning,</hi> and <hi>Sackcloth,</hi> and <hi>Aſhes;</hi> but how little of ſuch a Spirit is found amongſt us? <hi>Behold Joy and Gladneſs, ſlaying Oxen, and killing Sheep, eating Fleſh and drinking Wine, ſaying, Let us eat and drink, for to Morrow we ſhall die,</hi> Iſa. 22.12, 13. But what follows in <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>It was revealed in mine Ears by the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> ſays the Prophet, <hi>Surely this Iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till you die, ſays the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Matter be <hi>doubtful,</hi> whether God will preſerve and ſave us or no, the very <hi>poſſible Suppoſition</hi> that <hi>he may not,</hi> ſhould awaken a moſt ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. Is there but an <hi>it may be</hi> that the Lord will be gracious and ſpare us? Is it <hi>uncertain?</hi> Is there but <hi>a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure?</hi> Cannot we tell whether the Lord will turn from his fierce An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58544:59"/>againſt us, or no? How ſhould we be concerned to look about us! What if our Unthankfulneſs, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, and Formality, and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, our Unwillingneſs to be healed, after all the <hi>Overtures</hi> and <hi>Opportunities</hi> that have been before us; What if our Infidelity, and Sadduciſm, groſs Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities, and more provoking Goſpel-Sins, ſhould make God reſolve to <hi>cast us off,</hi> and call <hi>this Iſland,</hi> that has been <hi>Immanuel</hi>'s Land ſo long, <hi>Lo-ammi, Lo-ruamah,</hi> a People forſaken of the Lord? What if <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be <hi>a Seat of War,</hi> and <hi>a Field of Blood,</hi> as well as other Parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that never ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch <hi>Light,</hi> ſuch <hi>Warnings,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Obligations</hi> as we have? What if a ſudden <hi>Earthquake</hi> ſhould ſwallow up a great part of <hi>theſe Countries,</hi> as it hath of <hi>others?</hi> Why may not the very Dregs of the Cup be reſerved for us, who have been incorrigible under all the Methods of Divine Providence to reform us? What <hi>Certainty</hi> have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58544:59"/>we that it ſhall not be ſo? Where is the <hi>Ground</hi> of our <hi>Confidence?</hi> What <hi>Aſſurance</hi> have we that God will ſpare <hi>much longer?</hi> What <hi>ſtrong Reaſons</hi> can we produce for the Entail of <hi>Liberty, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Plenty?</hi> There needs no Spirit of <hi>Prophecy</hi> to declare our <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> conſidering our <hi>Guilt;</hi> but a more ſerious, and more general Spirit of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, Prayer</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> to be poured out, to prevent it.</p>
               <p>God has waited <hi>long,</hi> and tried us by <hi>various Methods</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> he has manifeſted how <hi>loth</hi> he is to deſtroy us, and therefore gives us many <hi>Admonitions</hi> and <hi>Items,</hi> former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of late. He calls loud and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, by <hi>manifold Warnings;</hi> he lifts up his Hand on high, as if he would ſtrike, that we might turn to the Lord, and prevent it: he ſhakes the City, and threatens the Nation, but has not yet delivered us over to utter Ruine. He tells us by the <hi>Examples of others,</hi> what he can do with us, and what we may expect if we will go on. He
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58544:60"/>
                  <hi>doubles</hi> and <hi>trebles</hi> his Meſſages by the Voice of his <hi>Prophets,</hi> and by the Voice of his <hi>Providence.</hi> He calls us by what he hath done <hi>abroad,</hi> and by what he hath done <hi>at home,</hi> to repent and turn to the Lord, leſt Iniquity prove our Ruine: But have we not reaſon to <hi>fear</hi> that all his <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> has but hardned us the more, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred us the more incorrigible, and ripe for Ruine? We continue our Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt him, as if we were ſure he would never be weary of Repenting.</p>
               <p>Being often reproved, and warned, and delivered, and yet <hi>Impenitent,</hi> ought we not to fear, leſt we be <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly deſtroyed, and that without Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy?</hi> How many Countries and Cities have been ſo? How many <hi>former In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> and <hi>later</hi> ones, may be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned? And if we are ſpared, it is <hi>mere Soveraignty,</hi> and <hi>Prerogative.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:58544:60"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of</hi> God's Unwillingneſs <hi>to deſtroy a People.</hi> Hoſea 11.8, 9. <hi>explained, paraphraſed, and applied to our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and City:</hi> How ſhall I give thee up, <hi>Ephraim?</hi> &amp;c. Abraham<hi>'s Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God for</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>Moral Cauſes why we may expect, and fear National and Publick Calamities.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is the Language of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to us, as to his ancient Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8, 9. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up,</hi> Ephraim? <hi>How ſhall I deliver thee,</hi> Iſrael? <hi>How ſhall I make thee as</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah? <hi>How ſhall I ſet thee as</hi> Zeboim? <hi>Mine Heart is turned within me, my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentings are kindled together. I will not execute the Fierceneſs of mine Anger, I will not return to deſtroy</hi> Ephraim; <hi>for I am God and not Man, the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>in the midſt of thee.</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58544:61"/>dreadful Judgments for their Ingratitude, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, 7. but when it comes to the <hi>Execution,</hi> he is <hi>loth</hi> to deſtroy; <hi>How ſhall I give thee up?</hi> To which it is anſwered, <q>
                     <hi>My Heart is turned within me,</hi> my Heart is turned againſt that Determination of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I ſeemed to reſolve on; or my Heart is <hi>returned</hi> to Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, that I cannot execute my threatned Vengeance.</q> 
                  <hi>How ſhall I deliver thee up, O</hi> Iſrael?To which it is anſwered, <q>
                     <hi>My Repentings are kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled together,</hi> that is, my Bowels yearn towards you ſtill: As little as you deſerve any Favour, or Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at my Hands, I am inclined to reprieve and ſpare you a while lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to give you ſpace and time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</q> 
                  <hi>How ſhall I make thee as</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah, one of the Cities of the Plain, that was utterly deſtroyed with Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven, with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah?</hi> Unto which it is anſwered, <q>
                     <hi>I will not execute the Fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mine Anger,</hi> as I did againſt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58544:61"/>that wicked City.</q> 
                  <hi>How ſhall I ſet thee as</hi> Zeboim? another of thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cities, <hi>which the Lord overthrew in his Anger and his Wrath,</hi> Gen. 19.24. To which it is anſwered, <q>
                     <hi>I will not return to deſtroy</hi> Ephraim, <hi>I will not make a full end of him, for I am God and not Man;</hi> not of an haſty, paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, revengeful Temper, as <hi>Men</hi> who are injured and affronted, and provoked by one another. I delight in Mercy, <hi>I have the Patience of a God as well as the Power;</hi> and <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are not conſumed,</hi> Mal. 3.6. <hi>I am the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, a God in Covenant with your Fathers, and have promiſed to be ſo with their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: I am the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael, in the midſt of thee:</hi> You are <hi>called by my Name,</hi> and I am <hi>yet amongst you</hi> by the Tokens of my Preſence; I am therefore loth to <hi>leave</hi> you, utterly to leave you to Deſtruction.</q>
               </p>
               <p>You have the like Expreſſion, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.4. <hi>O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee? O</hi> Judah, <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee? for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58544:62"/>your Goodneſs is as the Morning-Cloud, and the early Dew, that paſſeth away:</hi> that is, <q>I am loth to puniſh you with deſtructive Judgments, but what ſhall I do to prevent it? <hi>O Iſrael, O Judah,</hi> what would you have me to do? Would you have me neglect the Honour of my Government, and be an idle Spectator of all the Affronts that you have offered me? Muſt I repeal my <hi>Law,</hi> and throw aſide my <hi>Scepter,</hi> and tamely ſuffer the Rights of my Throne to be incroached on, and trampled under Foot? Muſt I reſolve to ſuffer you to go on in your Hypocriſy, and Idolatry, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Backſlidings, without teſtifying my Diſpleaſure? I have done much to warn you, to awaken you, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, to prevent your Ruine. I am inclined to <hi>Pity,</hi> I am unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deſtroy: But, <hi>O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee?</hi> You will not be purged, you will not be healed, you will not be gathered, <hi>you will die.</hi> And yet <hi>Mercy</hi> interpoſes again, before
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58544:62"/>the Stroak is given; <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, O</hi> Ephraim? Muſt I, after all, give Orders for thy Deſtruction? <hi>How ſhall I do it?</hi> Though thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveſt to be forſaken by <hi>my Mercy,</hi> which thou haſt abuſed, and ſeized by <hi>my Juſtice,</hi> which thou haſt provoked, yet how ſhall I find in my Heart to permit it? Though I can hardly tell how to bear with thee any longer, or with Honour to my Name and Government, to delay the Execution of that deſtructive Vengeance, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>on my part,</hi> and deſerved <hi>on thine;</hi> yet, <hi>O</hi> Ephraim, <hi>my dear Son, how ſhall I give thee up? O</hi> Iſrael, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of my ancient Friend <hi>Jacob, how ſhall I deliver thee over to final Ruine?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In anſwer to this, ſays God, <hi>My Heart is turned within me, my Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are kindled together:</hi> i. e. <q>I find ſuch Struglings of Compaſſion in my Heart towards thee, that I know not how to <hi>execute</hi> what I have <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: My Repentings are kindled,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58544:63"/>to repent of the Evil that I had threatned to inflict: Or my Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are <hi>kindled together;</hi> that is, all the <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> that might perſuade me to <hi>repent</hi> of my threatned Wrath, and keep back Deſtruction, they are <hi>all muſtered together,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Stroke.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus does the bleſſed God conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, to beſpeak us <hi>after the manner of Men;</hi> and like a tender-hearted and compaſſionate <hi>Parent,</hi> who is loth to diſinherit even a rebellious, and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient <hi>Son.</hi> His <hi>Kindneſs</hi> contends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Anger;</hi> his <hi>Mercy</hi> pleads a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Juſtice;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> denounceth <hi>Wrath,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> begs <hi>a Reprieve;</hi> the <hi>one</hi> threatens <hi>Deſolation,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſes to prevent it: <hi>My Heart is turned within me, and my Repentings are kindled;</hi> therefore I will not give thee up, I will not execute the Fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mine Anger, I will not return to deſtroy <hi>Ephraim,</hi> I will not make a full end of him; for <hi>I am God, and not Man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58544:63"/>
               <p>God has evidenced this to us, and others by undeniable Proofs; in that notwithſtanding <hi>the Provocations</hi> of a People, he is ready to <hi>Repent</hi> of his threatned Judgments upon <hi>their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and Return to him; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in that, before he gives up ſuch a People to <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> he gives them frequent <hi>Warnings</hi> by his <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> and by his <hi>leſſer Judgments;</hi> yea though his Warnings are ſlighted, and his Calls rejected, yet he doth <hi>not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy,</hi> but waits with much <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering,</hi> giving them Time and Space to Repent; and ſometimes appears to give unexpected Deliverance, even <hi>for his own Name ſake;</hi> and doth alſo ſpare and preſerve <hi>a Remnant,</hi> in the moſt general Deſtruction: And even at laſt doth not <hi>willingly</hi> abandon ſuch a People to utter Ruine, but with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy</hi> and <hi>Regret,</hi> ſo far as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the unchangeable <hi>Purity,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> of the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58544:64"/>
               <p>Like a compaſſionate Judg, who doth not <hi>willingly</hi> paſs the Sentence of Condemnation: If you will <hi>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> you muſt <hi>periſh:</hi> If you will not be <hi>reformed,</hi> you muſt be <hi>undone:</hi> If you will not <hi>take Warning,</hi> you muſt be <hi>forſaken. But, O</hi> Ephraim, <hi>how ſhall I give thee up? O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what ſhall I do unto thee? O that they knew the things that belong unto their Peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be hid from their Eyes!</hi> He ſigns the <hi>Warrant,</hi> as it were, for their <hi>Execution;</hi> and then he retracts the Order again: He gives <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for their <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> and then <hi>recalls</hi> it, and proves them yet a little longer. If that will not do, but <hi>Juſtice</hi> renews her Plea for <hi>Vengeance,</hi> then <hi>Mercy</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſes for <hi>a Delay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was on this Account God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>Abraham</hi> to plead with him ſo familiarly for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the Cities of the Plain; God lets him ſay all that he could, be grants him every thing he would have: If there be but <hi>fifty righteous Perſons,</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:58544:64"/>wilt thou not ſpare them? <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>Yes,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>I will:</hi> But, <hi>Lord,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure there be <hi>forty,</hi> is not that Number ſufficient? <hi>Yes,</hi> ſays God, that ſhall do, if there be but <hi>forty.</hi> But, <hi>Lord,</hi> it may be there are but <hi>twenty,</hi> wilt thou not ſpare them for their ſakes? <hi>Yes,</hi> for the ſake of <hi>twenty</hi> I will, ſays God. Once more let me beg, <hi>Lord,</hi> if there be but <hi>ten: Ay,</hi> if there be but <hi>ten</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons, I will ſpare them. God was willing to hear the utmoſt <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> could urge on their Behalf, as if he would have been glad to have met with <hi>an Argument,</hi> that might diſſwade him from ſo unpleaſing a Work. God grants him <hi>ſo often,</hi> and <hi>ſo long,</hi> till the holy Patriarch was <hi>aſhamed</hi> to ask any <hi>further,</hi> or plead any <hi>longer.</hi> So backward was God to deſtroy, and ſo unwilling to give up a People to utter Ruine; and that too, though ſuch a wicked People as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58544:65"/>
               <p>In the 4th of <hi>Amos</hi> you find God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached the Impenitence of that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under various Warnings, and leſſer Judgments; and mentions the Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of each Affliction, <hi>five</hi> ſeveral times, <hi>Yet have you not returned unto me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Thereupon, to awaken them to <hi>Repentance,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their Ruine, he pronounceth the Riddle of a Doom, <hi>Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O</hi> Iſrael; not mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what he would do, <hi>Thus will I do unto thee. Thus,</hi> as I have done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other Places, or worſe than I have ever done to Any; <hi>Thus will I do unto thee.</hi> It is a <hi>Relative</hi> without an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent;</hi> It is a <hi>locked Cabinet,</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> of Judgment, without a <hi>Key</hi> to open us a View of Particulars. <hi>No Judgment</hi> is expreſſed, that <hi>All</hi> may be feared; and <hi>All</hi> to be feared, that <hi>None</hi> may be felt: <hi>Therefore prepare to meet thy God, O</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>We have a great deal of Reaſon not to be <hi>Secure,</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>God's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwillingneſs to deſtroy.</hi> National
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58544:65"/>Judgments are deſerved, and threatned, and may be juſtly feared; and nothing but <hi>Repentance, Reformation, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and ſuch other Methods as are deſpiſed and neglected, can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, or preſerve us.</p>
               <p>This is certain, that no <hi>Situation</hi> of <hi>our</hi> Country, (or <hi>any</hi> Country, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Iſland,</hi> or <hi>Continent</hi>) can be our Safety, if God be againſt us. For what can preſerve us from an <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> or a thouſand other Methods of Judgment, which God can employ? All that Men expect Succour, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, and Protection from, is <hi>in vain,</hi> if God be not engaged on our behalf. All thoſe things that we can truſt to, are but ſo many <hi>Ciphers,</hi> if God be not on our ſide.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> truſts in his <hi>mighty Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> numerous enough <hi>to drink up a River,</hi> Iſa. 37.24. and yet the next News we hear of him, is, that God ſends <hi>an Angel,</hi> and cuts off near <hi>two hundred thouſand</hi> in one Night. No Courage or Valour, Numbers or
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58544:66"/>Strength, can avail in a time of <hi>War:</hi> No Skill or Policy, (of the Truth of this every Age affords Inſtances:). No external Relation to God by Church-Privileges, whereof the Jews are a ſad Example; No, nor any <hi>former Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances</hi> God hath wrought for us, are a Ground of <hi>Security</hi> for the future, without a thankful, and a holy Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of them. Not many Years after the Preſervation of the City of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> that City and People were deſtroyed. So it is threatned, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.20. <hi>If you forſake the Lord, he will turn againſt you, and do you Hurt, and conſume you, even after he hath done you Good.</hi> The like is threatned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.63. <hi>If you forſake the Lord, he will rejoice over you to Deſtroy you, as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiced over you to do you Good.</hi> Though a City be defended by Rocks and Mountains, as <hi>Edom</hi> was; yet the Strength and Situation of a Place, is no Preſervative againſt Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:58544:66"/>
               <p>In <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three Moments</hi> many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, yea <hi>many hundred thouſand</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be ſwallowed up by <hi>a ſudden Earthquake,</hi> tumbling alive into <hi>one common Grave, buried</hi> before they are <hi>dead,</hi> with miſerable Cries, and Groans, and Shrieks, till their Breath be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. And whatever the Wickedneſs of <hi>other Places</hi> may have been, who have ſmarted by ſuch Judgments, the Aggravations of <hi>our Sins</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>London</hi> are ſuch, as may make us fear the like, or worſe.</p>
               <p>If there were nothing but the <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>improvement</hi> of our <hi>paſt Mercies,</hi> we had reaſon to fear it: For what Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is there more than ordinarily va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable, but we have had? If <hi>Peace,</hi> if <hi>Plenty,</hi> if <hi>Victory,</hi> if the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> we have had it. But what <hi>unanſwerable Returns</hi> have we made, under all ſuch Obligations? All the Ways by which <hi>Eminent Mercies</hi> are abuſed, and God provoked, we have practiſed. <hi>Some</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> we have not valued at all; <hi>Others</hi> we have ſoon forgotten: As to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58544:67"/>
                  <hi>ſome,</hi> we have given the Praiſe and Glory, not to <hi>God,</hi> but to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> or our <hi>Friends,</hi> or the Inſtruments of Conveyance; Some (I fear the moſt) of theſe Bleſſings we have miſimployed to the Diſhonour of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our very Mercies may make us tremble.</p>
               <p>Yea further, that <hi>Drowſineſs</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,</hi> and <hi>Spirit of Slumber,</hi> that hath ſeemed to ſeize the Generality of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors amongſt us at this Day, is a juſt Ground for our preſent Fears; <hi>i. e.</hi> The general Unconcernedneſs about the State and Poſture of things amongſt us, with relation to God's Preſence or Departure. It cannot be well with ſuch a People, they cannot but be in exceeding Hazard, who when their Neighbour's Houſe is conſumed to Aſhes, or is yet on Fire, are faſt aſleep on their Beds. For this God threatens to <hi>ſearch</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with Candles,</hi> to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Men that are <hi>ſettled on their Lees,</hi> who ſaid in their Hearts, <hi>the Lord will not do Good or Evil,</hi> Zech. 1.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:58544:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Earthquakes uſually reckoned the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of other Calamities. We have had many Signs and VVarnings; and a long Seaſon of Divine For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance; though we are guilty of the like Sins, as have brought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Judgments on other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> The Land full of Sin. <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Societies only puniſh'd in this VVorld.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>BUT to come more particularly to conſider <hi>the late Earthquakes.</hi> There are many things that ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect us with an holy Awe and Fear of God, and his Judgments, upon thoſe Inſtances of his Severity in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> and by the leſſer one we felt <hi>September</hi> the 8th, 1692.</p>
               <p>It is not to be overlook'd, that moſt of the ancient <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> do obſerve, that this kind of Calamity has been
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58544:68"/>the Preſage of further Judgment
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cicero <hi>ſpeaking of an Earthquake,</hi> Orat. 30. de Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſpicum Reſponſis, <hi>ſpeaks to the like purpoſe:</hi> Etenim haec Deorum Immortalium vox, haec paenè Oratio judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canda eſt, cum ipſe Mundus, cum Aer, atque Terra, motu quodam novo contremiſcunt, &amp; inuſitato aliquid ſono, incredibilique praedicant; in quo conſtituendae nobis quidem ſunt Precationes &amp; Obſecratio, quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum monemur. Sed faciles ſunt Preces apud eos, qui ultrò nobis viam ſalutis oſtendunt: Noſtrae nobis ſunt inter nos Irae, diſſidiaeque placandae. <hi>And in another Place, diſcourſing how in the ſecond Punick War,</hi> C, Flami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius <hi>neglected the Signs of Futurities, to the Ruine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, his Army deſtroyed, and himſelf ſtain: He adds,</hi> Magnum illud etiam, quod addidit Caelius, eo tempore ipſo, cum hoc Calamitoſum fuerit Praelium, tantos Terrae Motus in Liguribus, Galliâ, compluribuſque In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulis, totâque in Italiâ, factos eſſe, ut multa Oppida corruerint, &amp;c. De Divinatione lib. 1. §. 35. <hi>And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward,</hi> §. 43, 50. <hi>ſpeaking of other Earthquakes, he adds,</hi> Quibus Portentis, magno Populo R. Bella, pornicioſaeque ſeditiones denunciabantur. Inque his omnibus reſponſa Haruſpicum cum Sibyllae verſibus congruebant.—<hi>And in another Place he reckons Earthquakes among thoſe things;</hi> Quae nuper Bello Octaviano magnarum fuerunt Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum Praenuntiae. <hi>Cicero</hi> de nat. Deor. l. 2. §. 13, 14.</note>. And even ſuch as have no great Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Religion, <hi>Machiavel</hi> himſelf not excepted, have acknowledged this to be true as to Matter of Fact. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">Socrates <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> l. 4. c. 11.</note> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58544:68"/>ſpeaking of the <hi>Earthquakes</hi> that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Bithynia,</hi> and the neighbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ring Countries, in the Days of <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Valons,</hi> takes notice of them as Signs of the Shakings and Convullions, the Tumults and Diſerders, which ſhould afterwards follow in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches. The whole <hi>known</hi> World, both Land and Sea, was then ſhaken, and its like the then <hi>unknown</hi> too; which might ſeem to be a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to the future Confiagration, or Deſtruction of the whole. <hi>Thucidides</hi> mentions an Earthquake in <hi>Delos,</hi> which in the
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Thucidides de Bell. Pelop. l. 2.</note> Memory of the <hi>Grecians</hi> never ſhook before; that it was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted for, and ſeemed to be a <hi>Sign</hi> of what was to come afterwards to paſs, in a moſt bloody War.</p>
               <p>We know that <hi>Earthquakes</hi> were foretold before the Deſtruction of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and the final Deſtruction of the World, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. That there ſhall be great Earthquakes <hi>in divers
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58544:69"/>Places.</hi> How far this may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in a <hi>Metaphorical Senſe,</hi> is worth conſidering: becauſe though ſome of thoſe Signs may be taken in a literal Senſe, others cannot; as how the Stars ſhould fall down from Heaven. And the declared <hi>Suddenneſs</hi> of Chriſt's Coming to judg the World, pleads for the Application of theſe illuſtrious Signs to the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And ſo it was literally as to Matter of Fact, before the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> as
<note n="*" place="bottom">De Bello Jud. l. 7. c. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> relates. So before the End of the World, or the Day of Judgment, the laſt of the laſt Plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18. we read of <hi>a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, ſuch as was not ſince Men were on the Earth, ſo mighty an Earthquake, and ſo great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know many make light of theſe things, becauſe they are capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſolved by natural Cauſes. But the Hand of God is not to be overlooked in ſuch things, under whoſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58544:69"/>and Influence all natural Agents act, and are over-ruled as to the Time and Degree of their Acting, eſpecially ſuch rare and unuſual Inſtances as <hi>Earthquakes.</hi> All ſecond Cauſes in their ſeveral Motions need the Continuation of the Divine Power and Influence, in order to their Operations, as well as their Subſiſtence. God uſes all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be the Inſtruments of his Will, and to ſerve his Purpoſes. Natural A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and moral, are all under his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <hi>Fire and Hail, Snow and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, and ſtormy Wind fulfil his Word, Pſal.</hi> 148.8. Blaſting and Mildew, Drought and Barrenneſs, an Infectious Air, Peſtilential Diſeaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever brought about by natural Cauſes, are under Divine Government, and act by virtue of his Influence. He gives Order to <hi>the Deſtroying Angel</hi> in a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence,</hi> 2 Sam. 24.16. He ſaith to the <hi>Sword, Go through the Land,</hi> Ezek. 14.17.</p>
               <p>Now though I will not ſay, that <hi>always</hi> theſe things are Preſages of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58544:70"/>Calamity and Judgment to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular People; yet, becauſe they have <hi>uſually</hi> been followed by ſome ſuch, and we have many other <hi>moral Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications</hi> of Divine Diſpleaſure, it ſhould call us to a humble Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Grounds of our Fear, as to National Calamities. And there are ſeveral Things (ſome whereof are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of by
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Fleming<hi>'s Diſcourſe of Earthquakes,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>ſome of whoſe Remarks I here repeat.</hi>
                  </note> Others) that may here very fitly be mentioned, as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we have a multitude of ſuch Signs, as have been generally eſteemed the Fore-runners of publick Calamity. It is not the late <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake alone,</hi> but in conjunction with many other things, that is the Ground of our Fear. And the more Signs we have, and the more they are deſpiſed, the louder is their Voice, to thoſe that will conſider them. We had Signs in the Heavens in 1681. We have had <hi>Earthquakes</hi> of late, <hi>in divers Places:</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:58544:70"/>And God has lately taken Peace from the Earth, as to this part of the World, by engaging ſo great a part of <hi>Europe</hi> in bloody Wars: All which has the Appearance of ſome great Things to be uſhered in. I durſt not be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as many are, what they ſhall be, or the particular Year, or Seaſon of their Accompliſhment: I chuſe rather to acknowledg my Ignorance in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Scripture; tho divers Learned Perſons ſay more on that Subject, than I am able to anſwer, or refute.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the longer the Time is of God's Patience and Forbearance, with the diſtinguiſhing Mercies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Warnings that we have had, the more terrible Judgments are like to follow, if we are Unthankful and Impenitent after all. Deliverances, if not improved, are but Reprievals from further Judgment; we may not be ſo much preſerved and ſaved, as <hi>reſerved</hi> to greater Miſery. That Paſſage ſeems to record our Doom, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.43. <hi>Many times did he deliver them; but they
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58544:71"/>provoked him by their Counſel, and were brought low for their Iniquity.</hi> As God will not <hi>always contend,</hi> ſo neither will he <hi>always forbear.</hi> There is no greater Sign of a final Overthrow, than a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>improvement of paſt Mercies, and Judgments: And if God be provoked by National Sins, we cannot think his Anger will be turned away, while the Cauſe of it remains; that is as much as to ſay, <hi>Except we repent, we must likewiſe periſh.</hi> Though a leſs Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may prevent National Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than will preſerve from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ruine.</p>
               <p>Is it nothing unto us, that God has dealt ſo ſeverely with other People? when our Privileges and Obligations are equal to, or greater than theirs? There is hardly any one ill Symptom, that has ever been upon any People, that God has dealt in Severity with, but ſomething of it is obſervable, and notorious amongſt us. I grant, we muſt not ſet Bounds to the <hi>Patience</hi> of God, any more than to his <hi>Power:</hi> We
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58544:71"/>know not how much longer he may bear with us, before he vindicate his own Rights, or in what Way, or to what Degree he will do ſo, at leaſt <hi>in our Time.</hi> But we have no Ground of <hi>Confidence,</hi> and <hi>Security:</hi> For while we ſay, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> ſudden Deſtruction, yea <hi>National Deſtruction may overtake us,</hi> as Travail upon a Woman with Child. And the rather, becauſe all his Warnings hitherto ſeem to be ſlighted: Our National Preſervation and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſo often repeated, has not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered us; but our Provocations are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the more aggravated, by all that God has done to Reform, Eſtabliſh, and Save us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If we are guilty of <hi>the like Sins</hi> with other People, who have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſh'd by extraordinary Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, why may not our continued Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitence expoſe us to an equal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And may not <hi>England</hi> ſay, <hi>Are there not with me, even with me, the ſame Sins against the Lord?</hi> The <hi>ſame</hi> Sins, for which <hi>Others</hi> have ſmarted,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58544:72"/>and that with this Aggravation, that we ſin againſt <hi>more VVarnings?</hi> God is unchangeably <hi>Just,</hi> as well as <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious.</hi> It is <hi>Soveraignty</hi> alone can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us; by <hi>that</hi> he may do ſo; But who can tell whether he will? God hates the ſame Sins in our Days, which he hated, and puniſhed formerly: He is as much, or more, diſpleaſed with our Impurities, as with thoſe of other People, that are deſtroyed. He loves the ſame Holineſs now, which he ever loved; he is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever: And why ſhould we think, God ſhould go out of his way to ſpare us? As they may encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage themſelves by truſting in God, who have <hi>Examples</hi> of God's Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in the like Caſe of holy Truſt in him; ſo they may fear, under the like Provocations, for which Others have been puniſhed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When a Land is <hi>full of Sin,</hi> and the whole Body of a Nation, a very <hi>Few</hi> excepted, have corrupted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and provoked God; conſider,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58544:72"/>
                  <hi>the Puniſhment of ſuch Sins can be only in this World, while the Community laſts.</hi> This is not to be reſerved to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Great Day, when every particular Perſon ſhall anſwer for his own Guilt. And is not our Nation full of Sin? Do not our Provocations reach to Heaven? Is there not a <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as to <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Multitude,</hi> as to <hi>Meaſure</hi> and <hi>Degree,</hi> that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren fill up the Meaſure of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Iniquity; and as to <hi>Strength,</hi> and <hi>Growth,</hi> that it riſes higher; and as to <hi>Cunning</hi> and <hi>Dexterity</hi> in the Arts of Wickedneſs, in <hi>Court, City, Country, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> among all Ranks and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; and as to <hi>Boldneſs</hi> and <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> by open bare-fac'd Impiety? Many of thoſe Crimes, which were formerly Matter of Reproach, and Shame, are now <hi>Alamode,</hi> and in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and the Character of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:58544:73"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moſt ſlight ſuch Warnings. What was done in</hi> Jamaica, <hi>had ſpecial Relation to us in this Iſland. We in</hi> England <hi>have had divers Earthquakes formerly.</hi> Their <hi>Wickedneſs was great, ſo is</hi> ours. <hi>Several Earthquakes have extended as far as ours,</hi> Sept. 8th, <hi>tho felt beyond the Seas near the ſame Time. Other Inſtances of</hi> Eathquakes <hi>in</hi> Europe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE ought to conſider the Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Warnings that we have had, by the late Earthquake in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> June the 7th, 1692. and here at home, <hi>September</hi> the 8th, and what we have lately heard concerning <hi>Sicily.</hi> This is the more to be attended to, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the Moſt</hi> are ready to aſcribe all to <hi>Natural Cauſes.</hi> There is <hi>an Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical,</hi> and <hi>Profane Spirit</hi> viſible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, to diſregard any thing of the Hand of God in theſe Matters; as
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58544:73"/>if he did not direct ſuch a Judgment, to <hi>one Place</hi> rather than <hi>Another,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, and over-rule the <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Seaſon,</hi> and <hi>Degree</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Conſider, what was done in <hi>Jamai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> had a ſpecial Reference to <hi>this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the Intereſt, and the Inhabitants of that Place, being purely <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo a Part of our Nation, though at a diſtance: which calls upon us the more to lay it to Heart. Neither is it to be deſpiſed, that they in <hi>Jamaica</hi> had a Forewarning by a Trembling of the Earth, a little before that Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on overtook them; and ſoon after that, we had the Warning of the <hi>Earthquake here:</hi> it followed ſo cloſe upon the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of that in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> as to be very proper to awaken us to a deeper Senſe of it, and to make the Warning the more Remarkable. So that God may ſay of us, as he did to <hi>Moſes,</hi> If they will not hearken to <hi>the Voice of the firſt Sign,</hi> they may yet hearken to <hi>the Voice of the ſecond:</hi> and the diſmal Account ſince that, of the Earthquake in <hi>Sicily,</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:58544:74"/>makes <hi>a Third;</hi> if that of <hi>Malta</hi> may not be reckon'd <hi>a Fourth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We do not read of any Inſtance of Earthquakes before in that <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> ſince it was under the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Power,</hi> nor before while under the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> But we have had ſeveral Inſtances of Earthquakes amongſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> formerly in <hi>England,</hi> and theſe Parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> tho more ſeldom than in the Eaſt; therefore it is not unreaſonable for us to Expect, and Fear the like.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, thoſe Countries which are very hot, or very cold, are leaſt ſubject to Earthquakes; and therefore it hath been matter of Wonder in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> or in
<note n="*" place="bottom">Herodot. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Scythia,</hi> to have the Earth tremble. <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are reckoned among thoſe Parts of <hi>Europe</hi> leaſt liable to violent Earthquakes; and yet our Hiſtorians mention ſeveral, as,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1081. <hi>April</hi> 6. in the time of
<note n="†" place="bottom">Matthew Paris. Speed<hi>'s Chron.</hi> p. 446.</note> King <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> (or
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58544:74"/>the <hi>Conqueror)</hi> was an Earthquake here with a great Noiſe, in the 15th Year of his Reign; and followed within a few Years with many Calamities.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt's Time,
<note n="*" place="bottom">Baker<hi>'s Chron.</hi> p. 43.</note> the Earth moved with ſo great a Violence, that many Buildings were ſhaken down; and <hi>Malmesbury</hi> ſaith, that the Houſe wherein he ſate, was lifted up with a double Remove, and at the <hi>third</hi> time ſettled again in the proper Place. And in divers Places it gave forth a hideous Noiſe, and caſt forth Flames at certain Rifts many days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which neither by Water, nor by other Means, could be ſuppreſs'd. In <hi>Lombardy</hi> the ſame Year, was an Earthquake that continued for 40 days, and remov'd a Town from the Place where it ſtood, a great way off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1133. <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> mentions a great Darkneſs in <hi>England,</hi> and an Earthquake at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1165. He mentions another
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58544:75"/>Earthquake, in the 11th Year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, <hi>January</hi> the 26th, in <hi>Ely, Norfolk,</hi> and <hi>Suffolk;</hi> which threw down many Perſons, who were ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or walking; and made the Clocks to ſtrike, and Bells to ring in the Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. And in the 24th Year of his Reign, in the Territory of <hi>Derlington,</hi> in the Biſhoprick of
<note n="*" place="bottom">Baker<hi>'s Chron.</hi> p. 58.</note> 
                  <hi>Durham,</hi> the Earth lifted up her ſelf in manner of an high Tower, and ſo remained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable from Morning till Evening, and then fell with ſo horrible a Noiſe, as frighted the Inhabitants thereabouts; and the Earth ſwallowing it up, made there a deep Pit, which is ſeen at this day: The Pits in that Place are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Hellkettles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1180. A great Earthquake threw down many Buildings, amongſt which the Cathedral Church of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln</hi> was rent in pieces, <hi>April</hi> 25th.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1247. There was an
<note n="†" place="bottom">Matthew Paris.</note> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58544:75"/>in <hi>April</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> eſpecially felt on the Banks of the River <hi>Thames;</hi> which ſhook, and threw down many Buildings; and was the more terrible, becauſe theſe Weſtern Parts are leſs accuſtom'd to Earthquakes. And the ſame Year there was little Ebbing or Flowing of the Sea obſervable as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, for about three Months.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1248. The ſame Hiſtorian men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions another Earthquake, which did a great deal of Miſchief, eſpecially in the Dioceſs of <hi>Bath;</hi> the Biſhop where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of gave him an Account of it. And this was the <hi>third</hi> which had happen'd within <hi>three</hi> Years, on this ſide the <hi>Alpes; one</hi> in ſome Parts of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and <hi>two</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> which was the more Terrible, becauſe the like not known before in theſe Parts. He takes notice of another Earthquake in <hi>England</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, in the Year 1250.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>thirteenth</hi> Year of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> a prodigious
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cambden<hi>'s Eliz.</hi> p. 158, 159. Baker<hi>'s Chron.</hi> p. 399.</note> Earthquake hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58544:76"/>in the Eaſt Parts of <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> near a little Town called <hi>Kinaſton.</hi> On the 17th of <hi>February,</hi> at ſix a clock in the Evening, the Earth began to open, and an Hill with a Rock under it (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at firſt a great bellowing Noiſe, which was heard a great way off) lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelf up a great Height, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to travel; bearing along with it the Trees that grew upon it, the Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds, and Flocks of Sheep abiding there at the ſame time: In the Place, from whence it was firſt moved, it left a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Diſtance forty Foot broad, and fourſcore Ells long; the whole Field was about twenty Acres. Paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, it overthrew a Chappel ſtanding in the way, removed an Yew Tree planted in a Church-yard, from the Weſt unto the Eaſt: with the like Force it thruſt before it High-ways, Sheepfolds, Hedges, and Trees; made tilled Ground Paſture, and again turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Paſture into Tillage. Having walk'd in this ſort from <hi>Saturday</hi> in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till <hi>Monday</hi> Noon, it then ſtood ſtill.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:58544:76"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1588. The like Prodigy hapned in
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cambden<hi>'s Eliz.</hi> p. 244. Baker<hi>'s Chron.</hi> p. 400.</note> 
                  <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> as in the Year 1571, in <hi>Herefordſhire.</hi> A Field of three A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, with the Trees and Fences, in <hi>Blackmore,</hi> moved from its Place, and paſſed over another Field, travelling in the High-way that goeth to <hi>Herne,</hi> and there ſtayed.</p>
               <p>In the 23d of Q. <hi>Elizabeth, An.</hi> 1580. in the beginning of <hi>April,</hi> about ſix in the Afternoon, happened an
<note n="†" place="bottom">Cambden <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 286.</note> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake not far from <hi>York,</hi> which in ſome places ſtruck the very Stones out of the Buildings, and made the Bells in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to jingle. The Night following the Earth trembled once or twice in <hi>Kent,</hi> and again the <hi>firſt</hi> of <hi>May.</hi> This Earthquake was felt at <hi>London,</hi> ſo as to give Occaſion to an Order of Prayer; and a Godly Admonition concerning it, appointed
<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Recited by Mr.</hi> D. Earthquakes Explain'd, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>p.</hi> 134.</note> to be read for the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God's Wrath from the Nation,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58544:77"/>threatned by the Earthquake, by Order of the Queen and her Privy-Council, to be uſed in all Churches, and Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds throughout the Realm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1657. On the 8th day of <hi>July</hi> there was an
<note n="*" place="bottom">Heath<hi>'s Chronicle,</hi> p. 395.</note> Earthquake at <hi>Bickley</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> have alſo felt Earthquakes. In <hi>April</hi> 1640, all the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and a great part of <hi>Germany,</hi> were ſhaken by a ſudden Earthquake. Which ſort of Prodigy was very unuſual, ſaith
<note n="†" place="bottom">Cluverius, p. 743.</note> 
                  <hi>Cluverius,</hi> in thoſe Parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1117. In the 17th Year of the Emperor
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Cluver. ad An. 1117. p. 434.</note> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the 5th, the World was ſhook by terrible Earthquakes; Cities, Caſtles, Villages, and a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of People were ſwallowed up in the Caverns of the Earth. Many at <hi>Liege,</hi> or <hi>Luyk,</hi> were deſtroyed by Thunder, while they were paying their Veneration to the Saints for Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58544:77"/>Mountains were cleft, Rivers dried up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So lately as the Year 1660, <hi>France</hi> had experience of
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Letters writ by a</hi> Spy <hi>at</hi> Paris, Vol. 6. p. 58, 67.</note> an Earthquake, which the <hi>Turkiſh Spy</hi> mentions, who was then at <hi>Paris.</hi> 
                  <q>We have felt the Menaces, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> of a terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake this Evening. When I liv'd in <hi>Aſia,</hi> an <hi>Earthquake</hi> was almoſt as common as the yearly Revolution of <hi>Summer</hi> and <hi>Winter:</hi> and we took as little notice of it, as we did of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Hail, or Rain. But now I have been ſo long diſus'd to theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions of the Globe—that I am become like the reſt of the World, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, and aſtoniſhed,—my Mind at firſt ſtagger'd as much as my Body. When I was walking croſs my Chamber, and felt the Floor rock under me, with that ſingular kind of Motion, which no humane Art or Force can imitate, I ſoon concluded 'twas an Earthquake, but knew not
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58544:78"/>how to bear that Thought with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference. Death is familiar to me in any other Figure, but that of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſurprizingly buried alive; it appeared to me very horrible to ſink on a ſudden into an unknown Grave, I knew not whither. Perhaps I might fall into ſome dark Lake of Water; or it may be, I might be drench'd in a River of Fire, or be daſh'd on a Rock: for who can tell the Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Caverns below, or what ſort of Apartments he ſhall find under the Surface of the Earth? We walk on the Battlements of a Marvellous Structure, a <hi>Globe</hi> full of Tremendous Secrets.—We had News here of an Earthquake, which had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown part of the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, ſome days before this happened at <hi>Paris;</hi> but few regarded it. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities at a Diſtance frighten. No Body: Yet thoſe which we feel, put us all in Fears.</q>— In another Letter he ſaith, <q>The Earthquake late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe Parts, hath put all <hi>France</hi>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:58544:78"/>into a great Conſternation, aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every Body, and encreaſed the Thoughtfulneſs of the Wiſe. The firſt Effects of it were felt by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the <hi>Pyrenees,</hi> which are certain Mountains dividing <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> There it did great Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, overwhelming ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me Medicinal Baths, many Houſes, and deſtroying Hundreds of People. Only one <hi>Moſque</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> which ſunk into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns below, was thrown up again, and ſtands very firm, but in another Place. This is look'd upon as a great Miracle, eſpecially by the <hi>French,</hi> who have diſputed with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> for this Church, as ſtanding on the Frontier Line; but now is remov'd near half a League within the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd Limits of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </q> The <hi>Matter of Fact</hi> is all I urge this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for; his <hi>Remarks</hi> here (and in many other places) not being ſuch, as a Serious Chriſtian will approve.</p>
               <p>If <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Britain,</hi> and <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> have had few Earthquakes, in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58544:79"/>compariſon of other Places of the Eaſt, yet <hi>Italy</hi> hath <hi>often</hi> ſmarted under ſuch Calamities. Among many Inſtances, I'le recite ſome, beſides thoſe already mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 801. While <hi>Charles the Great</hi> was in <hi>Italy,</hi> there was an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake
<note n="*" place="bottom">Le Sieur Hiſt. del. Egliſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vol. 7. p. 2, 3. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> with great Noiſes, on the laſt of <hi>April,</hi> which ſhook <hi>all France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>Italy;</hi> it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw ſeveral Towers, and even Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; and the Church of <hi>St. Paul</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> was deſtroyed by it. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Pope Leo the Third</hi> appointed three Days before the Aſcenſion, ſolemn Faſts, and Proceſſions. Theſe Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies were followed with furious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, and contagious Diſeaſes, which affected the Cattel throughout <hi>Italy,</hi> ſo that the moſt of their Beaſts died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1180. An Earthquake ruined a great part of the City of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1222. There were ſuch
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Cent. Magdeburg. Vol. 3. Cent. 13. cap. 13.</note> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58544:79"/>in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Lombardy,</hi> that the Cities and Towns were forſaken, and the People kept abroad in the Fields in Tents; many Houſes and Churches were thrown down, and many were thereby cruſh'd to Death. The Earth trembled twice a day in <hi>Lombardy,</hi> for fourteen days together. Beſides two Cities in <hi>Cyprus</hi> deſtroyed by Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes this Year. The City of
<note n="*" place="bottom">B. Corio Hiſt. Milaneſe, p. 164.</note> 
                  <hi>Breſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> was then almoſt ruin'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1276. In <hi>July,</hi> the ſame Month when <hi>Adrian the</hi> 4th was made Pope, and within a few days after, was
<note n="†" place="bottom">Corio Ib. p. 268. <hi>Il che ſi preſe per indicio de' gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimi fatti.</hi>
                  </note> a dreadful Earthquake at <hi>Milan,</hi> and all the Country round about. Which Pope died the next <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and in <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> Another ſucceeded by the Name of <hi>John</hi> the 21ſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1348. This Year was ſo famous for forty eight Earthquakes, and for Contagious Diſeaſes in <hi>Italy,</hi> and other
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:58544:80"/>parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cluver. ad An. 1348. p. 516.</note> 
                  <hi>Albertus Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenſis</hi> ſaith, from the time of the Flood, was not ſuch a Seaſon of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, <hi>(Haud inde a Diluvio regnaſſe tantam vim morborum &amp; mortium pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1397. On St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Day all <hi>Lombardy</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">B. Corio Hiſt. Milaneſe, p. 542.</note> was ſhaken by an unuſual Earthquake, which deſtroyed very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Buildings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1456. There aroſe upon the Sea of <hi>Ancona,</hi> together with a thick gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Cloud that extended above two Miles, a Tempeſt of Wind, Water, Fire, Lightning, and Thunder; which piercing to the moſt deep Abyſſes of the Sea, forc'd up the Waves with a moſt dreadful Fury, and carried all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it upon the Land: which cauſed ſo dreadful an Earthquake ſome time after, that the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> was ruined, and all
<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Monthly Mercury,</hi> March 1693. <hi>p.</hi> 90.</note> 
                  <hi>Italy</hi> carried the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58544:80"/>Marks of it. A <hi>Million</hi> of Houſes and Caſtles were buried in their own Ruine, above <hi>thirty thouſand</hi> People were cruſh'd to pieces, and a huge Mountain overturn'd into the Lake <hi>de la Garde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1473. There was ſuch an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake at
<note n="*" place="bottom">Corio Hiſt. Milaneſe, p. 820.</note> 
                  <hi>Milan,</hi> and the Country round about, as the like was not known in the Memory of any then Living there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1590. The Election of Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban the Seventh</hi> (who in 10 Months made room for <hi>Gregory the</hi> 14th) was ſignalized by an
<note n="†" place="bottom">Cluverius ad An. 1590. p. 625.</note> Earthquake, by which <hi>Auſtria, Moravia,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi> trembled; accompanied with a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Drought that Summer. Upon which enſued a Famine, and Peſtilence, with ſuch Havock in <hi>Italy,</hi> that in one Year there died at <hi>Rome, ſixty thouſand</hi> Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1629. The Divine Anger broke
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58544:81"/>out upon <hi>Italy</hi> by ſuch horrible
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cluverius, p. 680.</note> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, that in <hi>Apulia ſeventeen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> Perſons were deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1638. <hi>Athanaſius Kircher</hi> the Jeſuit, in his Preface to his <hi>Mundus Subterrancus,</hi> gives a ſad Narrative of a diſmal
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Cited by Mr.</hi> Bay, <hi>p.</hi> 185.</note> Earthquake in <hi>Calabria,</hi> wherein himſelf was, and out of which he hardly eſcap'd with his Life: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſeen in the whole Country he paſſed by, for two hundred Miles in length, but the Carcaſſes of Cities, and the horrible Ruines of Villages; the Inhabitants wandring about in the open Fields, being half dead with Fear, and Expectation of what might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. But moſt remarkable was the Subverſion of the noted Town of <hi>St. Eufemia,</hi> which was quite loſt out of their ſight, and abſorp'd; and inſtead thereof nothing left but a ſtinking Lake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> abound with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneous
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58544:81"/>Fires, eſpecially in the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Parts; which have broke out ſo often, as to be called by the Ancient Inhabitants, <hi>The Burnt Countrey.</hi> In ſome Places are ſeen perpetual Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as in <hi>Aetna,</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius;</hi> in others, Conflagrations by times: All <hi>Campania</hi> carries Footſteps of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagrations. Mount <hi>Aetna</hi> hath often rag'd mightily, and hath been wont to do ſo
<note n="*" place="bottom">Kircher's Mundus Subterraneus.</note> almoſt as many Years before Chriſt as ſince. <hi>An.</hi> 1669. it broke out with Violence, and overthrew all the adjacent Places with very great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, ſorely threatning <hi>Catanea</hi> it ſelf, which is ſince wholly deſtroyed by the late Earthquake. Theſe Irrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mount <hi>Aetna,</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> are always accompanied with <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,</hi> more or leſs; which ſometimes do incredible Miſchief in thoſe Parts. For Inſtance, <hi>An.</hi> 1688. we have an Account from
<note n="†" place="bottom">London <hi>Gazette,</hi> 1688. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2358.</note> 
                  <hi>Naples, June</hi> the 8th,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:58544:82"/>of an Earthquake there, which was accompanied with the Rage, and Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Mount <hi>Veſuvius.</hi> 
                  <q>On Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt, the 5th inſtant, about the 22d Hour, happened here a dreadful Earthquake, (though it laſted not long) which frightning the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants out of their Houſes with the Terrors of an inevitable Deſtruction, they betook themſelves to the Piaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za's, and the open publick Places of the City. The old College of the Jeſuits was ruined by it, alſo the great Chappel of their new College, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with three other Chappels ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining; three of the Fathers were killed there, beſides many others whoſe Numbers are not yet known. The Front of another great Church of the Jeſuits opened in many Cracks, and the great Tower or Steeple ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ready to fall. In the <hi>Theatins</hi> Convent of the Holy Apoſtles, a whole Dormitory fell down, beſides other conſiderable Damage they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: And the magnificent Arch
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58544:82"/>erected before the Church of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> belonging to the ſaid Fathers, fell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thoſe great and ancient Columns, that formerly made part of the Temple of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> there remaining only four of them ſtanding, and thoſe in a tottering Condition. Out of thoſe Ruines there have been already dug 19 Perſons that were dead; and there was reaſon to fear that the Miſchief might have been much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it being ſo near to a publick Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, where there were great Throngs of People. The Walls of the great Church of St. <hi>Dominick</hi> opened in many places, and great part of the Refectory fell down, as alſo a part of the adjoining Palace, where many were killed. Several other Churches of the <hi>Auguſtins,</hi> &amp;c. were ruined: and in ſhort, there is ſcarce a Palace or Houſe that has not received ſome conſiderable Damage. This occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned very devout Proceſſions of Perſons of all Ranks. The next day was another great Shock, which threw
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58544:83"/>down many of the Houſes that were before the moſt weakned: And ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday there was another perceived, but without much Damage; but this day we have felt nothing of it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Proceſſions continue in great numbers, and the Perſons of Quality are all retired from hence. In the Neighbourhood of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dico,</hi> a City at ſixteen Miles diſtance from hence, a Mountain opened; and a Courier from <hi>Benevento,</hi> a City belonging to the Pope, brings an account, that it was all ruined, and that of 6000 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants there were but few left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. The Archbiſhop's Palace there was thrown down; and the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop himſelf drawn out of the Ruines, being hurt in his Head and Arm: and there are Accounts of the like Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in ſeveral other Places.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Which was confirm'd from <hi>Rome, June</hi> 12. 1688. <q>We have had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing conſiderable to entertain us here this Week, but the ſad Relations of the Terrible Earthquakes at <hi>Naples,</hi>
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:58544:83"/>and ſeveral Places about it. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Naples</hi> on Saturday laſt about twenty one Hours and a half, (which at the ſame inſtant was perceiv'd even by a great many here:) On Sunday too it returned. Several Churches, Palaces, and Houſes are ruined; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, the famous Church of the Jeſuits, reckon'd the fineſt in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> is all tumbled down, except the Walls and the High Altar. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Number of thoſe killed and buried in the Ruines, cannot yet be known. The laſt Letters ſay, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Inhabitants lie abroad under Tents, in Coaches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Prayers, Proceſſions, publick Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are performed; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one runs about, crying, <hi>Miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</hi> Three Ships were ſunk in the Harbour, and the Water in the Wells roſe many Handſuls. <hi>Benevento</hi> is almoſt totally ruined; and of 10000 Inhabitants they ſay there remain ſcarce 600 alive. Cardinal <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſini,</hi> their Archbiſhop, was taken out of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:58544:84"/>the Ruines alive, but hurt. Several other Places and Seats are quite rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and moſt of the Inhabitants ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up. This City, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try hereabout, juſt felt the Shock, but received no Harm.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And in a following Account a Month after, it is ſaid, the Damage done amounts to above <hi>fifty Millions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſince by theſe, and other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples (in <hi>the next Chapter</hi>) we find <hi>Europe</hi> hath been viſited by ſuch Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities formerly: If the like <hi>moral Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> be found among us, the Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice can puniſh us by the like kind of Severity: and we ought to apprehend, and conſider it.</p>
               <p>The Wickedneſs and Impiety of the Inhabitants of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> we are told by Eye-witneſſes, was grown to a very great Height, before this Judgment: And they muſt be great Strangers to <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> who will not own the ſame of us, both as to <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> and <hi>Practice.</hi> Few will deny
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:58544:84"/>it, as to the <hi>latter:</hi> And as to the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> it is dreadful to think how <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm,</hi> and <hi>Infidelity</hi> prevails, and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd <hi>Deiſm,</hi> with the Rejection of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and all <hi>Revealed Religion:</hi> how it has obtained, and ſpread in this Nation. As if we were weary of the <hi>Chriſtian Profeſſion,</hi> and would ſet up for <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> to the Subverſion of the whole Frame of the Goſpel of Chriſt; pulling the Crown from off his Head, and plucking him from his Throne. Or at beſt, amongſt a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous growing Party of Others, who own themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of <hi>our Lord</hi> is diſown'd, and they allow him to be but <hi>a meer Man,</hi> not <hi>the Eternal Son of God.</hi> When ſuch Provocations abound amongſt us, it ſhould affect us with <hi>Horrour,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they prevail againſt the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Means,</hi> and <hi>Mercies,</hi> and ſpread as a <hi>Gangrene</hi> over the whole Kingdom.</p>
               <p>There were ſome Circumſtances of the Earthquake amongſt us, <hi>Sept.</hi> 8th, that have been obſerved to be very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:58544:85"/>I do not reckon this for one, that at the ſame Hour the Earth trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled here at <hi>London,</hi> and at many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Places, both in this Kingdom, and in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and the adjacent Parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Sea between us and them: for Earthquakes have reach'd farther. Not to mention <hi>that Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> at the Death of our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Christ,</hi> which ſhook not only one part of the Earth, as in other Caſes, but the whole of it trembled, if
<note n="*" place="bottom">Leſcoloper <hi>in</hi> Cicero <hi>de Nat. Deorum,</hi> p. 229. Quo motu, non pars aliqua Terrae, ut ſemper aliàs, ſed tota Terra conquaſſata eſt, &amp; centro convulſa, ut nulla Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, ne noſtra quidem Gallia, (quam Plinius a Terrae motu immunem fecit) primo ipſo Motore e vivis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moto, cum ſuis omnibus Incolis, immotiſque adeo Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deae rupibus, in tam inſolenti Commutatione, non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veretur: Et vero <hi>cum Dominus dedit vocem ſuam, mota eſt Terra;</hi> ut canit divinus Vates, quantò putamus ampliùs commotam eſſe, <hi>cum Dominus dedit Animam ſuam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus</hi> may be credited. Or the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that, whereby
<note n="†" place="bottom">Cluverius <hi>(mibi)</hi> p. 214.</note> 
                  <hi>twelve</hi> Cities of <hi>Aſia</hi> fell at once. <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> in the Life of <hi>Peireskius,</hi> reports, that at the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:58544:85"/>Mountain <hi>Semo</hi> in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a burning at the ſame time with that of <hi>Veſuvius</hi> in <hi>Campania,</hi> An. 1633. So that not only <hi>Veſuvius</hi> communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates with <hi>Aetna</hi> by ſubterraneous Vaults, but alſo <hi>Aetna</hi> with the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Syria,</hi> the Tunnels running un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Depths of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea; and thoſe with the <hi>Arabian;</hi> and laſtly the <hi>Arabian</hi> with Mount <hi>Semo</hi> in <hi>Aethiopia.</hi> And we read of other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, particularly by the Earthquake in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Switzerland,</hi> May 12. 1682. which reach'd as far as <hi>Collen</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and was perceiv'd in <hi>Lion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois, Dauphiny,</hi> and <hi>Beaujolois,</hi> at <hi>Mets</hi> in <hi>Lorrain,</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> &amp;c. That the Cities of <hi>Orleans, Troyes, Sens, Chalons, Joinville, Reims, Soiſſons, Laon, Moſcon, Dole, Strasburgh,</hi> &amp;c. felt it, eſpecially <hi>Remiremont</hi> on the <hi>Moſelle.</hi> The whole World almoſt trembled at once by the Earthquake, <hi>An.</hi> 1116. And by the Earthquake, <hi>An.</hi> 1601. <hi>Aſia, Hungary, Italy, Germany,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> are ſaid to have trembled at one time; that Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:58544:86"/>extending from <hi>Aſia</hi> to that Sea that waſhes the French Shores, the whole Length of <hi>Europe,</hi> in a quarter of an Hour; beſides ſome <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, it ſhook <hi>Hungary, Germany, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>France:</hi> This is affirmed by good Writers, ſaith Mr.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Of the Effects of Languid Motion,</hi> p. 49, 50.</note> 
                  <hi>Boyle,</hi> and Mr.
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Phyſico-Theological Diſcourſes,</hi> p. 215. Fromond. Meteor. l. 4. cap. ult. Art. 4. <hi>Dr.</hi> Tho. Burnet<hi>'s The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory of the Earth,</hi> p. 119, 120.</note> 
                  <hi>Ray;</hi> relating from <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Acoſta,</hi> an Earthquake in <hi>Peru,</hi> that reach'd for 160 Leagues. And <hi>Fournier</hi> gives an Account of one in <hi>Peru,</hi> that reach'd 300 Leagues along the Sea-ſhore, and 70 Leagues Inland, and levell'd the Mountains all along as it went, threw down Cities, turn'd the Rivers out of their Channels, and made an univerſal Havock and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. All this, he ſaith, was done within the ſpace of ſeven or eight Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes.</p>
               <p>Some have obſerv'd, that moſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had their Heads affected with an
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:58544:86"/>unuſual <hi>Giddineſs,</hi> before they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, or underſtood any thing of the <hi>Earthquake.</hi> The <hi>Time</hi> of it alſo may be obſerved by you of this City, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>ſecond Week</hi> in <hi>September,</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you of a former Judgment by <hi>Fire,</hi> in the <hi>first Week</hi> of that Month.</p>
               <p>Now think a little, what would have become of us, if it had laſted but a few Minutes more? How near were we to Ruine? How ſoon can God do the like again, if his Calls to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be not obeyed? And how impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible is it for all the Great Men of the World, as to cauſe ſuch a thing, ſo to hinder or prevent it, or to preſerve themſelves or us, if God ſhould thus viſit us in his Anger another time?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:58544:87"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many Examples of Terrible</hi> Earthquakes <hi>in other Parts of the World, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of late.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT hath been obſerv'd by Divers what <hi>Plato</hi> mentions in his <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus,</hi> of a vaſt Iſland without the Straits of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> called <hi>Atlantis,</hi> and bigger than <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which in one Day and Night by a violent Earthquake, and mighty Flood, and Inundation of Water, was wholly overwhelmed, and drown'd in the Sea. Earthquakes have made way for the Irruption of the Sea in divers Places. Our Iſland of
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>See Mr.</hi> Ray <hi>of the Primitive Chaos,</hi> chap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Great Britain</hi> is ſuppos'd to be broken off from the Continent in <hi>France</hi> by that means, and <hi>Sicily</hi> from <hi>Italy.</hi> Many Rivers have chang'd their Channels, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:58544:87"/>Countries have been turn'd into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts by Earthquakes. By that means the River
<note n="*" place="bottom">Purchas, <hi>out of</hi> Strabo, <hi>l.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Indus</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> that receives fifteen other Rivers into it, did change its Channel, and the neighbouring Country turn'd into a Wilderneſs. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus Siculus</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">Lib. 2.</note> mentions more than twenty thouſand <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> that periſh'd in <hi>Sparta</hi> by an Earthquake, that was of long Continuance. In the 7th Year of the Reign of <hi>Herod,</hi> by an Earthquake in
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Joſephi Antiqu. Jud. l. 15. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Judea,</hi> ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men, and a vaſt Multitude of Cattel were deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>'Tis about two thouſand and ſixty ſix Years ago, that there hapned
<note n="(*)" place="bottom">Oroſius, l. 3. c. 3. Diod. Sic. l. 15. §. 48.</note> one in <hi>Achaia,</hi> which almoſt utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it, and which was attended with Inundations, which in the very Heart of <hi>Corinth,</hi> delug'd the Cities of <hi>Helice</hi> and <hi>Buris;</hi> of which
<note n="(†)" place="bottom">Metamorphoſis, l. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Ovid</hi> makes mention:
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:58544:88"/>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Si quaeras Helicen &amp; Burin, Achaeidas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Invenies ſub aquis; &amp; adhuc oſtendere Nautae</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Inclinata ſolent cum Moenibus Oppida merſis.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He that for <hi>Helice</hi> or <hi>Buris</hi> ſeeks,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Achaean</hi> Cities, fam'd among the</l>
                        <l>Greeks,</l>
                        <l>Deep under Water ſunk, may find</l>
                        <l>'em now.</l>
                        <l>And Seamen, they that oft the Ocean</l>
                        <l>plough,</l>
                        <l>Now over lofty Towns we ſail, they</l>
                        <l>cry,</l>
                        <l>That once ſurvey'd the Secrets of</l>
                        <l>the Sky.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon</hi> in <hi>Phaenicia</hi> ſuffered exceedingly by Earthquakes, and an infinite Number of People buried un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Ruines. And <hi>Strabo</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a City, ſituate above <hi>Sidon,</hi> that was wholly ſwallowed up by an Earthquake. <hi>Twelve</hi> Cities in one
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:58544:88"/>Night in <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Lib. 1. c. 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> mentions. But S.
<note n="†" place="bottom">De <hi>Miraculis</hi> SS. l. 2. c. 3. <hi>if that Book be his.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is cited for what is more ſtrange, that in a famous Earthquake an <hi>hundred</hi> Cities of <hi>Lybia</hi> were demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Trajan</hi>'s time, the City of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och</hi> was ſwallowed up, <hi>An.</hi> 105. and a great part of <hi>Aſia</hi> with it: and ſome other Earthquakes <hi>there,</hi> I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Chap. 2. p. 76.</note> mentioned. The Terror of that in the time of the Emperor <hi>Trajan,</hi> is deſcribed by ſeveral
<note n="(*)" place="bottom">Dion. Caſſ. Trajan. §. 18.</note> Hiſtorians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 177. <hi>Smyrna</hi> in <hi>Aſia</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by an Earthquake, (as a few Years ſince it was again)
<note n="(†)" place="bottom">Euſebius.</note> towards the rebuilding whereof, the Emperour <hi>Antoninus</hi> forgave ten Years Tribute.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ammianus
<note n="(‖)" place="bottom">Lib. 17, &amp; 26.</note> Marcellinus</hi> ſpeaks of very dreadful Earthquakes that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> in the time of the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius.</hi> And of one that he ſaith was Univerſal, in the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:58544:89"/>time of the Emperour <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> And
<note n="*" place="bottom">Lib. 4. c. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Sozomen</hi> gives an Account, that <hi>An.</hi> 358. the City of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by an Earthquake, which made the Council appointed by <hi>Conſtantius</hi> to meet there, to be put off to another Year. The City of
<note n="†" place="bottom">Socrates, l. 4. c. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Nice</hi> in <hi>Bithynia</hi> was ruined, and almoſt all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants deſtroyed, twelve Years after this, ſaith <hi>Socrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An. D.</hi> 557. There was a violent Earthquake at
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Le Sieur. Agathias.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that laſted for <hi>many days;</hi> and every Hour the City ſuffered extraordinary Shocks. Many Houſes were thrown down, but the People betook themſelves to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Faſting, and Repentance; and God had Compaſſion on them: But many other Cities in the Eaſt were ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd by it. And even <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhaken; which was the more ſtrange and aſtoniſhing to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeldom happens in thoſe Parts.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:58544:89"/>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 986. there was another at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> which was ſo violent, that not only the Walls and Churches were ſhaken by it, but all
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cedrenus.</note> 
                  <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 12th Century there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the
<note n="†" place="bottom">Cent. Magdeb. cent. 12. cap. 13. de <hi>Miraculis.</hi>
                  </note> Eaſt. And in the Year 1300, which began the Turkiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, or the <hi>Ottoman Aera,
<note n="‖" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Life of Pope</hi> Boniface <hi>the</hi> 8th.</note> Platina</hi> relates ſuch an Earthquake at <hi>Rome,</hi> as the like was never before. And <hi>An.</hi> 1348. ſuch a one at
<note n="(*)" place="bottom">Aventinus.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> as endured for <hi>forty Days,</hi> and reach'd in the Extent of it to <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> twenty ſix Cities overthrown by it, Mountains torn up by the Roots; ſeveral Men, Women, and Beaſts, by that ſtrange Exhalation turn'd into Statues of Salt.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Perſia, An.</hi> 1400.
<note n="(†)" place="bottom">Herbert'<hi>s Travels,</hi> p. 120.</note> 
                  <hi>Herbert</hi> gives an account of an Earthquake, which threw down 500 Houſes in the City of <hi>Lair.</hi> And <hi>An.</hi> 1593. the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:58544:90"/>whole City (which they boaſted to conſiſt of 5000 Houſes) was ſhaken, and 3000 Houſes overthrown, and as many of the Inhabitants killed.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Azores,</hi> or French Iſlands, in the <hi>West Indies,</hi> (St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s Iſland) <hi>Linſchot</hi> mentions an Earthquake, <hi>An.</hi> 1591. that
<note n="*" place="bottom">Herbert<hi>'s Travels,</hi> p. 398.</note> endured ſhaking from <hi>July</hi> 26, unto the 12th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to the extreme Terror of the Inhabitants: Eſpecially when by force thereof, they perceived the Earth to remove from place to place; and <hi>Villa Franca,</hi> the beſt Town it had, to turn topſy-turvy: the Ships that then rode at Anchor in the Bay, trembled and quaked; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the People verily thought <hi>Doomſday</hi> was at hand, and that the Fabrick of the Univerſe was disjoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Tercera,</hi> the firſt and biggeſt of thoſe Iſlands, called the <hi>Azores,</hi> there happened a great
<note n="†" place="bottom">Mandelflo<hi>'s Travels into the</hi> Indies, <hi>added to</hi> Olea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, <hi>p.</hi> 221.</note> Earthquake, <hi>May</hi>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:58544:90"/>24. 1614. that overturn'd in the City of <hi>Agra,</hi> eleven Churches, nine Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, beſides many private Houſes. And in the City of <hi>Praya</hi> hardly an Houſe was left ſtanding. And in the Year 1628, <hi>June</hi> 16. there happened ſo horrible an one in the Iſland of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> that not far from it the Sea opened, and thruſt forth an Iſland a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a League and half in length, at a place where was above 150 Fathom Water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1581. <hi>Joſeph Acoſta</hi> relates, that in <hi>Peru</hi> there happened an Earthquake, which removed the City of <hi>Anguan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum</hi> two Leagues from the place where it ſtood, without demoliſhing it, in regard the Situation of the whole Country was chang'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1657. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> (ſaith the
<note n="*" place="bottom">Vol. 5. l. 3. Lett. 9. p. 204.</note> 
                  <hi>Turkiſh Spy</hi>) have lately felt a Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Blow in <hi>Peru;</hi> which if it be not a Mark of the Wrath of Heaven, is at leaſt a ſign that the Earth is weary of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:58544:91"/>them, eſpecially in thoſe parts, where they have ſtained it with ſo much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood. The City <hi>Lima</hi> not many Moons ago, was ſwallowed up by an Earthquake: and <hi>Calao,</hi> another City not far from it, was conſum'd by a Shower of Fire out of the Clouds. <hi>Eleven thouſand Spaniards</hi> loſt their Lives in this Calamity; and the Earth devoured an hundred Millions of Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Silver, which the Lucre of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had forc'd out of its Bowels. All the Mountains of <hi>Potoſi,</hi> from whence they dug their choiceſt Metal, were levell'd with the Plain, and no more hopes of Gold was left to their inſatiable Avarice.</p>
               <p>Concerning this City <hi>Lima</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Peru,</hi> we had a ſad Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of another Earthquake there, <hi>Octob.</hi> 20. 1687. (if it be not the ſame, and the Date miſtaken) which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the whole Town, not leaving one Houſe ſtanding; and buried ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Inhabitants under its Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines. At the ſame time <hi>Callao, Fanette,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:58544:91"/>Piſco, Chancay, los Florillos,</hi> &amp;c. moſt of them Sea-port-Towns, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by an Inundation of the Sea, which carried ſeveral Ships above three Leagues into the Country; and great numbers of People and Cattle were drown'd, there being found, when the Water fell, at one place near the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, above 5000 People dead; and every day more were found, ſo that no Account could be given of their Number. This was mentioned in the
<note n="*" place="bottom">An. 1688. Num. 2349.</note> 
                  <hi>London Gazette,</hi> and confirmed by many Merchants Letters: Tho the Damage by the Inundation was leſſen'd by another Account afterwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:58544:92"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God will yet preſerve his Church, and enlarge the Kingdom of Chriſt; tho Particular Churches and Countries may be deſtroyed. The Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Scripture-Prophecies and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, uſher'd in by great Commotions, and by</hi> Earthquakes. <hi>Some Inſtances thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>LAſtly,</hi> However God may deal with any particular Branch of the Proteſtant, Reformed Churches, as to National Judgments; yet we may hope he will gloriouſly Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his own Work, for the ſpreading, and inlarging of the Kingdom of Chriſt; and that all the <hi>Shakings of Heaven and Earth,</hi> ſhall but make way for <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of all Nations to come.</hi> God has preſerved his Church hitherto, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all Oppoſition. The Preſervation of the Venetian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:58544:92"/>for <hi>eleven</hi> or <hi>twelve hundred</hi> Years, is nothing to the Continuance and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Chriſtian Church, in the midſt of Paganiſm, Atheiſm, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſm, Deiſm, Arianiſm, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm, and all the Scoffs, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and Oppoſition of ſenſual profane Infidels. It hath born up its Head under all the Revolutions, and Changes of Countries and Nations; notwithſtanding all the Wars, and Confuſions, and Overturnings, that have been in the World. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt is <hi>an Everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and ſhall endure; he will always have a Church, and People, againſt whom <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail.</hi> Tho famous Countries and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have been deſtroyed, that made a great Figure in Hiſtory, whereof no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is now left but their very Name; and hardly ſo much of their Duſt and Aſhes, as will ſuffice to write their Names in. But <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is from above, the City of the Great King, which is built upon <hi>the Rock,</hi> doth and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:58544:93"/>ſhall indure. No Length of Time can weaken this Foundation, no Storms can ſhake it, no Earthquakes overturn it, no Waves or Floods drown it. There ever hath been, and will be, a Church of Chriſt on Earth, profeſſing ſo much Truth as is neceſſary to Salvation. He hath appointed his Ordinances, and a Miniſtry to continue to the End of the World, and promiſed his Preſence with them: He hath appointed the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of his Dying Love to be kept up, till his ſecond Coming: And therefore will always have a People, amongſt whom theſe ſhall be kept up. Tho <hi>particular Churches,</hi> in this Country, or another, may have their Riſe, Growth, and Period, as there have been parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Inundations in ſeveral Countries, notwithſtanding the Oath of God to <hi>Noah,</hi> that there ſhould not be another <hi>General Deluge:</hi> But the <hi>Truth</hi> of God endures throughout all Generations: Mount <hi>Sion</hi> abideth for ever, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be moved; and all the Promiſes of the latter Days ſhall certainly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed:
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:58544:93"/>Though I will not be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, as to the <hi>Time</hi> of thoſe things, ſo as to ground any Aſſurance concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>near</hi> Accompliſhment, or the particular Share of this Nation in them: Yet as to ſuch prophetick Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods, God will break through all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to accompliſh his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. And what the preſent Shakings, and Convulſions of the Nations round about, may iſſue in, who can tell? For never was any great Good to the Church, or any conſiderable Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion introduc'd, without great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions. And <hi>Literal Earthquakes</hi> are often taken notice to have preceded.</p>
               <p>About the Beginning of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from Popery, <hi>An.</hi> 1569, and 1570, there was <hi>one</hi> in <hi>Ferraria,</hi> which Country was lately given to the Pope, and in <hi>Portugal,</hi> whereby
<note n="*" place="bottom">P. Jovius.</note> 
                  <hi>Lisbon</hi> was ſhaken, 1500 Houſes ruined, all the Temples turn'd into Rubbiſh, the Ships ſwallowed up in the Ocean, the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:58544:94"/>River thrown out of its Channel. And the ſame Earthquake affected the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> and cauſed great Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Sea. And the like former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is obſervable before the Diviſion of the Roman Empire into ten Kingdoms, that there were <hi>frequent Earthquakes,</hi> and other Prodigies. Before <hi>Saladin</hi> attempted the Overthrow of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to ravage the Holy Land, <hi>An.</hi> 1172.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Saladinus adjecit animum ad Regni Jeroſolymitani everſionem, praevio, ut ſolet fieri, Terrae motu, quo Antiochia, Laodicea, Alapia, Caeſarea, Emiſſa, Tripo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, aliaeque Urbes ferè conciderunt. <hi>Cluverius.</hi>
                  </note> great Earthquakes preceded. <hi>Anno</hi> 1300. when the Turkiſh Empire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be conſiderable, there
<note n="†" place="bottom">Platina.</note> was ſuch an Earthquake at <hi>Rome,</hi> as the like never was before. As when the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> was to turn <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in the time of <hi>Conſtantine the Great;</hi> great Earthquakes alſo did precede: by one whereof thirteen Cities in <hi>Campania</hi> were overthrown.</p>
               <p>Great Deſigns of Providence being
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:58544:94"/>ſerv'd, and the Changes of States and Countries uſher'd in by <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> after the mention of that Terrible One in the Days of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah, Zech.</hi> 14.5. it is added, <hi>And the Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee:</hi> Or thus, <hi>And yet O Lord my God come, and all the Saints with thee.</hi> Notwithſtanding our Fears and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, without this we ſhould not ſee thy Salvation. Dr.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Jackſon<hi>'s Works,</hi> Tom. 2. Part 2. lib. 7. p. 526.</note> 
                  <hi>Jackſon</hi> thinks that <hi>Earthquakes</hi> were <hi>Emblems,</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> of that Great Change by the Miniſtry of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> our Lord's Forerunner, in the 15th Year of <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> who declared <hi>the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was at hand;</hi> when Publicans and Sinners were advanc'd, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who gloried in their Birthright, were debaſed; when poor Fiſhermen became Heads of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> greater Men in the Houſe of God, than <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> had been; while the Succeſſors of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:58544:95"/>Chief Prieſts and Doctors of the Law, were infatuated, and like Salt without Taſte or Savour. And he reckens the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 40.14. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Valley ſhall be exalted, and every Mountain and Hill ſhall be brought low,</hi> was fulfilled, and anſwered in its lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Meaning (in part at leaſt) by that <hi>Terrible Earthquake</hi> in the 6th or 7th Year of the Emperor <hi>Tiberius,</hi> which overthrew <hi>twelve</hi> famous Cities in <hi>Aſia.</hi> For among other Symptoms of it, <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Sediſſe immenſos Montes, viſa in arduo quae plana ſuerint. <hi>Tacit. Annal. lib.</hi> 2.</note> relates this for one, that <hi>the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys were exalted, and mighty Hills brought low.</hi> Before the Accompliſhment of divers Prophecies, God gives ſome Glimpſe or Hint, by ſome real Event, anſwerable to the plain literal Senſe of the Prophet, but immediate Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks of Greater Myſteries approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>He ſaith farther, that the <hi>Earthquake</hi> which happened in <hi>Jewry,</hi> while <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:58544:95"/>Ceſar,</hi> and <hi>Anthony</hi> tried their Fortunes in that great and famous Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fight at <hi>Actium,</hi> was in part an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> his literal meaning, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>Yet once, it is a little while, and I will ſhake the Heavens, and the Earth, and the Sea, and the dry Land: And I will ſhake all Nations,</hi> &amp;c. This ſhaking of the Nations, and of the Earth at that time, was a ſore Prognoſtick of that Myſtery, which the Prophet in the following Verſes foretells, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Glory of the latter Temple ſhould be greater than the Glory of the former;</hi> and that <hi>He,</hi> who was <hi>the Deſire of all Nations,</hi> and the Glory of both Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the Prince of that <hi>Peace</hi> which God had promiſed to give in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſhould ſhortly come.</hi> For about twelve Years after, <hi>Herod</hi> erects the Temple anew, and made it even for External Pomp and Ornament, more Beautiful than <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple had been; that the King of Glory, and Prince of Peace, for whoſe Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:58544:96"/>(though unwitting to <hi>Herod</hi>) it was erected, might come into it, and fill it with Glory. And within eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years after <hi>Herod</hi> began this Work, our Lord was preſented in it, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by <hi>Simeon</hi> to be <hi>the Light of the Gentiles,</hi> (or one deſired of all Nations) and <hi>the Glory of his People</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>Great Revolutions, and Changes ſometimes for the better, but more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for the worſe, have been obſerv'd to follow Earthquakes, as to Natural, Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical Affairs: Let me mention ſome Inſtances.</p>
               <p>Three Cities in
<note n="*" place="bottom">Oroſius, l. 7. c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprus</hi> fell by an Earthquake, in the time of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> followed with a great <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> In <hi>Julian</hi>'s
<note n="†" place="bottom">Sozomen, l. 6. c. 2. Theodoret, l. 4. c. 4.</note> time there were ſeveral great Earthquakes, followed with a terrible <hi>Famine</hi> at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> and in <hi>Egypt</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                     <hi>See</hi> Hottingeri Diſſert. de Terrae motu, Diſſ. 4. Quaeſt. 3. Unde Terrae motus immittantur, fintne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutti, purè naturales, an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>?</note>.</p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:58544:96"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An. D.</hi> 342. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral beneficial Laws for the People, and renewed the Privileges granted to Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers. It is obſerv'd he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd thereunto by a ſenſe of Publick Calamities: for during the War with <hi>Perſia,</hi> and about thoſe Times, great Miſchiefs had proceeded from many, and moſt Terrible
<note n="*" place="bottom">Howel<hi>'s Gen. Hiſt.</hi> Vol. 2. p. 83, 84.</note> Earthquakes. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> in his <hi>Cronicon</hi> tells us, that the Year following the Death of <hi>Conſtans</hi> the Younger, many Cities of the Eaſt fell to the Ground by an horrible Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Earth. And ſome three Years after this, that <hi>Neocaeſarea</hi> was overturn'd, and all its Inhabitants pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, except ſuch as were ſaved with the Biſhop in the Church: as alſo that the Year following this, and preceding the building of the Haven in <hi>Seleucia, Dirrachium</hi> was by an Earthquake de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed, <hi>Rome</hi> trembled for three Days, and as many Nights, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Towns of <hi>Campania</hi> were ſorely
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:58544:97"/>troubled. To theſe <hi>Cedrenus</hi> adds, that in the fourth or fifth Year of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Antioch</hi> was endangered by an Earthquake of three days continuance; that in his eighth Year <hi>Rhodes</hi> was much diſtreſſed by the ſame Accident: That when <hi>Dirrachium,</hi> the City of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> periſhed, and <hi>Rome</hi> was in ſuch Danger, twelve Cities of <hi>Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> were deſtroyed: And that in the twelfth Year of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of <hi>Berytus,</hi> the City of <hi>Phaeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> alſo miſcarried. In which Year alſo happened an Eclipſe of the Sun, on the ſixth Day of the Month <hi>Deſius.</hi> The ill Succeſs of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> in the Perſian War, was by the more Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians, according to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Parties, concluded to have happened to him, becauſe of his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to, and countenancing the Arian Hereſy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 344. In the fifth Year after the Death of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> (<hi>Marcellus</hi> and <hi>Probinus</hi> being Conſuls) a Synod was held at <hi>Antioch</hi> that condemn'd <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi>
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:58544:97"/>and only in Words profeſs'd to own the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, but really to condemn it, and ſubſtitute another in its room. This Impiety God declared againſt by
<note n="*" place="bottom">Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ. l. 2. c. 7, &amp; 10.</note> Terrible Earthquakes, ſay the Hiſtorians of that Time, eſpecially at <hi>Antioch,</hi> for above a Year together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 366. while <hi>Procopius</hi>'s Rebellion was yet but little advanc'd, <hi>July</hi> 21. in the Conſulſhip of the two Emperors, <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Valens,</hi> there hapned ſuch Horrible Earthquakes throughout the World, as neither true Hiſtorians have related the like, nor Fables them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves repreſented to us. A little after the Day dawn'd, there was a great Tempeſt of Thunder and Lightning, which was followed by ſo dreadful a Trembling of the Earth, that the Sea alſo was ſhaken therewith, and deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Shore, and its ancient Bounds for a great ſpace; and the Depth of its Channels were diſcovered; multitudes of Fiſh were ſeen to ſtick in the Mud,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:58544:98"/>and the Unequalneſs of the Seas Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom appear'd, here Hills, and there Valleys, which never had before ſeen the Sun, ſince at the Original of all things they were firſt overwhelm'd with the Floods. Many Ships were left on the dry Ground, and Swarms of People flew thither to catch Fiſh; when ſuddenly the Sea, as diſdaining to be impriſon'd, return'd to its former Place with ſuch Fury, that not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it ſelf therein, but tranſported beyond its Bounds, by the Violence of its Rage and Motion, it overturned Houſes and other Buildings innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, drowned many Thouſands of Men, and overwhelmed numbers of Ships; Great Veſſels were by the Violence of theſe Guſts blown upon the Tops of Houſes, as it happened at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and ſome near two Miles from the Shore, as <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> (who relates theſe things, <hi>lib.</hi> 26.) ſaw one himſelf
<note n="*" place="bottom">Howel's <hi>Gen. Hiſt.</hi> Vol. 2. p. 231. ad An. C. 366.</note>. This Prodigy we cannot
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:58544:98"/>take to have ſignified any thing to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copius</hi>'s Rebellion, ſo much as that Dreadful Inundation made into the Roman Empire by the Northern Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which ſhortly after happened; and the Ruin of the Weſtern Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which followed thereupon.</p>
               <p>In the Year 430, a great
<note n="*" place="bottom">Triceſimo deinde Anno <hi>Theodoſii,</hi> Terrae motus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti ſunt ingentes per menſes aliquot integros, <hi>maxima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Praenuntii Mutationum,</hi> quibus Reſpublica tum Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica, tum Mundana mox laboravit, ac tantum non occidit. Romanum tum Praeſulatum accepit <hi>Lea,</hi> qui primus in omnes totius Orbis Chriſtiani Epiſcopos do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum, ſibi aliquem, ut Privilegio Petro dato, coepit arrogare. <hi>Cluverius,</hi> p. 322.</note> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake preceded the Death of one of the beſt Emperors, <hi>viz. Theodoſius,</hi> as the Fore-runner of Great Changes. Some
<note n="†" place="bottom">Howel<hi>'s Hiſt.</hi> p. 673.</note> think this the ſame with that <hi>An.</hi> 446. which <hi>Marcellinus</hi> writes to have happened in the Confulſhip of <hi>Aelius</hi> and <hi>Sepronius:</hi> which raged in many places, and therein overturned many Cities; the Wall of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> tho but new built, it threw to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:58544:99"/>the Ground, with fifty ſeven Turrets: Stones of great Bulk, lately plac'd in the Building of the <hi>Forum</hi> of <hi>Taurus,</hi> fell down. Many Towns were rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and a Peſtilent Vapour aroſe, which cauſed a <hi>Plague;</hi> and this join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a <hi>Famine,</hi> deſtroyed many Thouſands. The Civil Motions and Ruptures in the Roman Empire, were agreeable hereunto.</p>
               <p>This Earthquake in the Reign of <hi>Theodoſius, Evagrius</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Lib. 1. cap. 17.</note> ſaith was the Greateſt, and moſt memorable of all others: Such as by its Greatneſs ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>inconſiderable</hi> all that went before it. It afflicted, he had almoſt ſaid, the whole World. The Earth gaped, and ſwallowed many Villages, beſides many other, nay innumerable Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties both by Sea and Land. Some Fountains were dried up; in other Places Water in great quantity broke out, where formerly it had not been known: Great Trees were torn up by
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:58544:99"/>the Roots: Heaps of Earth were ſo ſhaken together, that they were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into Mountains. The Sea caſt forth dead Fiſhes: In it many Iſlands were overwhelmed and ſunk: Ships ſailing in the Sea, by a ſudden Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Water, were left on dry Ground. In concluſion, many Places of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> and both the <hi>Phrygia</hi>'s were grievouſly diſtreſs'd. This Diſaſter a long time and ſorely afflicted the World.
<note n="*" place="bottom">Lib. 14. cap. 46.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> writes, that it continued ſix Months, and that in a manner without Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; that it reached <hi>Alexandria,</hi> but eſpecially afflicted <hi>Antioch.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Countries mentioned by <hi>Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grius,</hi> it invaded the greateſt part of the <hi>East,</hi> and ſpared not many Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>West.</hi> He adds, that the People of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> not daring to ſtay in the City, for fear of the fall of Houſes, continued together with the Emperour, and <hi>Proclus</hi> their Patriarch,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:58544:100"/>in the Fields, inſtant in Prayer for the removal of ſo heavy a Judgment.— <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> when delivered from the Danger of the Earthquake, preſently betook himſelf to repair the Walls of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When
<note n="*" place="bottom">Theodoret, <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was baniſh'd, in the beginning of the fifth Century, by the Emperour <hi>Arcadius,</hi> from the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the ſame Night was a great Earthquake that ſhook the Emperor's Palace, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Ruine of it; on which Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers were ſent to recal him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 458. <hi>Evagrius</hi> writes of a great
<note n="†" place="bottom">Howel<hi>'s Hiſt.</hi> p. 202.</note> Earthquake that happened at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> which the Citizens had ſad cauſe to remember. Before it began, ſome of the Inhabitants were ſeized with an extraordinary <hi>Madneſs,</hi> ſuch as ſeemed to exceed all Ferity of wild Beaſts, and to be the Prelude to that Calamity which followed on the fourth Day of
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:58544:100"/>the Month <hi>Gorpiaeus,</hi> which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans call <hi>September,</hi> about the fourth Hour of the Night, and the fifty ſixth Year of the Life of <hi>Leo.</hi> It overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed almoſt all the Buildings of the new City, which was well peopled, and none of it forſaken or empty, being curiouſly built by the Magnificence of Emperours, who ſtrove to exceed each other in the Adornment of it. The firſt and ſecond Fabricks in the Palace were alſo caſt down, the reſt ſtanding, together with a Bath; which having formerly been neglected, now when by the Earthquake the reſt were choaked up, ſtood the Citizens in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good ſtead. Many other Damages of this Earthquake are there mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (with ſome Differences as to Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology) and the Diſorder of publick Matters, as the Murder of <hi>Majoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> joint Emperour in the Weſt with <hi>Leo</hi> in the Eaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An. D.</hi> 557. There was a violent Earthquake, with great Noiſes and Tempeſts, at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:58544:101"/>in
<note n="*" place="bottom">Agathias, <hi>who continued the Hiſtory of</hi> Procopius.</note> 
                  <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s time, followed the next Year with a great Plague at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi> The Earthquake which ſhook that City three Years before, laſted forty Days, and deſtroyed many Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Eaſt.</p>
               <p>In the Year 648, before the
<note n="†" place="bottom">Cent. Magdeburg. cent. 7. c. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi> overrun <hi>Africa,</hi> there were many great Earthquakes in the time of the Emperor <hi>Conſtans.</hi> The like
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Ingruentium Maloru praenuncius. <hi>Cluver.</hi> p. 350, 406.</note> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes followed with great Calamities in the Eaſt, were obſerv'd, <hi>An.</hi> 679.</p>
               <p>In the Year 740, was another at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which alſo deſtroyed many Cities of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and laſted above a Twelve-month. This was thought to
<note n="(*)" place="bottom">Cent. Magdeb. cent. 8. c. 13. Cluver. p. 358.</note> forebode the Death of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Leo,</hi> the Loſs of <hi>Artabaſdus,</hi> and the Conqueſt of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which ſoon after followed.</p>
               <p>In the Year 791, in the time of the Empreſs <hi>Irené,</hi> a great Favourer and
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:58544:101"/>Patroneſs of Image-Worſhip, was
<note n="*" place="bottom">Hoſpinian de orig. Templorum. l. 2. c. 16.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother violent Earthquake at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1077, the Earthquake on the 6th of <hi>April,</hi> in the 15th Year of the Reign of King <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, was followed by many Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, ſay <hi>Matthew Paris, Speed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1088, the Earthquake in the time of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> or <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> was followed with ſuch unſeaſonable Weather, that there was no Seeds-time till <hi>December.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1298, the Earthquake at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the time of
<note n="†" place="bottom">Inſtabat nimirum ferale ſeculum, quo ſolvendus e carcere Satanas, ſurſum deorſum omnia volutare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitabat. <hi>Cluver.</hi> p. 497.</note> 
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> (who fainted away for fear, and afterwards publiſh'd a <hi>Jubilee</hi>) was followed with many Calamities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1509. On the 14th of <hi>September</hi> there happened a terrible Earthquake at
<note n="‖" place="bottom">Knolles<hi>'s Turkiſh Hiſtory.</hi> Bajazet <hi>the</hi> Second.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:58544:102"/>Country thereabouts, in the time of <hi>Bajazet</hi> the <hi>Second;</hi> by the violence whereof, a great part of the Walls of that Imperial City, with many ſtately Buildings, both publick and private, were overthrown, and thirteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand People overwhelmed and ſlain. The Terror thereof was ſo great, that the People generally forſook their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and lay abroad in the Fields: Yea, <hi>Bajazet</hi> himſelf, then very aged and ſore troubled with the Gout, for fear thereof, went from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to <hi>Adrianople;</hi> but finding himſelf in no more ſafety there than before, he left the City, and lay abroad in the Fields in his Tent. This Earthquake endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſpace of eighteen Days; or, as the Turks Hiſtories relate, for a Month, with little Intermiſſion. Which was then accounted ominous, as por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the miſerable Calamities which afterwards happened in the Ottoman Family.</p>
               <p>After this Earthquake enſued a great Plague; where with the City was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:58544:102"/>viſited, and for the moſt part unpeopl'd. But when the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake ceas'd, and the Mortality was aſſwaged, <hi>Bajazet</hi> cauſed the Imperial City to be repaired with all ſpeed, and employed eighty thouſand Men about it; who, in the ſpace of four Months, in a moſt beautiful Manner, repaired the Ruins of that great City.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1510. The late Wars of the French in <hi>Savoy,</hi> were thought to be foreſhewn by many Prodigies, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe preceded by an Earthquake in <hi>Apulia,</hi> whereby more than ſixteen thouſand Perſons were overwhelm'd; after which enſued the War, which devoured more than a Million of Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1631. The like terrible Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in <hi>February,</hi> was in, and about the City of <hi>Naples,</hi> before the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Troubles there: which did ſuch Miſchief as to Houſes, Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Cattel, as can't be expreſs'd.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1590. The Election of Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the <hi>Seventh,</hi> was ſignalized by an Earthquake, which made <hi>Auſtria,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:58544:103"/>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Moravia</hi> to tremble, and was followed by an extraordinary Drought. <hi>Gregory</hi> XIV. quickly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, and died in ten Months. There was ſuch a <hi>Famine</hi> and <hi>Plague</hi> in
<note n="*" place="bottom">Cluverius, <hi>citing</hi> Thuanus.</note> 
                  <hi>Italy</hi> that Year, that above 60000 died.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning the</hi> Fear <hi>of Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the Regulation of it. What</hi> Fear of Evil <hi>God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and we may expect to be delivered from, and what not. Counſels proper to obtain an Intereſt in thoſe Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and to experience the fulfilling of them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter all theſe Examples of terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earthquakes, which may make us tremble, it may be proper to add ſomething to regulate our <hi>Fears</hi> of Divine Judgments, and to eſtabliſh our Hearts under the doubtful Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:58544:103"/>of what God will do againſt us. There is a <hi>natural Fear</hi> of approaching Evil, which we muſt not expect to be delivered from, nor is it poſſible we ſhould. There is alſo a Fear of <hi>prudent Caution,</hi> that may help us to ſuppoſe, and provide againſt the worſt that may happen: This we are obliged to, as oppoſite to <hi>Security:</hi> This will make us flee to <hi>God</hi> as our <hi>Refuge,</hi> and <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-place.</hi> Neither muſt we expect to be delivered from the Fear of all temporal Evils; conſidering what our preſent State in this World is, and what is ſutable for ſuch imperfect ſinful Souls, who muſt have Matter of Mourning, while there are ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of Sin: Eſpecially being in the Condition of <hi>Strangers,</hi> in a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Country, and in the midſt of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; and who have this preſent World to be ſaved from, and the Love of the World to be mortified; and who muſt expect to be treated as the Followers of a <hi>Crucified Saviour;</hi> and ſo to be conformed to him, our Head,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:58544:104"/>in Suffering, or in Reſolution and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs for it. Therefore, though it be true, that if our Hearts are fixed on God, we need not be <hi>afraid of evil Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings;</hi> and God has promiſed to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us from anxious, tormenting Fears: Yet ſo much Fear of Evil as is needful to drive us to God, by Prayer, Dependance and Truſt, we muſt not expect to be delivered from; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as we are Members of a defiled, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Church; or live in a City, or Country, where are many whoſe Sins call for Judgment; whom God does puniſh in this World. We may not think in ſuch a Caſe, that we ſhall be quiet from all Fear of Evil, eſpecially if we our ſelves have (as doubtleſs we all have) contributed our own ſhare to the common Guilt.</p>
               <p>But ſuch as fear the Lord, may hope to be delivered from <hi>the Fear of Evil;</hi> ſo as it ſhall not overwhelm their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and deſtroy their Confidence and Hope in God, weaken their Hands in preſent Duty, and take away the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:58544:104"/>of their preſent Mercies, or would deſpirit and diſtract them. Such a Fear of Evil is threatned as a Puniſhment, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.64. <hi>Job</hi> 15.21. <hi>Job</hi> 18.5. <hi>Terrors ſhall make him afraid on every ſide, and ſhall drive him to his Feet. Thou ſhalt be afraid to go forth into the Field, or to walk by the Way: for the Sword of the Enemy, and Fear is on every ſide.</hi> Jer. 6.25. chap. 20.2. chap. 49.29. <hi>They ſhall cry unto one another, and uſe this Expreſſion,</hi> FEAR IS ON EVERY SIDE. That is; <q>We know not what to do, or what to expect; whither to go, or what Courſe to take; what Counſel to follow, or what Evil next to look for; or how far it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, or when or where it will iſſue.</q> The like Inſtance ſee, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.2.</p>
               <p>God promiſes his People, that they ſhall be <hi>kept in Peace,</hi> ſhall <hi>ſleep in Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et,</hi> ſhall <hi>dwell in Safety,</hi> Pſal. 4. laſt. Prov. 3.24, 25, 26. <hi>When thou lieſt down, thou ſhalt not be afraid: Yea, thou ſhalt lie down, and thy Sleep ſhall be ſweet. Be not afraid of ſudden Fear, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:58544:105"/>of the Deſolation of the Wicked, when it cometh: For the Lord ſhall be thy Confidence, and ſhall keep thy Foot from being taken,</hi> Job 11.18, 19. Pſal. 112.7, 8. God promiſeth us Quiet, Peace and Safety, from the <hi>real Hurt</hi> of temporal Evil; and from the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Afflictions themſelves, if that be <hi>beſt;</hi> and from ſuch a Fear of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Judgment and Calamity, as the Wicked are puniſhed with.</p>
               <p>If you would be intereſted in theſe Promiſes, and experience the fulfilling of 'em, ſtudy much <hi>the Covenant of Grace,</hi> and God's unchangeable Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to it. This is the Ground of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the worſt times, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.1. <hi>Fear not, for I am with thee; be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, for I am thy God. He hath made with me an everlaſting Covenant, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all things and ſure. This is all my Deſire, and all my Salvation,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.5. <q>I now need nothing more, I fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, I am ſolicitous for nothing. Let God build up or pull down, ſave or deſtroy; prolong, or ſhorten my
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:58544:105"/>Life; do what he will with me and mine, he is my God in Covenant.</q> This made the Pſalmiſt triumph in Faith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.6. <hi>The Lord is on my ſide, I will not fear: God is our Refuge and Strength, we will not be afraid, though the Earth be moved, and the Pillars there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be ſhaken,</hi> Pſal. 46. beginning; <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bak.</hi> 3.17. <q>I am not afraid of what Man can do, I am not afraid of what God will do, or what I ſhall do, or the Nation do. By this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That <hi>He is my God,</hi> I can anſwer all my Fears: By this I know my great Intereſt is ſecure, my Treaſure is ſafe, my principal Concern is out of danger. He is my God in <hi>an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant;</hi> He will not leave till he bring me to Glory: If my Body periſh by an Earthquake, my Soul ſhall aſcend to Heaven. The Noiſe of Wars, and Rumours of Wars, ſhall not break my Reſt, for I have <hi>Peace with God through Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q> Study there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Covenant of Grace, and the Promiſes of it; and believe the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſs
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:58544:106"/>of God, and his Power, Truth and Goodneſs, to make them good.</p>
               <p>And in order to your advantage, by the Conſideration of <hi>God</hi> as in <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> labour to ſtrengthen and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your <hi>Faith,</hi> that you may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to apply all the Promiſes of the Covenant for your Comfort. If we did heartily aſſent to the Truth of the Promiſes, and had a realizing View of what God is, and can be, and do, for all that fear and truſt him; and did more entirely yield, and devote our ſelves to him, as our Lord and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, our God and Portion, to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned and diſpoſed of according to the Tenor of his Covenant, (all which is implied in Faith) this would relieve us againſt a thouſand Fears: This would make it evident to our ſelves, that let our Dangers be what they will, we are ſafe in the Hands of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and a good God: All Events are under his Management, and ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his Counſel. Our Dangers
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:58544:106"/>ſhall reach no further, riſe no higher, laſt no longer, than to ſerve his glorious Purpoſes.</p>
               <p>Accordingly we read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.7. compared with the 15th <hi>Verſe,</hi> that in Caſes of Danger, <hi>our Strength is to ſit ſtill.</hi> Not in oppoſition to the uſe of <hi>Means</hi> for our Safety, for that is the <hi>Duty</hi> of every Man in his place: But in oppoſition to Reliance on any other Help than God; as an Expreſſion of Faith in God, deſcribed at the 15th <hi>Verſe: In Returning, and in Reſt ſhall you be ſaved; in Quietneſs, and in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence ſhall be your Strength.</hi> Waiting on God in the way of our Duty, ſo far as we know it, in expectation of what God ſhall pleaſe to do for, or againſt us.</p>
               <p>You ought alſo to recollect, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>former Experiences,</hi> to ſilence diſtruſtful Fears. <hi>The Lord is my Strength and my Shield, my Heart truſted in him, and I was helped,</hi> Pſal. 28.7. <hi>Experience worketh Hope;</hi> and that which aſſiſteth our <hi>Hope,</hi> muſt needs ſcatter our <hi>Fears.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:58544:107"/>
               <p>Endeavour alſo to mortify the Love of this World, and of Life it ſelf; and look to your Integrity and Upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart: This will make you as <hi>a Brazen-Wall, and an Iron-Pillar:</hi> Whereas an Hypocrite will be afraid of every Shadow. No wonder if <hi>the Sinners in</hi> Sion <hi>are afraid, and Fear ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizeth the Hypocrite,</hi> while <hi>the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are as bold as a Lion.</hi> It is therefore good Advice of <hi>Zophar</hi> unto <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 11.14, 15. <hi>If Iniquity be in thy Hands, put it far from thee, and let not Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs dwell in thy Tabernacle.</hi> And then it follows, <hi>Thou ſhalt lift up thy Face without Spot; yea, thou ſhalt be ſtedfaſt, and thou ſhalt not fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reſign and give up your ſelves, and all you have, into the Hands of God. Commit the keeping of <hi>your Souls,</hi> and the keeping of <hi>the Nation,</hi> and of <hi>the City,</hi> and of <hi>your Families,</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> and <hi>Relations,</hi> into the Hands of God, as of <hi>a faithul Creator and Preſerver,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. Leave all to his Care, reſolving to be ſatisfied, and pleaſed
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:58544:107"/>with his holy Will. We ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of loſing that by <hi>Violence,</hi> which we have <hi>voluntarily</hi> given up into the Hands of God.</p>
               <p>But eſpecially let us give up our ſelves, by renewing our <hi>Covenant,</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitently and ſeriouſly, at the Table of the Lord. See that there be no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy between God and you, while he hath a Controverſy with the Nation in general. Renew <hi>Repentance</hi> for paſt Backſlidings, that your Peace may be made with Heaven; that <hi>God may not be your Terror, in a Day of evil:</hi> For nothing will ſo much take away the Heart, abate the Courage, the Vigor, and Firmneſs of your Spirits, as the Jealouſy and Miſgivings of a guilty Conſcience. If you cannot look up to God with Comfort, if you cannot lift up your Eyes to Heaven with Hope, to what Refuge will you flee in a Day of Evil?</p>
               <p>This is the great Counſel I would give, and take, as <hi>the beſt Preparation,</hi> for whatſoever ſhould come to paſs.
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:58544:108"/>For what can daunt the Courage of that Man, or Woman, who can ſay, <hi>This God is my God for ever; This Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who hath all Power in Heaven and in Earth, is my Saviour and my Lord, and the Lord of all this World?</hi> An up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Chriſtian, with <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> was never a <hi>Coward,</hi> and never can be. But if we live at Uncertainties about our Spiritual State, if our Backſlidings be many, our Corruptions ſtrong, and our Evidences blotted; we muſt needs be afraid of publick Changes, and threatned Calamities, becauſe we are <hi>afraid to die.</hi> Shall I mind you how ſad the Caſe of <hi>Saul</hi> was, when he cries out, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.15. <hi>I am ſore diſtreſſed, for the Philiſtines make War againſt me, and God is departed from me, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers me no more?</hi> How miſerable is their Caſe, who, in a time of Trouble, cannot eaſe their Hearts by Prayer to God? who, in a time of Danger, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not look to the End and Iſſue of Things with Comfort? who have no Anchor to drop in a Storm? The Difference
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:58544:108"/>is unſpeakably great, at ſuch a time, between the one ſort and the other: For while <hi>the Wicked is driven away in his Wickedneſs,</hi> and hurried by Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Sufferings into Eternal Ones, <hi>the Righteous hath Hope in his Death,</hi> Prov. 14.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Security <hi>a Preſage of Temporal and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ruine, to particular Perſons, whatever God may do as to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>LAſtly;</hi> Whatever God may in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty</hi> do in ſparing this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and how well ſoever he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for thoſe who are upright before him; yet, as to particular Perſons, who are not at peace with God, it is moſt <hi>certain,</hi> that <hi>Security is a Preſage of Ruine;</hi> that ſudden Deſtruction ſhall overtake them, as Travail on a Woman with Child. When the ſlothful and
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:58544:109"/>wicked Servant thinks, and ſays in his Heart, that his Lord doth delay his Coming; <hi>He will come and cut him in ſunder, in a Day that he looked not for, and in an Hour that he was not aware of, Matth.</hi> 24.55. When the rich Fool in the Parable ſaid, <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe;</hi> the next News we hear of him is, that the Pillow is plucked from under his Head, and he is caſt into <hi>Hell.</hi> When, notwithſtanding all the Warnings of God by his Word and Providence, Men will <hi>bleſs themſelves in their Hearts,</hi> and ſay, <hi>I ſhall have Peace, though I walk in the Imagination of my Heart,</hi> Deut. 29.19, 20. <hi>The Lord will not ſpare ſuch a Man, but the Anger of the Lord, and his Jealouſy ſhall ſmoak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and all the Curſes that are written in this Book ſhall lie upon him,</hi> and <hi>the Lord ſhall blot out his Name from under Heaven.</hi> Therefore let Men take heed how they arrogantly boaſt themſelves in their Wickedneſs, leſt God ſingle them out unto ſome ſignal Vengeance in <hi>this World,</hi> to
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:58544:109"/>make them <hi>Examples</hi> to thoſe who ſhall afterwards live ungodly. If they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not a Judgment to come, to put the evil Day far from them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all the Fore-runners of Judgment in this World; yet they may <hi>ſuddenly</hi> be ſurprized in their Security, and they are every Moment liable to a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Arreſt of Judgment, againſt which they have no Relief.</p>
               <p>They are under Condemnation, they are yet in their Sins; and therefore to ſuch I muſt ſay, <hi>Except you repent,</hi> (ſpeedily, and heartily repent) <hi>you muſt periſh.</hi> For tho God be loth to ſtrike, and inclined to Pity, and willing to ſpare; tho he be ſlow to Anger, and ready to forgive; Yet the Day of his Vengeance is at hand, when he ſhall put on Fury like a Garment; when his Eye ſhall not pity, nor his Hand ſpare; when he ſhall laugh at your Calamity, and mock when your Fear cometh. <hi>Now,</hi> O fooliſh delaying Sinner, that goeſt on in Sin! the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Mercy of God pleads for
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:58544:110"/>thee againſt his Juſtice, and he would lead thee to <hi>Repentance</hi> by his Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering; his Bowels yearn over thee, and he would fain overcome thee by his Love, and conquer thee by his Grace: But the Day is haſtning, when there ſhall never be a Word ſpoke for thee by the Mercy of God more; when, becauſe he ſtretched out his Hand, and thou regardeſt not, thou wouldſt not hear his Voice, or know the Day of thy Viſitation, he ſhall condemn thee without Pity, and ſend thee to Hell, without any ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Language as he uſed to his ancient People, <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, Ephraim?</hi> The Voice of Mercy ſhall then ceaſe, and plead for thee no more: <hi>He that made thee, will ſhew thee no Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; He that formed thee, will ſhew thee no Favour.</hi> He would <hi>Now</hi> delight in thee, and rejoice over thee to do thee Good, and therefore beſeecheth thee to have Pity on thy ſelf: But <hi>Then</hi> he will delight in the Glory of his provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Juſtice; becauſe thou wouldſt not
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:58544:110"/>be perſwaded to Accept of his Mercy while it might be had. Think of it, and Tremble, all ye that go on in Sin, and hate to be Reformed!</p>
               <p>Whatever become of the Nation, if National Judgments do not overtake you, you cannot be long out of the <hi>Grave,</hi> or out of <hi>Hell.</hi> You are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Damnation</hi> every Hour: And <hi>tho Sentence against an evil Work is not ſpeedily executed, tho a Sinner do Evil an hundred times, and his Days be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed; Yet ſurely I know it ſhall not be well with the Wicked,</hi> Eccl. 8.11, 12, 13. Chriſt hath told you again and again, that ſuch as you can <hi>never</hi> be Saved. It is the Word of the Living God, that ſuch and ſuch Perſons as you know your ſelves to be, ſhall never enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven. It is a Truth founded on ſuch Principles, that the Contrary is impoſſible.</p>
               <p>And yet to convince Men of this as to their own State and Condition, there's the <hi>Difficulty.</hi> For if you will not believe God and Chriſt, how ſhall
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:58544:111"/>I expect you ſhould believe me? Alas! you will not conſider your Caſe for one ſerious Hour: We can hardly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail ſo far, as to bring you to compare your ſelves with the Word; and your own Character with the Deſcription of ſuch as ſhall periſh. You will put it to the <hi>venture,</hi> and a bold Venture it is: For if no Miniſter in the World ſhould tell you, That <hi>except you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, you muſt periſh;</hi> yea, if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſhould tell you the <hi>contrary</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, it will not make the Word of God of none Effect, or your Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation the leſs Certain.</p>
               <p>You may make a ſhift for a little time to drown the Voice of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or ſtop its Mouth; to lay aſide the Thoughts of Death, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an everlaſting Hell; to ſpeak Peace to your ſelves, againſt the expreſs Word of God: But if you are not Renewed and Sanctified; if you do not truly Repent, ſo as to hate Sin, and leave it, and turn to the Lord; if you do not unfeignedly give up your
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:58544:111"/>ſelves to God in Chriſt, as your Saviour, and Soveraign, in the Method of the Goſpel; your Judgment is near, your Deſtruction is at hand, <hi>you muſt Periſh;</hi> and that <hi>more dreadfully,</hi> than moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the World: For your Light, your Knowledg, your Means, your Mercies, your Calls, your Warnings, your Examples, are more and greater than others. Divine Patience will not laſt always. <hi>The Lord is not ſlack</hi> (as Men count Slackneſs) <hi>concerning the Promiſe of his Coming, but is long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to usward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. But if <hi>they turn not, he will whet his Sword; he hath bent his Bow, and made it ready; he hath prepared alſo Inſtruments of Death,</hi> Pſal. 7.12, 13. Tho there are in God Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Goodneſs, and Forbearance, yet if you <hi>deſpiſe the Riches of his Goodneſs, not knowing that the Goodneſs of God leads to Repentance,</hi> you do but <hi>treaſure up to your ſelves Wrath against the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:58544:112"/>Judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2.4, 5.</p>
               <p>It is dreadful to periſh as to a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Ruine, by Wars, and Fires, and Earthquakes, and ſuch Calamities: But how much ſadder is it to think of deſcending into the Place of Remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Torment, under the everlaſting Curſe of God, to be tormented with the Devil and his Angels! It is ſad to hear of this, ſad to foreſee it, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, to think of it; but it will be much ſadder to ſuffer, and to feel it. And be not deceived, it is not the <hi>leſs Certain,</hi> becauſe it is yet <hi>Future.</hi> You are now alive, and do not ſee the Grave digged for you, and yet you <hi>muſt die:</hi> And as certainly do I know from the Word of God, who cannot lie, That <hi>except you Repent, you muſt Periſh,</hi> and that <hi>for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:58544:112"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Abraham Chandler <hi>in</hi> Alderſgate-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>THE Mourner's Companion, or Funeral-Diſcourſes on ſeveral Texts.</p>
            <p>Death a Deliverance; In a Funeral-Diſcourſe preached in part on the Deceaſe of Mrs. <hi>Mary Doolittle,</hi> late Wife of Mr. <hi>Thomas Doolittle,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Sacramental Diſcourſes on ſeveral Texts, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and After the Lord's Supper; Together with a Paraphraſe on the Lord's Prayer.</p>
            <p>All three by Mr. <hi>John Shower.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> John Salusbury <hi>at the Riſing Sun in</hi> Cornhill.</head>
            <p>THE Harmony of the Divine Attributes in the Contrivance and Accompliſhment of Man's Redemption by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>William Bates</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Changeableneſs of this World with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Nations, Families, and particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: With a practical Application thereof to the various Conditions of this mortal Life. By <hi>Timothy Rogers</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>A Mirror for Atheiſts; being ſome Paſſages of the Life and Death of the Right Honourable
<pb facs="tcp:58544:113"/>
               <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Rocheſter;</hi> written by his own Direction on his Death-bed. By <hi>Gilbert Burnet,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An End of Doctrinal Controverſies which have lately troubled the Churches. By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Certainty of the Worlds of Spirits, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evinced by unqueſtionable Hiſtories of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions and Witchcrafts, Voices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> proving the Immortality of Souls. By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proteſtant Religion truly ſtated and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, by the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> prepared for the Preſs ſome time before his Death. Whereunto is added ſome Account of the learned Author; by Mr. <hi>Daniel Williams,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Matthew Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chriſtian's Converſe with God, or the Inſufficiency of humane Friendſhip, and the Improvements of Solitude in Converſe with God; with ſome of the Author's Breathings after him. By <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi> Recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Reader's ſerious Thoughts when at the Houſe of Mourning, and in Retirement. By Mr. <hi>Matthew Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Mourner's Memorial, in two Sermons on the Death of the truly pious Mrs. <hi>Suſanna Soame:</hi> With ſome Account of her Life and Death, by <hi>Timothy Wright</hi> and <hi>Robert Fleming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Works of <hi>Iſaac Ambroſe.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58544:113"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
